Hello and welcome to the tenth week of CSI 533. This video and one introduce our week's topic,
where we're going to pivot from regression to classifications where learning outcomes for this
week are for you to be able to predict binary outcomes or classes for observed instances to
evaluate the accuracy of a model for doing this classification and also to use psychic learn
for predictive modeling in addition to the stats models code that we've been using so far.
So if we think about our different outcome variables,
we talked at the beginning of the class about different types of variables and that applies to outcomes as well as all the other variables.
What we saw in the last couple of weeks is using is trying to predict continuous outcome variables and we call this regression.
It also applies to other numeric outcome variables like integers,
but regressions where we're trying to we're trying to predict these continuous numeric outcome variables.
We're trying to predict a categorical variable. We typically call it classification.
And if we have a two level category or a two level ordinal,
we call this binary classification because our goal is to classify instances into one of two different categories.
There's also methods for dealing with multi-level ordinals, which are called ordinal regression.
And if you have multi-level categorically, you have more than two categories.
Then you then we have what we call multiclass classification.
We're going to be focusing, particularly for now, on binary classification, where we have a yes or no outcome that we're trying to predict.
We call it yes, no positive, negative, true, false. We could call it a B. if we don't want to assign positive value to one.
But our usual classification setup is going to be to estimate. Is this in the positive class?
Sometimes we'll simplify another problem to a binary problems. We can apply a classification, for example, in the Rotten Tomatoes data.
We may say we want to we want to classify movies as mostly fresh.
If they have a percent fresh, greater than 50 percent or some other threshold.
You might say categorized a rating as positive if it's greater than three or greater than or equal to three other ways in which we
will sometimes take outcomes that are richer than a binary class and convert them into one for the purposes of using a classifier.
Now, to relate this to the inference that we saw back in the fourth week.
So if we've got two different groups or two different classes here,
an inference that we saw is looking at what what is different about these two groups?
One's in a basket. One's on stairs. One's kittens. One's puppies.
We use things like T tests, other pair Y or other tests to look at the difference between two groups.
But our goal is to understand the groups and their relationships. That's what we're doing with inference.
Just like with with inference in the regression context,
trying to understand the structure of the space and what drives changes with classification, which is a type of prediction.
What we're trying to do is we're given a new animal. We're trying to figure out which group it goes in.
So inference is, given these groups of animals, what makes them different classification is given a new animal.
Is it a cat or a dog? Now we're assuming everything is cats or dogs for now.
If you bring in a rabbit or a ferret or a durable classifier, it's going to have a hard time.
But. The got the idea here is that the classification is trying to figure out which group it belongs in,
whereas in France is trying to figure out what is the differences between the groups.
These are gonna be very related because the differences between the groups are the basis for figuring out which group something belongs in.
But the outcome is different. And the way we assess what we're doing is different classification, as with prediction.
We assess on the basis of its ability to correctly predict or classify future unseen data.
So we often encode our binary classes in zero one where one is the positive class.
If you use a logical value, if you use a logical and pandas, it will automatically convert to an integer zero one where one is true.
And remember that when we have a vector or a series of zero ones, then if you can take you take the mean of that,
you get the fraction of trews or the estimated probability of true.
It's the probability of drawing an item from your data and it being true.
But also, if your data is a reasonable as a as a representative sample, it is a estimate of the probability of data being true.
When you drop in the population so we can think about taking the mean of why for some fixed X.
So when we're doing a regression, what we do is we compute the the the expected y the expected outcome variable
for some fixed X regression is gonna find an estimate of the mean outcome.
And if the regression properly captures the the what's going on in the data, then the output of the regression is going to be the mean outcome.
Because remember, our residuals are normally distributed. Heteros, you're homeless, get ascetics centered at zero.
So everywhere along of everywhere along your line, the mean zero, which means that the the lie is the mean residual zero,
which means that the line is the expected value of the outcome variable for that particular value of X.
What we do here, well, we often do here as we try to compute the conditional probability.
What's the probability of Y being true, given a particular value of X?
So it's gonna have this relationship there to regression. In both cases, we're trying to compute the dis expectation or this probability.
Fun sidebar fact probability is the expected value of the characteristic function where the characteristic function is one.
If something is true and zero if it's false. But we're trying to compute this conditional probability, which we as a which.
Conclusion to this we can also frame as a continuant, as a conditional expectation.
So to wrap up classification allows us to predict discrete outcome variables.
There are many different models for doing this. We're gonna start with linear ones as we were using for regression.