Hello. This video, I want to introduce the concept of odds and log odds,
learning outcomes are to be able to convert between probability odds and log odds
and understand the role and the purpose of the logistic and logic functions.
So if we have a probability of success. Probability is not the only way to quantify a probability.
We can also quantify it. And what's her called? The odds. So if you've heard of odds of like ten to one against odds of two to one.
This is what it's talking about. So if we have a probability of success.
And remember, this is going to be in the range zero less than or equal.
So probability is going to be in the range zero to one.
We can't actually have probabilities of zero and one when we're talking about odds four.
I'll get to that in a moment, but the odds is the probability of success.
Divided by the probability of failure or the probability of success, divided by the probability of one minus success.
And it gives us this ratio of the likelihood of one outcome versus the other.
And how much it expresses odds expresses how much more likely.
Success is than failure or failure is then success if we're quantifying the odds of failure.
So a couple of examples. Star Wars robots.
A couple of them talk differently, some in some in probability and some odds.
K2 Esso says there's a ninety seven point six percent chance of failure.
So our probability of failure is ninety seven point six. Point nine, seven, six.
And so our odds are point nine seven six divided by pointing to four.
Which is equal to forty point six seven. So we affect it.
We approximately have a forty one to one odds. The odds against success are the odds of failure are forty one to one.
That if we're going to translate this ninety seven point six percent chance into OD's, we can also translate the other way around.
See through Apio is being a little imprecise in his speech.
He should say the odds. The odds against successfully navigating an asteroid field.
But he says the possibility of successfully navigating will forgive him because he's talking about a ratio 37 20 to one.
He's clearly talking about odds. And so if the odds are thirty seven, twenty over one, that's equal to P. over one minus P.
If we solve that equation, what we're going to get is that the probability of failure, if we converting this odds of thirty seven,
twenty to one, that we get a probability of failure of point nine nine nine seven or ninety nine point nine seven.
And so we can convert back and forth between probability and odds.
So long as our probability is not zero or one, we can't.
If probability is zero, then the odds will be zero.
But if the probability is one, then the probability of failure will be zero.
And so the odds will be infinite. Another thing about odds is that P is equal to zero point five, then odds is equal to one.
So one is even odds. Just as likely as it is unlikely.
Now, hopefully you may remember from high school algebra, logarithms and logarithms allow us to convert between exponents and.
In normal numbers, and so if X is the log base B of Y, that means Y is equal to be to the X logarithms undo exponentiation.
A few common bases. We have E the natural log. That's the one we use.
By far the most. We have log 10. That's really useful for doing orders of magnitude.
And when we plot on a log access, that log is almost always log.
Ten logs and different bases are proportional to each other, just a constant multiplier.
And so we have the we can have E for a lot of computations based 10 logs for displaying log axes and plots.
Sometimes you're gonna see base two logs when we're dealing, particularly dealing with low level operations and computer programing.
NUM Pi has the function log, which is the natural log and log 10, which is the base 10 log.
So a couple logarithms have a variety of identities.
If you're going to multiply two numbers, you can that's equivalent to adding their logarithm.
So log of X Y is equal to log of X plus log of Y. Exponentiation is multiplying the logarithm to the log of X to the Y as Y times the log of X.
These identities are useful for reasoning about what's happening with your logarithms.
Logarithms are only defined for X greater than zero.
And so. In a moment, we're going to get to log odds in which you so your.
The probability can't be won and allow you to convert to odds, because then you're going to have infinite,
infinite odds and it can't be zero and convert to law gods because you have zero and you can't take the log of zero.
One common operation when we do have some zeroes is to take the log of one plus X and this and num PI has a function that does that very,
very precisely. If you need to do log of one plus X, don't just do log of one plus X two log one P floating point is a weird beast.
I'm going to post a reading or two free to learn more about what's going on with floating point.
But logarithms are very useful for compute because they will help us avoid floating point under or overflow.
And so very, very small probabilities. We'll have logarithms that are still within the reasonable range that we can store.
Also, though, you have to be a little bit careful because in flooding point arithmetic.
So in addition and subtraction are more efficient than multiplication and division.
So if you do the logarithms in your computations, the more efficient they stay in a more useful range of values many times.
But you have to be a little bit careful with particularly subtraction,
but also addition and floating point to avoid problems with precision and cancelation.
Again, I'm going to post a couple of reading or two about that.
But we have our odds and we have our logarithms, so now we can get to law gods or add logs.
But we can go to log odds. And so the log odds is the log of the odds.
And so it's the log of p0 ovei times one minus PMA, which is equal to log of P of a minus the log of one minus P of A.
Because multiplication is addition. Division is subtraction. This function has a name.
This log God's function is called the logic and the logic of P is equal to
log P minus log of one minus P or log the P of log of P over one minus P and.
This converts odd or this converts probability into odds to go back.
It would convert K to S.O. indices through Pyo. The logistic function is the inverse of the logic.
So the logic is the log, the logistic is one over one plus E, the minus X, equivalently, it's either the X over each of the X plus one.
And it has a curve like this. The logic, the logistic of zero is point five as logistic goes to infinity.
This approaches one. As it goes to negative infinity, it approaches zero.
So it maps unbounded real values into the range zero one.
This is very useful because we have zero one outcomes.
It allows us to have an unbounded value that predicts it and it gets us into zero
ones without having to do clamping or anything else that's not differentiable. It also often when you.
You might have a zero one outcome variable. OK?
That's not not the 01 isn't normal or Pritam probabilities often aren't normal because they're bounded in this range zero one.
But it's not uncommon to find a situation where the logic of probabilities is normal.
And so you can if the logic of your probabilities is normal, then that lets you apply that like the law gods is normal.
So that lets you apply things that, like normal numbers,
normally distributed numbers to the log odds and then convert them back into probabilities with the logistic function.
When you actually need a probability, the logistic function is also an example of what's called a sigmoid curve.
S shaped curve. As I said, it converts log odds in the probability.
So odds are another way of representing probabilities and the logistic and logic functions convert between probabilities and the log odds and odds.
The odds of one is even log odds of zero is even log odds.
Zero. When odds equals one.
So and also they're more their balance. So. The odds of two to one is two, odds of one to two is point five.
Odds of long odds of two to one is just a little under one.
And the drug odds of one to two is just a little over negative one.
So it gives you more symmetry, more balance in the law. Become very computationally useful to work with.