This video, we're going to take the combination, the concept we introduced in the last video,
the law guides the logistic and introduced the logistic regression learning outcomes are for you to be able to compute logistic,
which are great aggression, to predict a binary value and understand and generalize logistic regression.
So recall linear regression where we have we're trying to generate predictions y hatam.
We do that with an intercept. And then the sum of scalar multiples of our feature values.
We can generalize this in one way. We can transform feature values with which generally we can think of as applying a
function F of JD each feature X of IJA rather than just multiplying it by a car,
by a coefficient. The full version of this is called what's called a generalized additive model.
But that's it's transforming our input features. We can also do that as a part of our data cleaning process.
But in addition to transforming input features, we can transform output features.
We're going to see that as we always we look at our classification setup. So if Y is a zero one logical random variable,
one is going to be what we call our positive class is admitted is spam is fraud, whatever it is we're trying to detect.
We're going to say one will get Y equals. One is the positive class and Y equals zero is the negative class in some cases numbers.
There's not going to be any hierarchy or moral value.
We just have to pick one and say it's the positive class and then we have our predictive variables X just like we did in the linear regression.
And our goal is to compute Y hat that predicts y just like we did in linear modeling,
except now we don't have these continuous values and it's not meaningful.
Subtract. What happens if you subtract zero like true from false.
So one way to do this is to rather than estimate the value of why we can estimate the probability that Y is one.
Now, remember probability of one.
And when we have zero. One probability of one. And the mean.
Are the same thing we can try to estimate the probability that Y is one.
In a way, we can do this as well with what's called a general linear models with general linear model wrapped the whole model and a functions.
We have a link function G and we wrap the model and its infers inverse G to the minus one.
And so there's different ways we can do this. We can do this for count data with what's called a Poisson.
Regression in the link function is the log. We can do it with binary data or zero one outcomes.
That's what we're going to be focusing on here. This is called a logistic regression and the like function is the logic.
So G minus one. So this is G. So G to the minus one is the logistic.
It's called logistic regression, because we wrap call, we wrap.
The results of our linear model, better zero plus the sum of the better.
I better JS X JS in the logistic function.
So we get the probability of Y equals one. For a particular ax.
Is why hat our predictive value, which is equal to the would?
Which is equal to the logistic. Made an error in the slide.
There it is equal to the logistic of BITA zero plus the sum of our beta JS.
So in this case, why can be our variable admitted grad school X can be and then we have X one, X two, x three as our GRV GPA and school rank.
I'm going to provide a notebook that does this and we can try to predict that with our Y hats now.
So we can do this. We can not. We have this code here that we call G.L. AM instead of oh,
I'll ask for the general linear model we want to predicted met with our three variables and then we tell it that we have a family.
So general linear models have what are called the code usually caused in families.
We're going to say it's the family binomial, which gives us the logic link function.
And then we we fit the bottle when we get the results. And this is going to look kind of familiar.
We don't have an R squared because we're predicting zero one outcomes. It's not really meaningful to talk about their variance.
We do have a lot of likelihood. We're going to see in a later video what that means.
We also have our column of P values, which gives us significant tests on our different coefficients.
We can use them. We can drop non significant predictor variables like we did and like we would in linear regression.
But this gives us that. But there's now so then builds up this linear model.
The coefficient is the coefficients are harder to interpret.
They're not impossible to interpret and logistic regression, but they're harder to interpret.
The important the first important thing is that they are all in terms of log odds.
And so a increase in school. An increase in rank of one decreases the law gods of admission by by point five.
One point five to. But this is the output of our logistic regression.
We can then predict with a logistic regression using the predict method, just like we do in with a linear regression stats,
models that predict method gives us predicted scores which are going to be and these are after calling logistic.
So these are estimated probabilities and they get. We can then convert them into a binary class so we can actually make a decision with a threshold so
we can say we're going to accept everything where the predicted accept is greater than point five.
So it's more likely than not that we're going to accept that we that this one would be.
Yes, according to our model. Different models and different tasks may require different thresholds because there are going
to be different costs for false positives and false negatives depending on our application.
So a couple of terms that are going to be useful as we talk more about these.
First, the outcome that this is the true outcome of the data we seek to predict as it the linear model.
We're going to call it Y. We call this the ground truth as well, and this is also why it's called a supervised learning problem,
because we have this ground truth outcome data that we're trying to learn to predict.
And for the purposes of building and evaluating our model, we assume the data is correct.
Ground troops data can be biased in various ways as well, that can affect our that can affect what we.
That affects what we learn from it, that affects our ability to predict.
It also is a really, really important to note that the outcome variable, this needs to be the actual outcome we're looking for.
Because you're predicting your outcome variable and if your outcome variable isn't what you think it is.
Then you're not predicting the thing you think you're predicting.
I mentioned this in class at one point, but Cathy O'Neill, author of Weapons of Mass Destruction,
pointed out on Twitter a few earlier this fall that in most cases we don't actually have crime data if we want to predict crime,
say, high crime area, or whether a crime is going to happen in a particular area or particular time.
We don't usually actually have crime data. None of our data tells whether a crime happened or not.
Our data says whether a crime was reported. Our data says what police do.
And so if we're trading off of that data, we're not predicting crimes. We're predicting crime reports or police activity, which is not the same thing.
And so it's important to know what our outcome variable,
what our observed outcome variable actually is and how that relates the task that we're actually trying to solve.
We then have a score, which is the prediction score that comes out of our model and the logistic regression.
It's the estimated probability if we just take the linear part of the logistic regression, that it's the estimated log odds.
And then we have our decisions. We use the score to make a decision, often by thresholding it.
And that's what we decide to do.
So if we got a spam detector, our outcome is whether or not the message is spam, as it's been labeled, maybe by our users, maybe by our spam experts.
Our decision is whether or not our model says it's spam. And then what we're going to look for when we start to look at the accuracy of these models
for their predictions is the extent to which those decisions match those outcome variables.
When we say it's spam, is it spam? So to wrap up general linear models, allow linear predictions of nonlinear quantities such as sometimes counts.
Such as. Particularly for our purposes. Binary outcomes, yes or no, true or false.
Logistic regression is the particular way that we use a linear model in order to do binary classification.