Oh, and this video, I'm going to introduce the log likelihood measure that you see when you're training a logistic regression.
We're going to see how that's computed. And we're going to talk about what it means to to estimate parameters with a maximum likelihood estimate.
So our our learning outcomes for this video,
for you to be able to compute the log likelihood of data and understand the objective function of logistic regression.
So recall and logistic regression, we're learning a model y hat equals the logistic function of a linear model.
And that's why Hat is trying to predict the probability that our outcome variable will be one or the probability of yes.
That's what we're doing in our logistic regression. But we can also think about the probability of the data.
So what if we want to not just compute, what if we want to compute,
not the probability that Y is one, but the probability that it equals our observed value?
So what probability does our model, our logistic regression model, assign to the outcomes that we actually observe in the data?
That's what's being captured in the log likelihood. So we can compute this by computing, by using the scores.
These estimated probabilities. And the actual values.
So. We have here. We're going to take the score and we're going to raise it to the power of the outcome variable, which is in zero one.
We're gonna have one minus the score. And remember, the one minus the probability of something is the probability of not something.
So if y hat sabai is, the probability of Y is one than one minus Y has survived, the estimated probability of Y is zero.
We're going to raise that to the power of one minus Y to the eye. So.
This is a trick where if you're going to multiply things.
So we saw in previous examples, when we're trying to add things, we can use multiplication by a one or a zero effectively as an.
If if you multiply something by one, you get something. If you multiply it by zero, you get zero.
So if you're adding those together, what you get it basically turn the ones and zeros turn on and off.
Different pieces of the of the computation and multiplication.
We can use exponentiation to do that or raising something to a power.
And so because because remember that X to the zero is one no matter what axis.
So if our power is a one or a zero.
X to the one equals X. So. If we have, why I as one.
Then why hat's a bye to the one is why hat survived and one minus Y hats a bye to the one minus Y.
Is going to be. Zero. So when Y equals one, then this is one.
And this is zero. See, this is why hat sub I.
And this is zero. And if. Why have I?
If Y. Supply equals zero, then we get zero over here and we get why we get.
One minus Y hats have I here. And so it the zero over the one picks, which of these two scores we actually use.
Because if the observed value is one, then it's probability as the result of our logistic regression.
Passes the logic for the logistic function, so it's actually a probability.
But if the observed value is zero, then we need the negation of that probability one minus it.
And the exponentiation and the multiplication turns into precisely the switching, the conditional that we need there.
It's a neat little trick, because if you if you multiply a variable by a one or a zero, you get the additive identity.
And if you raise a variable to the power of one or zero, you get the multiplicative identity one.
When the very when. When you raise it to the zero.
So. We can compute the probability of our observed data.
We can also condition on probability. So we've been thinking about the probability of Y equals one given X.
But we can extend that to think about the probability of Y equals one given our parameters, beta two.
So what our model is really computing if we generalize it over betas.
So their input as well is the probability of one given X and given our parameter values beta.
And that is equal to the logistic function of our batur zero plus our sum of better job, better j.s multiplied by the feature values.
So this gives us given data Y and X, and I'm using boldface here to indicate this is a vector of data values as opposed to individual data values,
and just to make it a little bit distinct from a random variable.
The likelihood of the data, given the parameters, is the probability of the data Y and X,
given our parameters, which is proportional to the in this case, it's proportional to probability of Y,
A and X given beta is proportional to probability of Y given X and beta,
which in turn is equal to the product of the probabilities of our individual y excise.
We are assuming here that they are exchangeable, that there's no difference if we shuffle the order.
Now this is the probability of the exact sequence that we observed.
But and we can renormalize it if we want to be able to observe these data in any sequence.
But this is the likelihood function. And you're talking a little bit more about what likelihood means and how it fits into a bigger picture.
But I said here that it is proportional. So this operator here is the proportional to operator.
And what it means is that it is equal to the left hand side is equal to the right hand side, multiplied by some scaling constant.
And the reason we get this here is that probably by the by the definition of conditional probability, P of Y of X,
Y and X given be given better is the probability of Y given X and bita times
the probability of X given bita but X we're not choosing X based on Batur.
Y y es probability is conditional on beta, but X is is not X is independent of our parameter is better.
It's just the data that we have. So the probability of X given beta is equal to the probability of X also because X is fixed.
We just have X, we treat it as an unknown constant or we can treat it as one.
The probability of having the data we have is one as one as another way to think about it.
And so. If we think of that as one than this, proud torsional two becomes equals.
But we get this proportionality so that we can just move we can move the ax to the other side of the given bar here in this specific case,
because we're not using Beda to choose X, so we can then do the last piece and we can convert this to a log.
Likelihoods of a log likelihood is the log of the likelihood. So it's the log of P of X times, this big product,
because we want the probability of of the first outcome and the second outcome and the third outcome and probability of these things.
Since we're assuming all of our values are are independent, the probability is equal to their product.
So but then and log is low-Pitched X plus the sum of the logs of the individual probabilities because multiplying values becomes Sum's and log space.
So we can do this thing as a big sum. We do it as a multiplications value is gonna get vanishingly small.
The example dataset I've been using like ten to the negative 80.
But if we use logs, then it's gonna be in a much more reasonable space, like nine minus one hundred and fifty two.
And so lets us do it with additional lets us keep the probabilities in a much more reasonable range so we can compute with much smaller probabilities.
The the probability of any specific sequence of a specific set of observations is relatively low.
We can still talk about finding the data that gives it the most probability, but the probability is small because,
well, you could have just shuffled them and gotten a very, very different value on the order of N factorial.
Different times. So we have this log likelihood is the some of the lives of the individual probabilities
we saw in an earlier slide how to compute those individual probabilities.
The code that actually does this is in the logistic regression demo notebook.
So we have this likelihood function. And we can use what's called a maximum likelihood estimate or so logistic regression.
The way it actually trains what it does is it uses the log likelihood as a as a utility function.
Utility function is the opposite of a lost function or a cost function. And it maximize it.
So it finds the parameter values that maximize this log likelihood.
We can optimize many other models. We could opt out. We can optimize any model that produces a probability or a likelihood.
By computing this kind of an amax, by maximizing the log likelihood of the training data given the model.
This gives us what, as I said, this gives us a maximum likelihood estimate or note.
This is it's maximizing the log likelihood, not the log odds, but the log maximum with the log likelihood,
a maximum of the log odds are going to have the same parameter values because they're monotonic functions or they have a monotonic relationship.
So if we expand this log likelihood, though, we get the log likelihood is equal to Y times.
The log of Y had EI plus the one minus log. Why times the log of one minus Y had I.
And now I've turned. Because we're now adding in log space.
And also because of how you expand powers when you're doing a log. We've now moved.
What was this multiplicative switch or multiplicative conditional that we were using the power as we've now turned it into an additive conditional.
They said this is applicable to any model, where are y hat is an estimate of the probability of the positive class.
So to show you an example of computing this, if we have the first data point.
It's SCOR, why that is. Point one eight to eight 07, and but it's admit it's why a zero, so it's going to be.
We're going to compute why hat zero? Why hat time to the zero?
Times one minus Y hat. Which is point eight, seven to the one, and that's going to be point it one seven.
And we have point eight one seven right here. If you want to compute the log likelihood, you're gonna get negative point, too.
To sum up all these log likelihoods and we're going to get the total log likelihood of the data for this model.
We can compare these on the same data. But if one if you have this, if we have the same.
If we have this model, that fits just as well. But we have different data, even if it's just, say, half of this data.
It's going to change the likelihood because the likelihood is over the whole data set.
So you can use the log likelihood to compare models on exactly the same data.
But as soon as you change the data set. You can't you can't compete.
You cannot use the log likelihood to compare a model on one data with the same
model with a with either the same or a different model on a different data set.
It's only comparable within the exact same set of training data.
So I said I was gonna tell you a little bit about what it means to a maximum likelihood estimate by sideswiping likelihood function,
we're going to maximize it. So if we're ever Bayes Theorem. We can break Bayes Theorem down into a few pieces.
We have the posterior. Which is the probability I'm using here data.
And why? Because we have some data. Why? And I'm folding X into Y for now.
And we have some model parameters, STADA, oftentimes we want to be able to ask,
given the data I have, what's the probability of a particular set of model parameters?
And this is the heart of what we call Bayesian inference. Not all applications that base theorem are Bayesian inference,
but Bayesian thinking becomes it's quite common in various machine learning applications.
So we can think about what's the probability of my parameters, given my particular data.
And we do that with a few pieces. We have our prior.
Before I see any data, what's my knowledge of the ah, what's the probability I assigned to different portions of the parameter space?
This might be uniform, it might be broad, like some broad normal. It might be based on actual information.
The likelihood function, it tells me, for a particular parameter set.
How likely is my data? And that's what we just saw computing for a logistic regression for a particular parameter set.
How likely is the data that we have seen? If it if it's true, if this is the true value of the parameter,
how likely is the particular data I would have seen then we have probability of y, which effectively for our purposes is a scaling factor.
Because for a given data set, if the data set is not changing, its probability is not going to change.
So if our goal is to say find Fada, that either maximizes the likelihood or maximizes the posterior.
Because multiplying by a scalar doesn't change where the maximum point is, it just changes the value of that maximum point.
We can ignore it. Most of the time. So we treated the scaling factor, if you need the definition.
It's the integral overall of the possible parameter values of the numerator there.
So. Where Maxima in training a logistic regression,
we maximize the likelihood we call this a maximum likelihood or an MLS demetre because it does exactly what it says,
it maximizes the likelihood it maximize it finds the parameter values.
For which the data is as likely as possible with our particular model.
We can also maximize the posterior. We can find the theta that is the most likely given our model.
That's often more computationally expensive. And when the prior is, say, uniform.
They're all constant across parameter space. There's no difference.
But also with lots and lots of data as the amount of data you have and why increases
the relative importance of the likelihood increases and outweighs the prior.
And so when you have a lot of data, the prior doesn't influence the posterior very much so long as it's sufficiently broad over your parameter space.
And so the parameter values that maximize the likelihood we very close to the parameter values to maximize the posterior.
The exact relationship between those and when you when in detail, when you can use MRL, when you really need to use map,
those are you're going to say you should see those in more detail in either machine learning or the computational statistics course.
For now, we're going to. For our purposes right here, they're going to be very, very similar.
To wrap up, the logistic function is back trained by maximizing the log likelihood of the training data.
Given the model with a particular set of parameters, you could implement this yourself.
And if you want to practice this, you could take what we did in last week's material to optimize linear regression using
the optimize function and use that to optimize the parameters of a logistic regression.
Note that you can just tick in negative if you if you maximizing the log likelihood is equivalent to minimizing the negative log likelihood.
So if you want to see this in action, I encourage you to open up one of the notebooks and go practice and try to use it out,
optimize to train yourself a logistic regression.