So this video I want to introduce you to, Saikat Learned, which is another tool kit for training models.
So with this video, I want you to be able to apply a logistic regression model with psychic learn,
understand and understand the API differences between psychic learning stats, models code to accompany.
This is in the course notes for this week. You'll be able to go see the psychic learn.
It's the same problem as I use for the logistics regression demo with stats models.
You can directly compare a stats model solution and a psychic learned solution.
So to train a model with psychic learn, we need to do a few things.
So I'm going to create here a couple of variables that store the names of columns just to make it easy to extract columns,
the same columns in the same order from both my training data and my test data.
So I'm going to get my training x my input features by getting the feature column.
So this. So this is my predictor features.
Then I'm going to grab the outcome variable. This is my outcome.
And then I, I set up my logistic regression and I just pass those values to fit Kirilov just to progression model, pass them to fit.
And it is going to train the models parameters based on my data to fit my logistic regression model.
And that's all there is to it. Structures just a little bit different here. Notice that fit does not return a new results object.
It actually just returns to the model. There's not two objects in stats, models, you create a model and then you fit it and you get results.
And Saikat learn, you create a model and then you fit it.
And the results are stored in the model object. Lots of other software in the Python ecosystem follows the Saikat Learn API patterns.
So if you're familiar with them, that's going to also help you with a lot of other software.
Tenzer flow follows the same patterns. Many other packages follow the same pattern, just like it learn.
So those who want to use the model we use predict now.
And Saikat learn to, when stat's models predict, gave us the estimated probability in psychic learn,
it gives us the actual class, the actual predicted class.
So it gives us the decision. It makes the decision right away.
One of the advantages of this is that any of the psychic learn classifier A-P eyes or classifier models do this.
So you predict is going to return the decision. There's other function to give you.
The underlying scores decision function gives you the log odds.
You can use predict Prop eight to get the probabilities. It returns both the probabilities of fail of zero and the probabilities of one.
So we need to get the second column, the one column to get the probabilities of one.
This is equivalent to the stats model's output. But the nice advantage of Saikat predict returning your classes is it's easier to use directly.
You don't have to manage Threshold's yourself.
And the other thing is that since all of the different psychic classifier models return decisions like that,
then you can make write code to do classification. They can use any model and you can plug in the different models with the same code.
And it makes it easier to to exchange models as part of your workflow and to also test the performance of different models in the same data workflow.
So a few differences from stats models Saikat Learn works with matrices, not data frames.
A data frame is a matrix. They're compatible. You can treat a data frame as a matrix, but Saikat Learn doesn't know that it's a data frame.
It just treats it as a matrix. One of the things this means is that your column labels are ignored.
Everything is based on position. You need to have your columns in the same order for fit and for every call to predict and fit and predict.
Map require the same column num numbers, the same column positions.
You also don't have your you have your feature, your input feature matrix and your outcome variable as separate vectors.
So a matrix of input features a vector of outcome variables. And then.
And so that's why I when I was doing the training I got our input matrix and I got
our our outcome vector column as a series which can be treated as an umpire ray,
which is what syk it does. So you can't cycad it doesn't know anything about your column names.
Also, Psyche just has a single motto object that's updated by fit. As I said, there's no separate results.
And then predict returns, the predicted class, not the score.
So use case wise stats models is good for inference, and it's it's easier to do inference.
With stats, models am a psychic. Learn it reports a lot of statistical goodness.
Fitz measures it defaults to UN regularized models, which are often easier for inference.
It reports. It also say things like when you do your fit, you get your results.
It also gives you all the residual psychic learning to go back and get those yourself because Saikat learns best for prediction.
So you don't need the residuals to go to a prediction. You only need the residuals to understand your training process.
For in France, Saikat learned, though, is really good for prediction. It has many bottles.
Many more models than Stotz models. And its API is output.
The actual prediction, not just the underlying score, but a fault.
It also is a bunch of capabilities for data transformation, preprocessing post-processing,
etc. and it only saves the parameter estimates when you call the logistic regression that fit.
It learns coefficients, it learns at intercept, and that's all it saves.
It doesn't say if you're fitted values, it doesn't save your residuals. You have to go back and get those by having it predict.
The outcomes for your training is what you have to do yourself.
If you want to do those. So it's more work if you want to do inference, but it's fantastic for prediction.
So wrap up Saikat Learn provides a lot of machine learning models, including logistic and linear.
You can go back into the linear regression things we've been doing with Saikat learn as well.
It's more difficult to do inference with Saikat learn,
but it's got a broader selection of models that are useful for prediction and in most production prediction predictive analytics tasks.
You're probably gonna want Saikat learn instead of stats models.