Love this video. I want to introduce you to R.O. curves that we can use to understand and visualize tradeoffs between
different types of errors as we change the threshold for our our logistic or for classifier.
So objectives here. Friedberger plot accuracy curve and to compute interprete receiver operating characteristic curve.
So the matrix metrics from the confusion matrix are hard.
Are based on hard. Yes no outcomes. They compare your decision. Yes.
Or one or zero. Yes or no. To the action to the observed outcome in our ground.
Truth data. One or zero. Yes or no. But a single classifier often has this tradeoff points.
So you train a logistic regression, the default. This is what Saikat learned does is it uses point five probability or zero log odds as the threshold.
And if it's more if one is more likely than zero, it returns one.
But we could have it be more conservative to say require an 80 percent probability of one in order to classify as one.
Or we could classify as one as soon as that are 20 percent probability,
depending on the needs we have and depending on the specific costs of false positives and false negatives in our application.
So we can plot curves for various metrics here, I've done precision, you could do it for recall, you could do it for accuracy at different thresholds.
So here I have thresholds. And these are in law gods and I. The X axis decreases as you go.
Right. So as you go from left to right, we're decreasing our threshold and seeing what happens to the physician.
And it's wobbly up at the top. That's wobbly in the higher end because we make a few more classifications.
It can wind up being more precise for a little bit.
And then as we keep it starts stabilizing and as we decrease to as we keep decreasing the threshold,
we keep decreasing the precision of our system because we're classifying more and more as.
Yes. And we're deeping digging deeper and deeper into the barrel to find the ones we want to classify as.
Yes. And we're finding quite a few. And then we wind up classifying quite a few noses.
Yes. Now, we also do see here that at ah, at our zero cut off about here, we can look at a negative point five and that actually has just as high.
That actually has a higher precision than the default cutoff. A zero.
This is useful for actually setting the threshold value, if you can plot your metric, be a precision,
be it something else at these different thresholds, and and use that to gain insight, to think about where you want to set your threshold.
Another curve that we use for evaluating classifiers sometimes is the receiver operating characteristic curve.
And so in the ROIC curve, what we do is we plot the true positive rate on the Y axis and the false positive rate on the x axis.
And what this lets us see is as we as we decrease R, as we increase our tolerance for false positives,
what happens to the number of true positives we find? Now, remember, two true positive rate and recall are the same thing.
So if we want to find half of the Yes cases. How what's the flip, false positive rate?
Do we have to accept in order to do that, we have to accept the point to.
And it lets us see it. Well, if we want to find if we want to find 80 percent of the positives, then we have to accept around a point for three or so.
But it lets us it lets us see here what false positive rate we have to tolerate in order to achieve a certain recall in our classifier.
You can also do other curves like this for other pairs of metrics, but other pairs of metrics against each other.
A precision recall curve looks at the relationship between precision and recall.
As you change your threshold. Another thing that's important to note is that the diagonal line here is random.
So a random classifier is going to get the diagonal lines performance. If you're if your curve is up over here to the left, then that's doing better.
One of the things we can do, though, is even for the same precision, we might have a curve that goes like this.
We might have a curve that goes up more quickly and then dials off.
We might have a curve that trails off for a while and then gets better. This lets us understand.
It lets us see the different tradeoff points for different classifiers and determine which one has a curve that
better aligns with the needs of our application and and generally want to be able to pick up the false positives.
The true positive quickly. But this curve here, as you see, is as soon as you get over here, if you want to get over about.
You want to get more than point six recall. So you want point eight.
Recall, you have to accept a lot more false positives with this one than you do with the blue curve.
Because it doesn't cross point eight to here as opposed to here.
Whereas if you want if you want to recall a 50 percent, then you don't have to have as many false positives with this one.
So it really lets you it lets you know. It characterizes.
The tradeoffs of the different classifiers and lets you pick one that's going to be better aligned with the needs of your particular application.
If you wind up with a classifier down here.
It's worse than random, but in verdict classified, yes.
When it and when it says no. And then you're going to get a relatively good classifier.
So we're really paying attention to classifiers in the top left triangle of the ROIC curve.
We could also compute the area under the ROIC curve. And this gives us a metric, a U.S.
Put a random classifier, that agonal line is going to have an AUC of point five greater is good because.
The only way you get greater than point five is you have mass here,
you have a curve that goes up that gives you more true positives for the false positives than you would with a random classifier.
It's less than point five again. You can avert your classifier. Also, the area under the curve is the problem, Bill, is equal to the probability of.
If you pick two items at random that your classifier put them in the correct order.
So it said it scored Y above J when Y is actually better than J.
Or its score or vice versa. It scored Y below J. Y is actually below J.
The probability of that is the same as the area under the curve, which becomes useful in a few applications, especially where your application,
what you care about is what's the probability that I put you care about the relative classifications of things.
This becomes important when you're doing systems that rank that rank their outputs.
And the classification is we're gonna take the top ten as our good ones.
That's basically what a search engine does. Area under the curve gives you the probability that you stuck two things in the right order.
So to conclude ROIC,
Kurz gives us a way to see tradeoffs between false positives and false and true positives and compared to the tradeoff curves of multiple classifiers.
It also gives us the area under the curve metric that we can use to quantify classifier performance.