Hello again.
This video, I want to talk some more about biases we've been talking about a little bit throughout the class and also the assumptions that we make.
We're doing a predictive modeling task.
Learning outcomes are for you to build a reason about its potential biases and classification inputs and outputs and
also identify some cases or building a classifier or a predictor it applies to regression to is not appropriate.
So I want to talk a little bit about the assumptions of most predictive modeling tasks.
So we make use that we have an outcome variable and observed I'm biased.
That's not the same as not erroneous. But we have. But we assume that there's no systematic bias in our outcome variable or in our features that
are outcome variable actually matches the target of the thing that we're trying to classify.
And that predicting this outcome with these features is reasonable.
Think about what you need to think about what the fact that you are trying to do this prediction implies.
The one of the readings I've assigned is going to talk in more detail about the assumptions of using prediction systems to make decisions.
So recall from week two, I talked about a few sources of bias. Selection bias is when your there's a there's a discrepancy in who gets selected.
Your selection is not uniformly at random from the population.
Some some instances are more likely to be selected than another that others response bias
is that some some selected instances are more likely to give you a response than others.
This is super common when we're dealing with human data, because even if you are perfectly unbiased and who you select to ask a survey question,
people aren't necessarily all are people aren't always going to respond.
And there may be a correlation between whether or not they respond and what their response would be if they responded.
One one example of this. That's not a Soviet or refusing to respond is if you ask somebody to tell you they're to
rate a random movie that they've never seen and you're not having them watch it just hey,
what did you think of the 5000 fingers of Dr. T? They're more likely to be able to answer that question for movies they watched and
they're more likely to have watched movies that they think they're going to like.
And so you can think of this as a selection bias that users selecting movies to rate are more likely to psych movies they want to watch.
But if you flip it around, so it's you asking a person, what do you think of the 5000 fingers of Dr. T?
They're going to be more likely to respond if it's Poovey they thought they would have liked and watched.
You're not going to get very many respondents on the 5000 fingers of Dr. T, and they measure my biases.
You can get the response and it skews one way or another based in a systematic way,
possibly based on on sensitive attributes, protected group classification of protected attributes of of the data subjects.
So. It's important to notice that there's a difference between error and bias.
Observations often have error in them. But the bias comes in when they are systematically erroneous.
So when we talk about we talk about an unbiased estimate or statistics,
an unbiased estimate or is an estimate or whose expected value is equal to the parameter or the expected value,
the parameter a bias comes in when the the values the estimate is or the actual observations we're making are systematically higher,
low, or they may trend different for different groups. And maybe the deal for all means is even.
But one group tends to score higher on on your measurement than another group or or you're mis measuring one group more likely than another group.
So if you have features or outcome variables that are unbiased, then you can just roll your errors into your model uncertainty.
Everything's uncertain if the the errors are independent and identically distributed.
It's more uncertainty in your model. If they have no bias, you may be able to correct.
You may be able to remove a bias term.
You may be able to make some assumptions like saying, well, there's a difference in the score between these two groups.
We're going. But we don't believe the groups are actually different, so we'll just normalize them within groups.
Some of these things are what happens in some of the election forecasting.
So the election forecasters, they they pool together polling data from a bunch of polling sources, along with other data that affects their forecast.
And one of the things they have is they have a model of the bias of different polling houses.
So some polling houses do their sampling strategy might might be more likely to contact or there
might be a Republican leaning bias or a Democrat leaning bias in their sampling strategies.
And they're polling results. You can tell that you can.
Look, see this in some ways by their agreement with each other, also by their agreement and their historical agreement with election outcomes.
If you are assuming that the House bias is relatively stable over time and but if you've got good data to estimate how it's biases,
you can use those to adjust your polling average polling when you're pool pooling together multiple polling sources for election modeling.
That's one example of a way where you where there's deliberately trying to de bias, where you've got an estimate of the bias.
There's unknown bias, which this is really common. You need to start to think about how and how severe.
And first, can you start to try to quantify the bias, but then also what are the downstream applications?
This is one of the reasons why we always start with our goal and we move to our question because some biases will affect the question.
And for that, the same bias may render some questions unanswerable and have negligible impact on other questions.
So the the the problems that arise from bias in our data are not intrinsic, necessarily intrinsic to the data ourselves itself.
They arise in combination of what we're going to do with it and that that needs to
inform how we go about understanding the impact of a potential bias in the data.
We also, though, we need to think about the assumptions we bring to our data and also some assumptions can sometimes help us get out of some problems.
We need to document them and be clear about them, but assumptions can provide us some guidance.
So, for example, if we find S.A.T. scores differ by socioeconomic status, that's relatively well established.
But what's what causes this? What are these is more likely that poor students are intrinsically less academically
capable or that poor students have had less less access to academic preparation.
And that can be formal academic preparation, such as S.A.T. prep courses, a greater selection of college prep courses in high school.
And it may be less formal, such as a greater selection of reading materials when they were in elementary school.
It's relatively well established that good access to reading,
which had access to a good quantity of reading materials for young children and engagement with reading,
can really help them with educational outcomes down the road.
There's one study that we cite in some of the research that I've been I've been involved
with that found that if you engage children in what they called authentic literacy tasks,
but reading things besides a text book,
when they are in the first or second grade, then later on in junior high around the junior high age or just a little bit younger,
those students have higher learning outcomes when in in various STEM tasks.
And so that can be the kind of this informal a student who has early access to good
reading materials and diverse reading materials is going to do better academically.
This is a good, good reason to believe they'll do better on the S.A.T.
And so one of my one one of the research projects I'm involved with is are working on
is looking at how do we how can we use technology tools to enable to make it easier?
For teachers to provide more and different reading materials for their students in a way with minimal costs,
it's accessible in low resource educational settings. Then there's also the question of does the S.A.T. measure some combination of academic
capability and familiarity with conventions and expectations for middle to upper class?
So when you see a difference like this. Anything. What's more like is it really more likely that the students are intrinsically different or that?
There's this difference in access to academic preparation. And that's what we're actually measuring.
And if that's what we're actually measuring,
what implications should that have for how we actually use the resulting numbers and what we do with them?
So I also want to talk a little bit about outcome target mismatch.
So what I mean by this is you got a Klatt, you're trying to predict X and you have a class label for X Prime.
That's not really X. And so you're actually training a model to predict one thing when your goal is another.
Sometimes you have to. Sometimes all we have is a proxy. And that's a reasonable thing to do.
We need to evaluate the quality and the credibility of our proxy because sometimes it's all we have.
But sometimes the proxy is too disconnected from the target to be credible.
For example, if we want to model crime. So if we want to classify neighborhoods, if we want to be able to predict the crime level of a neighborhood.
And the data we have as crime reports and or arrests.
What we're trained to predict or to do is predict crime reports and police activity, which is not the same thing as actual crime,
because an area where crimes go unreported, because there could be a variety of reasons.
One could be that the people in that neighborhood have less trust for the police, with the police.
And so they're less likely to report minor crimes or crimes aren't observed because that area isn't as heavily police.
So crime is happening. But police aren't there to observe it and make arrests and nobody's bothering to report it.
So if you're trying to predict crime, but your prediction model is trained on.
Crime reports or police activity? You're not predicting crime. You're predicting crime reports or police activity.
And so you have to be really careful about the relationship between the labels you have and the actual target variable that you're trying to measure.
So with that, our claims then need to be supported by our evidence.
And so we can't claim that we're detecting crime when we are trusting our classifier on crime reports because we're testing its ability to detect.
They reported crime, which is not the same thing as a crime that actually happened.
We're missing all of the unreported crimes and we also have the reports of things that weren't actually crimes.
This is why early on in the semester, I talked with you about this goal question analysis chain.
And I encourage you to go back and review that material because we need we have a goal.
We would find that in the research questions and then we connect the research questions to the analysis.
And at every step, it needs to be clear, the analysis we do needs to directly illuminate the research question and we need
to revise the analysis and or reframe the research question until we have a match.
That the analysis is actually addressing the question, can we detect crime reports?
And then the question needs to advance our goal and breaks anywhere in that chain.
Reduce the ability of our data analysis to advance the goals that we're trying to use it for.
We also need to think about the reasonableness of the task,
because whenever we use acts to predict why, we are assuming that that's a reasonable thing to do.
Predicting college performance with S.A.T. scores. That's kind of what the S.A.T. is built for.
There are problems. The S.A.T.,
but this isn't an inherently unreasonable task performance on a standardized test as a legitimate basis for predicting future academic grades.
On its face, not a bad assumption, but. Every year or so,
somebody or another gets the idea that they're going to take a deep learner and they're going to train out of a bunch of photos
and their outcome variable is going to be some attempted measure of criminality has been arrested or maybe has been convicted.
And trying to convey trying to trying to predict criminality from photos and what
this assumes is that facial features are a legitimate predictor of criminality.
And so the question can arise, why would you assume that? This this mechanism is called physiognomy.
It's been rejected for a good, solid century, it was kicking around in the eighteen hundreds and then people realized that it was a bad idea.
It's close cousin. It's phrenology. Physiognomy is when you're trying to predict attributes such as criminality or other personality traits.
My face fits. Phrenology is when you're trying to do it based on the shape of a skull.
It involves a lot of calibers and school measurements.
But you it's it's assuming here that you can use these physical characteristics to predict criminality and you can probably predict arrested.
You can put you might even be able to predict charged or convicted with a crime because the social process of
constructing what is a crime and who gets arrested for a crime is going to have correlates to physical attributes.
But. At its base, we have to think about what is crime and crime is actions.
That as a society, we have decided are sufficiently aberrant that they deserve criminal treatment.
Some of those are relatively uncontroversial, like theft. But if crime is an action in violation of our societal laws.
Why would that be a physically observable characteristic? What's the theory, what's the mechanism there?
Because you can find all kinds of correlations and theory and thinking about
as the assumptions and what theoretical constructs could motivate something.
Are a key. Ah, one of the guiding points we can use to keep away from some of these madrassas.
So be careful what you assume. Theory drives our research questions. We don't just ask every question willy nilly.
That's a very inefficient use of science theory either.
The theory we have that we want to clarify or that we want to apply to a new problem or propose theories that we want to evaluate,
we should first give them a smell test and see it.
Is this a reasonable theory to try to evaluate? And theory also drives or drives our predictions.
We don't want to just throw a bunch of data at Saikat Learn or at Tenzer Flower or whatever and use whatever predictions come out.
We want to put some thought into the process and we want to think about is this a reasonable prediction task?
Is this a reasonable set of features? Is it legitimate to try to predict?
Is this person a criminal? Based on what they look like, based on the picture that you see in the CCTV camera?
Is that suppose, even suppose we did have a reliable correlation, is that a societally legitimate or useful thing to do?
So another problem, though, that we also have is we can have problems with labeled dependency, so observations are often incomplete.
For example, if the bank does not give someone a loan, they don't get to observe whether or not they're going to pay that loan back.
This is a problem. Machine learning researchers, stative statistics, researchers like to give things clever names.
This is a problem called the apple tasting problem. Also, though, criminal databases only have those were caught by the justice system in some way,
it doesn't have the criminals that people who committed crimes and didn't get caught.
And also, we have to be careful of inverse probabilities. So the probability of A given B and the probability of being given A are not the same thing.
You have to be careful when you're using this to say if you've got two groups, say the group and you look try to look at their composition.
That does not. That that that's not enough evidence to make.
Conclusions in the other direction.
So if you look at the racial makeup of basketball players, what you get is probability of race given basketball player.
But that doesn't get give you a probability of skilled basketball player given race.
And.
So you have to be really careful about accidentally inverting your probability when you don't have the rest of the pieces of Bayes theorem involved.
This is a this is one of the traps of common in formal probabilistic reasoning.
You also have to be careful with pulling from different groups.
So one example is like if if you're if you're if you have a bunch of mug shots and people getting arrested using those, you're criminal cases.
Well, what are you using as a non-criminal face?
If you're getting it from a different set, then are you really learning criminality or are you learning the visual distinct,
the distinctive visual features of a mug shot? This also comes up in a variety of other settings.
You need to you need to pay attention to what your learner is actually learning when it's going to try to do a prediction.
I read of a case a few years ago where a machine learning algorithm for examining X-ray photos
was trying to learn to to identify X-ray photos that indicated a particular medical condition.
Had relatively good accuracy, but. Someone went and dug into what it was actually learning and see what parts of the images it looking at.
And it was looking at over on the side, this code that indicated where the X-ray was taken because some of the X-ray pictures came from.
A hospital where people were far more likely to have the disease.
And the other one came for more general hospital or more general X-ray lab.
And so it wasn't actually learning to identify the disease in the X-ray photo.
It was learning the X-ray photos taken in a particular hospital's lab were more likely
to have the disease because it was where the more advanced cases were being sent.
So you have to be really, really careful, even if you've got a reasonable set of data.
Oh, I have a bunch of X-ray photos.
There can be differences that you don't expect that you need to be careful about what your systems actually learning.
So what do you do about all of this? Unfortunately, there's not just a quick fix solution.
You can't import psychic psychic lern dot unbias.
And if someone ever gives us killer and that unbias be very, very skeptical.
The starting point was we assume that we've got bias problems, we just don't necessarily know what they are, especially if you've got social data.
The question isn't, are the data biased? The question is how are they biased? How much are they biased?
And what impact does that have on the conclusions and tasks to which we're trying to apply it?
We then need to start understanding how the data is collected and what the labels actually are.
This is why we spent so much time early in the class talking about how do you actually describe data?
And I have you read things about describing where your data came from, how it was collected, why it was collected,
because incentive structures can skew the data collection process so that you have the information to start doing the reasoning about it.
Study what's known about the data biases in your domain. There may be a plethora of radiate a body of existing research.
You can draw off of to understand what's going on in it.
Also look for systematic variations in the data, especially if you have data from different groups of people.
If you have data from different sites, look for systematic variations.
Those alone aren't necessarily aren't enough to tell you the drivers of different biases, but they give you a starting point where to go looking.
And then you can go look for research like what might cause this kind of a difference between the groups that I'm seeing.
Also, clarify a document, all of your assumptions. We want our analysis.
We want to do a good job with our analysis. Our analysis will never be perfect.
At some point they need to be done, but clarify and document what you're assuming each step of the pathway document why you're building this model.
What's your theoretical justification for using these features to predict this outcome?
What does that theoretical justification have to say about how you should use this features and how you should evaluate your model?
Always be critical of of your own work and a reasonably critical the work of others as well.
Does your problem make sense that your outcome makes sense? Are the results too good to be true?
Too good to be true? They often are. But then also read broadly and critically.
And this is one that it's hard to give a quick fix on, too.
But a lot of what I learn about the way biases creep in and how to deal with them and the data that I work
with and a lot of it's domain specific and contextual is from reading widely and reading deeply sometimes,
but reading a lot of different things.
And not just the statistics research, the data science research at the computer science research, but reading, pop science work.
Good pop science work, reading, legal scholarship, reading,
various other things to give you a more holistic picture of what is going on in the domains that I'm trying to study.
So to wrap up all of our analysis are based on assumptions, and you need to be clear what your assumptions are.
And you just study how your data is biased. And there's no magic bullet for all of this.
We're gonna be talking about some things. We're going to talk about some measures for how do you measure bias and outcomes of a system.
But there's no magic bullet. It requires continuous critical thought and reflection on what it is that we're doing and interrogation of what our
system is doing and how its impacts are distributed and what its underlying data and conceptual theoretical bases are.
This is also where the place where a few weeks ago we had the video about epistemology is this is one of the sources.
This is one of the places where critical epistemology is can become very useful because they they give us the starting point for wit,
the ways in which our system could go wrong and or might be a bad idea.
That doesn't mean we thwe we just shut it down because someone said something.
But it's something we need to reflect on it and incorporate what we learned from reading critical scholarship
and reading critical analysis into how we think about going about the work that we're trying to do.