Oh, this video, I'm going to introduce our week's topic about building and evaluating models, talking more in detail about how we go about doing that,
learning outcomes for the week or for you to be able to build and refine a predictive model,
construct features for that model, apply regularization to control features and then her interaction and to give us models that
generalize better and to model measure of a model's effectiveness and its other behavior.
So where we're at right now, we've seen linear regression and we have seen continue to be able to do continuous prediction,
we want to predict a continuous outcome or target variable.
We've seen logistic regression that lets us take the concept of linear modeling and move it into the realm of binary classification,
where rather than having a continuous outcome variable, we have a binary outcome such as defaulted on the loan or is spam or fraud.
We've also seen the idea of minimize it, of optimizing objective functions, we might minimize a loss function such as the squared error.
We might maximize utility functions such as log likelihood. These are equivalent to each other.
And if you've got a utility function in the minimize or you can minimize the negative of the utility function.
We've also seen that we can think about what we're doing with modeling is doing conditional estimation.
So in a regression model, we're trying to estimate the conditional expectation, given a particular set of values for my input features X.
What's the expected value of Y? We might we might do some transformations to all these variables.
But we're trying to compute this conditional expectation function.
What's the expected value of Y condition done by feature values, X and classification?
We're trying to solve a conditional probability problem.
What's the probability of a particular outcome given that I have some particular feature values x.
Also so. There's another, though, thing in here that's useful to thinking about,
so that would just add regression at its heart is trying to model the probability of your data.
So what we've been doing is with stats, models.
We do model that predict and we get some scores and then we use the scores to make a decision because internally,
the logistic regression mathematically with solving this problem of maximizing the log likelihood.
Mathematically, what the logistic regression is doing is it's trying to build a probabilistic model of the data and the
parameters are estimated based on their ability to accurately model probabilities in your training data.
We then use these output probabilities to make decisions. So we'll say success if y had is greater than point five.
Saikat Learn uses the logistic regression to directly classify by using the threshold of point five.
But you can get those estimated probabilities out of it with decision, the decision function.
This is important to note.
So the log likelihood that you get out of a logistic regression is not based on its actual actual decisions that it's making.
It's based on its ability to model probabilistically what the labels look like in your training data.
And it's the more it's the probability that it assigns to those labels with the final fitted versions of the parameters.
I want to mention briefly again, a trick that I mentioned, I believe, last week where.
Expected value and probability are closely related. The expected value is the integral or the somewhere of values weighted by their probabilities.
But also if we have an indicator function, ie, which is one if.
X is in the set and and zero, if it is not with what one?
Basically, given a value, it decides whether or not it's in the set. If that said as an event, it says whether or not the event happened,
the probability and the expected value of the indicator function are the same thing.
So we can think about estimating conditional expectation probable, but we can think about everything is estimated conditional expectation.
When we're estimating a probability, we're estimating the conditional expectation of the characteristic or indicator function.
So to wrap up, we're building models that estimate conditional probability and expectation.
We've been doing this in a variety of ways. We use these models to make decisions.
This week we're gonna see more. So we've got the idea of doing the modeling. This week, we're looking more at how do we build inputs for these models?
And how do we evaluate the outputs that we get out of them?