This video I want to talk with you about, transforming features,
learning outcomes are for you to be able to transform individual features and also derive new features and combine features.
What we're talking about here applies to both classification and regression models.
So. We've seen a few different things we can do with features already.
Just a little bit. Such as dealing with categorical features by dummy coating them.
But I'm going to start by refreshing on some discrete feature transference if we have one feature and it's a discrete feature.
There's a few things we can do with it. This is not an exhaustive list. But we can we can recode it.
We can rename coats. It might be that we've got the code. Just the names aren't very useful, so we want to rename them.
It might be that we want to merge codes. So some distinctions are irrelevant.
So, for example, on one of my datasets for completeness and being able to track coverage across each stage of the data integration pipeline,
there are four or five different ways a value can be unknown.
But when it comes to doing my final computations, I just care if it's unknown.
So I merge all of those codes into one unknown code. So that's one thing you might want to do is,
is merge some codes that your model doesn't have as many different codes to
work with because you don't care about the distinctions between some of them.
You may want to convert a value to a logical or a zero one numeric so that maybe it's you just want you're doing your recoding
where you pick one value and it's got to be one or two values that are going to be true and everything else is gonna be false.
You may also want to threshold values. For example, if you've gotten ordinal,
maybe you have some ratings and you want to say you want to collapse that into a category or a logical feature of rated positively,
where if they gave it more than three out of five stars, you say it was rated positively.
This can be really useful because people are really noisy and their inputs, like some people will say.
For some people say a five and you can reduce some of that noise by saying, you know,
we don't care how good they said the movie was, we just care if they said it was good.
This is kind of what Rotten Tomatoes is doing with its percent Frasch.
They take each rating and they convert it into did the you did the person say rate it positively or not.
And they look at the fraction of users or of critics who rated the movie positively and that becomes that becomes a feature.
So you can also dummy code your values. If you've got a categorical value with more than two levels,
then you can expand that out of the multiple features, that dummy code, your variable or one hot in code.
You can also do a number of things, the continuous features. You can take a log. You can take a square root.
Both of these are useful for reducing SKU. Sometimes you might want to take a square or a higher order polynomial in order
to a higher order power or higher order polynomial building out more features.
You've got a feature and it's square and it's cube that lets you learn more complex, nonlinear functions using a linear model.
You can also standardize various standardized and center variables. So they're mean what they call what we call mean centered.
If you take the mean of a feature and you subtract it from all the feature values,
the resulting mean is zero and the data is now means centered and you can also democratize it.
So you can convert it to either to more than one bean or you can threshold it to convert it to a binary value that's positive or negative.
There is a binary value based on whether it's above or below a threshold. So but how do you think about when you want to do this?
There's a couple of things that particularly drive when we might want to transform features.
One is when the feature has a non linear relationship to our outcome.
Variable transformation of the feature and or the outcome variable can make the relationship linear.
And now all of our linear modeling techniques work again. Also that the feature is not normally distributed.
This isn't inherently a problem, but close to normally distributed features often work better.
There's often more likely going to be linear.
So if we have a feature that's really that's very not normal and there's a simple transformation that can make it normal,
that's often going to make it work better as a feature that's input into particularly a linear model.
But other kinds of models as well. So, for one example,
if we want to standardize variables where we want to do is we want to subtract the
main feature value that's going to make the new mean on the training data zero.
And then what this means is so if if you've got this means centered variable and you use it as a feature, a linear model.
Then when the value is average, you're just going to have the intercept or the intercept,
plus the other features and the coefficient describes the change in the re outcome.
As the variable bill goes above or below average, rather than as it goes just with respect to zero, it's its natural value.
Mean Centerin can also result in more interpretable intercepts.
Because. If all of your features are mean centered, then your intercept of your linear model is the average value.
If your features aren't, many aren't mean centered than the the intercept is average,
but corrected for the averages of your different features so it can make the model more interpretable.
It can make it make the meet means enter.
It makes the model far more interpretable.
It's also useful for dealing with sparse data because if you mean center your values, then it's a lot more reasonable to treat missing values as zero.
It's still a form of a mutation, but if you mean center your values and you have something come in that doesn't have a value,
you can say, well, we don't know anything about it, so we're gonna assume at zero or we're going to zoom it's average.
Since you've means centered, the value average means the coefficient on that feature plays no role in the outcome prediction.
That's also very important. So mean centering really gives you this way to allow missing data to not have an effect
in your model because you're going sue its average average has a zero coefficient.
Its outcome is going to be based completely on the values of the other features and the observation.
It's not a perfect solution for all systems. You can't just blindly assume it's going to work, but it is a really useful technique.
The other thing we do in standard is a full standardization is we divide by the standard deviation and so the resulting value of F X.
We have a value X AI that's in our input feature. We subtract the main divide by the standard deviation and we get this transformed value x sabai.
Now the coefficients on this in a linear model are going to be a units of standard deviations.
So if f x changes by one standard deviation, how much does that change the output?
One. And this also makes if we standardize it, this makes our coefficients more directly comparable.
Because if all of our features are standardized or all of our numeric features are standardized,
then all of the coefficients are in terms of standard deviation.
You can say if this feature moves by one standard deviation,
if that feature moves by one standard deviation and you don't have to deal with all this was in millimeters and this one's in Gramp's,
how do we think about the relative impact of these two features? You can't if they're in their natural units, you can.
If they're in terms of standard, it's much easier if they're in terms of standard deviations.
And this applies to both inference and predictive modeling.
Now, it's important to note that the the parameters here, the mean that we're going to shift by.
And the scaling factor are parameters that we learned from the training data.
And when we want to transform the test data, we need to transform them by the training data's parameters,
because effectively what you do is part of the training process. You learn.
Okay, I've got I've got my coefficients, but also I normalize this feature by subtracting seven and dividing by three.
Well, that's going to change a little bit with different training data.
So you treat these as parameters and use the same values for transforming your test data.
I want to show you an example of why you might want to do a log transform even for binary outcome.
So here what I've done. Here's our outcome variable.
And I've been and I've shown a Bloks box plot of our input variable as it changes for the two versions, the output variable.
So we've got some much larger values here. And what's going to happen with these larger value?
One of the things that's gonna happen with these larger values.
Yes, it's useful that yes, it's useful that the values, the mean or the median is higher.
So it's going to. Yes. If for higher values, it's more likely to be a one on the outcome.
But we have a very, very large values. And you get. OK.
So you get some these a little bit lower. But you can. OK. We're gonna get one of these values its way up here at fifty.
You put that in your linear model. If on the off chance, that might be a zero.
It's going to jack the. It's going to push the numbers so far. Or the model output so far,
it's impossible for any other features to do anything to allow these extreme that these larger values to just completely dominate your computation.
So if you log transform, what you're gonna do is you're going to significantly decrease the skew.
It's not going to make our poor distributions perfectly symmetric. But the skew is going to be there's going to be substantially less skew.
There's going to be substantially smaller range. These values are a lot more comparable to each other.
And so the log we are looking at a difference of two here rather than about eight.
And we don't have the massively large values like the the top value here is only as large as four.
And so it really is going to make the values a lot a lot better distributed.
If you've got heavily skewed data, it's worth trying both a log transform and a square root transform,
just depending on how precisely the data is skewed. One might work better than another, but you decrease the skew, you decrease the range.
The values are a lot more contained. You don't the extreme values are still being collapsed down to a much more manageable range.
And this is. But we haven't lost the fact that a difference in this value is going to correlate with a difference in outcome.
We haven't lost the ability to use it to distinguish. We've just compressed, condensed that ability down into a more reasonable range of values.
So the resulting mathematical model is going to be better behaved. Another example is descript haisong.
So sometimes this might come from outside knowledge.
So one of the hints I've given you in the assignment is that you might want to disk critize term
so that greater than or equal to two hundred and forty months is considered a real estate loan.
We know that's a reasonable thing to do from the reading that came with the data set and explain what happens with the real estate loans.
You might also, as I said earlier, talk about going from greater than three stars to I liked it.
It can reduce the noise in the rating data. One sign that you might want to discuss ties.
If there's a non-linear response with a sharp change, it might be that you want rather than.
Trying to fit a continuous model may be the OK. There's this really sharp jump, a really sharp change at a particular point.
Let's let's turn that into a binary feature. One way you can think and sometimes what you might want to do is just split the data in half.
So your median becomes your threshold. You might want to look for an inflection point, increase in the response curve of some other variable to it.
One thing to note, though, is that discrimination can have very subtle effects on your model performance.
You have to be careful with it. If you're measuring all the things you're measuring about your model,
make sure you measure them after you change your disparate causation to see what happens as the results change.
So there's other transformations you can do to a box.
Cox or a power transformation learns a monotonic function of data to transform all your points quite a bit into something that's close to normal.
And effectively, you've learned the parameters of this transformation to optimize like with the objective function.
That is that back that minimizes its distance from normality and the distribution of the resulting form of the resulting data.
Psychic learned gives you methods for doing boxcutter, for doing power transformations, splain functions,
allow you to learn complex functions that don't have to be monotonic of a single variable.
We're not going to touch on them. I just want you to know that they exist.
But also sometimes we're going to need to deal with multi feature normalization. So we have a group of related features.
These might be we've got some of our features are accounts of different tack.
Like how often users have tagged the ah item with different tags.
And sometimes it's going to be useful to normalize those together that either some to one or they form a unit vector.
The sum of squares is equal to one. And this. This for the unit vector one,
it puts makes its that all of them are on a unit hyper sphere and so like you can compute similarities between them easily.
Distances become more normalized if it's word counts or tag count.
So if you if your features are how many times you've say you've got ten different tags and you allow users to tag it
with those tags or you have the Facebook emoji responses and users can respond with five or six different emojis,
and your features are how often they've responded to each of these emojis?
Well, there's two components of each of those features.
The two in the two components are how many people have interacted with this because if a million people interact with a message.
And five and a thousand people interact with a message or 10 people interact with the message.
They're going to have and the same fraction of them use the wow emoji.
You're going to have the feature values are going to be dominated by the popularity, not by the wow.
How much it's wow versus how much it's care or how much it's t.
It's cry.
And so if you make them some to one or if you turn them into a unit vector, then you make it to these features are no longer proxies for popularity.
But they are specifically. What fraction of the interactions are wow or cry or heart or care?
And if you all you probably also want to keep a popularity and there you.
There's a good chance you want to take take the log of it. But it really treant changes the meaning of the feature.
How many caires is a different feature from what fraction of responses work hair.
And depending on your modeling task, one of those might be a more useful model than the other.
And so you can get this multi feature normalization that you want to do together.
Another thing you can do with multiple features is an eye interaction term that we've seen a product.
You can combine the effects of two features by multiplying them together. And if they're numeric, then it's the product of them.
If one of them is logical or it's the dummy for a categorical, then effectively what it does is it turns on or off the other feature.
It gives you an F in your linear model.
And so B one two is the influence of if if X one is logical and B one, two is the influence of X two when X one is equal to one.
But if one is equal to zero, it just uses the default term.
B two X two. Now the effects are additive. So one X one is one.
The result is B two times. So if, if we have B two X two and we have B one two x one.
X two. And X is equal to one or X, one is equal to one, then the total coefficient.
On X two is Beda two plus beta one to.
And that's how you'd interpret it. You're going to go interpret the coefficients.
But this is a really useful way to allow a feature to have additional effect for some of the.
Additional linear effect for some of your of your data point and not for others.
Another one you can do as you can, computer ratio or a fraction.
And one example of this, if we're trying to model something that happens when students are in a class, again, this is a useful thing to do.
And you've got something that's dominated by popularity. You have to be careful with counts.
Counts from user activity often become really heavily skewed.
And if you've got anything that's a count of something, you really it's going to be dominated by popularity.
And it often times it's going to be more effective to separate popularity as its own feature
from how much of that popularity is being allocated to different things in your model.
So if a an x ray is the number of students in a class and X F is the number of first year students in a class,
and we want to understand like something about the B,
the impact of a class or the dynamics of a class based on what frat based on how many first years are taking it?
Well, a small class is going to a small number of first years and it's going to have a small number of students.
So we might take a ratio or proportion.
And so we might take the X, F, F for a fraction first year, which is the first year divided by the total students.
And that's going to give us the fraction of students for first year. And that allows us to build a model that rather than being.
I have two proxies for popularity. Number of students, a number of first years.
It allows us to separate. OK. What is the influence of having a lot of students in the class as a separate component of our predictive
modeling from what is the influence of having a large portion of the class being first year students?
And it also reduces our clinic already because X, say, at X, F are going to be quite highly correlated.
But X say an X, F, F probably won't or won't be.
At least they likely won't be unless larger classes are more likely to have more first year for a higher fraction of first years.
So it's another piece of the toolbag, an assignment five.
I give you a suggestion to possibly consider computing a ratio or a fraction feature.
There are other combinations we can do too, such as the difference. So if you take if you have a list of of actions, say,
forum posts or account transactions and you take the activity date minus the accounts creation date,
then what you get is the account age at the time of activity. And if you're trying to classify something that you're trying to understand.
OK, what is this more happened with new accounts. It allows you to make the feature rather than being when did the thing happen?
It allows the feature to be how established was the account when it was the account when it happened.
You then might want to describe disparities. It is this account at least a year old,
because it might be that established accounts of that established accounts are going to have different behavior than new accounts.
You might also want to some you want to combine with.
You can also combine with single feature transforms so you can do a product where one of the features is logged or square rooted or whatever.
So you can combine these things in arbitrary ways to get the final set of features that you need.
Actually, figuring out what are these you need to do takes practice and creativity.
I've given you a few hints. Look, to try to make things normal. Look to try to build linear relationships.
Look for hard jumps. Like if you if you haven't if you plot an X value and you plot a Y response, you see this jump at some point.
That suggests democratization might be useful. One thing that's super useful, though, is to read read other data.
Scientists working in Europe, brain working in other domains. If you're doing research, you should be reading papers.
Pay attention to what they do in their feature engineering. What features do they pick?
Why do they pick them? That can give you a lot of good ideas for what to go do when you're doing your own projects.
Also, it's important to note that you do all this feature exploration and design on the training data.
You don't get to look at your testing data while you're doing your feature exploration and development.
So to wrap up transforming and building features is a really important and powerful part of model building.
The model can only accept. So one of the things some deep learning models can do is do some of their own feature engineering,
like they can work with raw features and learn sophisticated functions of them on somewhat on their own.
That works well, very well for some domains, but for a lot simpler models.
The model can only work with the features you give it.
We're gonna see some techniques for automatic feature selection, but though they can't generate new features, they can.
If you if you give them a product, they can decide whether or not it's actually helping the model.
But they can't create the product. If you didn't give them product feature to start with.
So it's important to get your features right and to give your model a good set of features to work with.
Even when you're doing automated feature selection.