Though, in this video, I want to talk more about the workflow and the iterative process of model, building and refinement.
We talk about how to properly split training, tuning in evaluation data,
understand better what is and is not cheating for evaluating a predictive model.
So we're setting up our setup. So we split our testing data. We have our main dataset, all the data.
We split it into training data and testing data. And then on our training data, we print our model.
We experiment with different model designs, different features. We select hyper parameters.
We can do this based on the models internal goodness of fit statistics.
So you can if you're training a linear regression model, you can be looking at your R-squared.
You can look and be looking at your adjusted R-squared. You can be looking your AIC for a for logistic regression model.
You can be looking at your log likelihood or you can do it by testing, by running a classifier evaluation metric on some tuning data.
So you further subdivide your training data into train. Antoon.
Or you may do cross-validation where you split your training data into five or 10 pieces.
And for each piece you trade, the rest of the data, predict that piece and measure your metric.
You can do all of these things basically so long as you don't touch your training.
You're testing data. You can do whatever you want with your training data to better improve and understand your model.
Well, not all things are reasonable to do, but you can do it. You can do. You're not cheating with whatever you do there in your training data.
What you can't do is use knowledge from the testing data to refine.
Your modeling process, and this includes exploratory analysis of the testing data, because the idea here is that.
There is sort of the the motivation of what we're trying to do with this predictive
modeling is to build models that are going to be able to process new data.
So predicting our testing data isn't the point. If you're training something to detect.
Fraudulent transactions in your online gaming platform.
Your goal isn't to predict that like you're the purpose of your model is never to predict the fraudulent transactions in your historical data.
For the purpose of the motto is to be able to run it. And as new transactions happen, categorize them as likely fraud or not.
And so the goal of our evaluation is to simulate the model's ability to generalize to new data that it hasn't seen yet.
And the way we do this is we hide some of the data and pretend it's new.
And as soon as you allow this data that's supposed to be new.
If you're simulating what's gonna happen, if you run this for a week and try to classify the new transactions,
what you're doing is you're giving the model. Or the modeling process data that it's not going to be allowed to have in real life.
We call this leakage. Information leaks into the model than its actual application.
It's not going to be able to have in some ways, it's the opposite of the problem that we have when we're trying to give you tests in class and tests.
We say you can't have a textbook, you can't have notes, you can't use the Internet, answer these questions.
But in real life, you can use all of the reference material you want.
Anytime you want have to actually solve that problem. In practice, there's still value in internalizing.
A lot of it's that you can detect when you because you need if you haven't internalized a lot
of the knowledge that it's hard to detect when you're going to go need to look something up.
If you don't know that overfitting is a problem, then you don't know when you need to go read more about Overfitting.
You just don't even think about it.
But when it comes to actually doing things about things, you have all these resources available in machine learning.
We have the opposite problem. Because in real life,
the model is not going to have access to the test data because you're trying to use it to classify new transactions as they come in.
You're trying to use it to predict the purchasing behavior of users as they come in.
You're trying to use it to forecast the load that's going to be on your power grid or on your transportation network for a time in the future.
And you don't get to look ahead and see any of that information. So in the real world,
your model does not have access to any information about what it's trying to predict other than what it can learn from historical data.
And so if you do anything with your test data that leaks information about the unknown,
it's supposed to be predicting into your true model building process,
either learning the model itself or the process of figuring out what feature parameters and values and whatever are going to be useful for your model.
Then you effectively allow the model to cheat.
And it's going to get better and you reduce it's gonna get better performance than who actually will in reality.
And you reduce the ability of the evaluation process to simulate what you actually care about.
Can my model effectively predict how much traffic is going to be on the freeway in December?
Based on. Previous Decembers and on the date earlier in the air, like let's say we've got 10 years of traffic data.
Can I accurately predict what the freeway data is going to be this December?
You don't get to look at this December if you do. I think the physics department would like to have a word with you.
So. When we have within this setup, we have an iterative model process.
So with our training data, we can do exploratory analysis. We can try features and transforms.
We can try different hyper parameters, talking to a hyper print.
The parameters are what we learn in the model. Your logistic regression coefficients, those are parameters.
We learn them from the data. Hyper parameters are additional values that control how the model learning process works.
Oh, we can try different models like a logistic regression or random forest.
We can test effectiveness with the tuning set so we can take our training set, split it into tuning and real training.
We can do cross-validation, as I talked about, where we can split into many separate things.
Some of the circuit models Saikat learn models have built in selection for some of their hyper parameters using cross-validation.
Once you see regularization, you can pick the regular.
You can tell logistic regression c.v to automatically find the regularization strength using cross-validation on on your training data.
Then, though, you need to apply it to your test data. And a couple of things here.
First, you need to apply your feature transformations and combinations to your test data.
You have to apply them to test data because your model is built on these, your model, your linear model or whatever is built on these.
These transformed features. These combine features, all of your feature engineering.
The results of that are what the model is trained on. If you just try to apply the model to the raw data, it's not going to work.
It's not going to have the features it needs. But the difference is you apply the feature transformations, the test data,
but you don't use the test data to a site to test to assess which feature transformations are useful.
You did all of that in the training data. And you take that as a pattern or a recipe.
I'm going to show you in a future video how you can change Saikat, learn pipelines together to do this, to automate some of this.
If you aren't using. Saikat learned you might write a function that, given raw data,
will return transformed feature Saul or will you turn data with the final set of features?
That's a very good design as well. You just take this as a pre canned recipe and you apply it to your test data.
Then you run the model, predict the test outcome data and you measure accuracy precision area under the ROIC curve,
whatever measure you're going to measure of of your model effectiveness on those results.
The outcome of the iterative modeling process in the preceding slide, though,
is one model or possibly like one model from each of three or different families
that you want to finally evaluate for effectiveness using the test data.
So. A few, too, does kind of synthesize what I've been talking about here.
It's fine to split the training data and a small and additional subsets.
You can do train test things within your training process as an iterative process to figure out.
Does this does this feature give me? Does this feature transformation? Give me a more accurate classifier.
Will do a train tune split. Add the feature. Measure the accuracy on the tuning data.
Does it help? Does it not? Does a square root give me better give me better classifications or does a log give me better classifications.
Do that on splits of your training data and leave the test data alone.
Go put it on the shelf, lock it in the cupboard, whatever you're going to do with it. You can iteratively refining the models, predictive quality,
you can explore and test all of your features using, as I said, using cross-validation or using train,
using tuning splits of your training data,
allow you to use predictive accuracy as part of your decision for what features do include how to transform them,
how to construct new combinations, etc. Don't know if it was a once you then you take you take your model, you go, you run on your test data.
You don't get to go back and fix the model if it performs poorly on the test data.
That's what you need.
In get it to do all of those fixes, because as soon as you say, oh, it didn't perform on the testing data, let me go back and fix something.
Then you're giving your model development process access to information it doesn't have in reality.
And testing on that test data is no longer a reliable test of what's going to happen when your model meets new data in the field.
You also can't use the test data to inform model or future decisions, at least within the scope of one project.
You can't say you've got your project, your test data thing. You've got to learn things from that.
You're going to publish a paper.
If you're doing this for a graduate, research the results of that learning you're going to carry into the next project.
Arguably, that's that can induce a little bit of leakage because you or someone else is going to use them and they might work on the same dataset.
Get a different data set. Arguably, it's a little bit of leakage if they read your paper on your test data.
OK. We have these things on test data. I'm going to make a neutron test split of the same dataset and I want to do things.
Arguably, we have some leakage. We can't plug all the leaks. The goal is to have the goal is not to be perfect.
The goal is to have a good and credible emulation of the actual production environment for what
we're trying to do so that we have an effective test of our models ability to do its job.
And its job is almost never classify preexisting data.
And the trick in the test data. That's how we study the model's effectiveness.
But that's not how we deploy the model to improve our lives and improve our businesses.
Production systems often have new streams of test data coming in every day.
If you're doing online. If if you're doing an online.
Shopping center. If you are monitoring quality control processes in a chip fab you've gotten used to in the test data.
The things keep running next week, next month. And so you could knowledge from today's test data.
So you run things. You predict the month of October. You predict last December.
You're doing these tests on your models effectiveness. You run it.
You're predicting this coming December. It's fine to learn what you learn about predicting this December for next December.
There's no cheating. You aren't seeing next December.
You're accusing the year over year, the month over month, etc, trends to be able to predict what's gonna happen next December.
So in the industrial setting, because we can continually acquire new test data,
it makes some of the iterative problems that happen in academic research with a static dataset significantly less of a problem because.
OK, well, that's so I learned something from this project. What am I going to do next?
Project when next project you have new test data because your chip plant has been running for another two UTS.
You can use some of that data and your what you learn from the data you captured before, that isn't cheating at all.
It's a problem in academic research where we have a static dataset.
The movie lends data that wreck data edness pick your data set.
We're all working with test sets on the same data set. I read your paper.
And that's effectively a form of leakage. That's not a whole, as I said, that we can completely plug.
So we carry knowledge forward and we use what we learn that our test data for the next
project in production with new test data that comes from new runs of the system.
As I said, technical violation. But if we pick a new test sample, it's less of a problem.
We're all using the same test set. Then we have a real problem.
But we don't often have a choice when we're trying to do academic research with these data sets.
So to wrap up trend test splits are to help us test the model's ability to predict future unseen data that it didn't have a chance to learn from.
So we're doing what we've been doing here with this predictive modeling its machine, learning the machine that the system is learning about the data.
So we can generate predictions for future data. And we test it by giving it data hasn't been able to see using test data knowledge going back.
It's like making a loop and using knowledge from our test data to inform our modeling decisions, breaks down that barrier.
And it means testing on our test data is no longer an effective test of the model's ability to generalize to data.
It wasn't able to learn from. This isn't a problem within your training process.
The train tunes that like OK, train and try something, train data, see it on tuning data,
go back and keep doing with the same tuning data because we're not using the
tuning data results as the conclusive evidence of our model's effectiveness.
We're just using them for our own internal debugging. It's why we want to go see this model works better.
That we do that, then we go. We do that with the test data,
we're not allowed to go back because otherwise we're optimizing for our ability to predict that specific set of test data.
Which means predicting that specific set of tests we want is predicting that test
data to be representative of predicting data that we haven't been able to see yet.