This video, I'm going to introduce psychic learn transformers and pipelines that are going to allow
you to put your feature transformation and your modeling process into one pipeline that's
reproducible across your training and your test data learning objectives are for you to
be able to use a psychic learning pipeline to combine feature transforms and prediction.
So our data often takes the form conceptually of a pipeline.
We're going to transform some features that are going to fit a model.
And then in prediction, we need to transform the features and generate the predictions.
Both of these steps you have, the transformation, the transformation may have parameters, for example, the standardization that we talked about.
We have to learn the mean and the standard deviation that we're going to subtract and scale by in order to do the transformation.
And in the test data, we want to transform by the training data properties, not the test data properties, for two reasons.
One, they might be different to an actual production.
You don't necessarily have a whole batch of test data. If you've got a new.
So if you've got a new user coming to your online shop and you're going to predict for you want to
predict whether they're going to which of the three specials they're most likely to be interested in.
You just have this customer coming and you need to be able to transform their features to put them in the model
or the way you do that as you use the transformation parameters that you learned from the training data.
So Psyched Learn has an object called a pipeline that allows us to create a sequence of models.
And the typically this is one or more transformer algorithms or models followed by finally a regressive or a classifier or some other kind of model,
though, to output.
There's other things you can put in the middle, like Matrix decompositions and other things like that that we're going to see a little bit of later.
But if you have if you put this into a pipeline and then you tell and then you fit the pipeline, the pipeline exposes the fit method.
It will fit its inner models and it will transform the data through in sequence.
So if you've got so if you've got a if you've got a pipeline.
And it has a transform. And it has a classifier.
When you call fit, what it's going to do is it's going to, one, fit the data.
Or fit the transform to transform data. Using the parameters at Just Fit.
And then three fit the classifier. On the Transform data.
So it automates this process of managing your data pipelines.
So to talk a little bit about Transformers, the learned use case we've seen so far is that we train something on data with fit.
We give it our input features, we give it our output class, and then we generate predictions with predict transformers.
Add another modeled another function to this paradigm.
Transform some functions can do both transformation and prediction, but transform returns a copy of your input data with the features adjusted.
So if you fit so for the scale the standardization transformer.
Fitt. What it does is it computes. It computes X Bar and S and then transform.
Return. X minus X bar over s.
And it. It does this separately for each column,
for each of your input features is going to learn a separate mean and a separate scale for each of your input features.
But that's what fit and transform. And so you can then.
So if you fit the transformer and then you transform that, you can then use the transformed data as input to the next stage in the pipeline,
another transformer or your your final classification of regression model.
If you want to transform your columns differently, so Transformer's if you have a transformer, it's going to fly to every column in the asset column.
Transformer allows you to apply different transformations to different columns in your input data.
It's also one of the few Pay Saikat learn classes that actually knows about Panda's data frames.
And so you give it a list of triples, you give it name transformer and column triples,
and it will learn this transformer for these columns in this transformer for these columns.
And then there's a remainder option, which you can say either a transformer that apply to all of them or a drop or there's some other options as well.
And so what you can do is if you've got, say, three different categorical transfer functions, you want to do something.
Or call it you want to do something, too. And you have a number of numerics you can apply.
OK, here's one transformer for one of the the the categorical calls transformer
for another one and then remainder just standardize all my numeric variables.
Lets you do that conveniently. But the column I'm going to refer you to the documentation.
I've got links to the documentation in the notes for this week.
I'm going to refer you to that to learn more about how to apply column transformers, but they allow you to transform columns differently.
Some of the useful transformers that psychic learn gives you are the standard scalar that standardizes variables.
There's a power transformer that does power box or does box Cox style power transformations binary or
converts numeric data to zero one by applying a threshold's be one of its greater one out encoder.
We'll take a particle Virk Oracle variable. So a transformer is not limited to just returning one output column.
It can expand the column in the multiple columns. So one hot encoder.
We'll take your categorical column and it will return multiple columns by encoding
by dummy encoding the categorical variable and then the function transformer.
You can give an arbitrary function that will use that to transform the data.
So the Transformers, though, they only apply to features if you also need to transform your outcome variable.
The transformer target regressed classes. What you need to use and it does not go into a pipeline.
You could use it as the as the last stage of a pipeline or as a stage in a pipeline.
But it wraps an underlying predictors.
You pass a predictor and a transformer in its constructor parameters and it transforms the target before calling the predict method or the fit method.
And then if you when you call, predict it untransformed, the results, you get the results back out in the original scale.
So to wrap up pipelines, let us combine multiple data steps into a single operation.
One of the things this is really useful for is being able to apply your training data transforms to your test data.
You fit the whole pipeline that transforms. You're going to learn the parameters from the training data.
You then go apply them to the test data and it just does the right thing for you automatically.
Now, one thing you have to do throughout your work with Saikat learn is pay very close attention to defaults.
The defaults are not always what you expected.
You need to pay close attention to them in order to understand that the model is doing exactly what you think that it's doing.