But now it's time for a topic that I've mentioned a few times, when we're actually going to learn what it is, regularization.
So the goal here is for you to understand the function of regularization,
terminal lost function and apply regularization to your logistic regression models and then finally tune regularization parameters.
I want to start by reviewing MultiKulti Darity. So remember that if we have correlated predictors that can cause poor model fit.
So if we've got X1 and x2 and they cause why we've got this correlation between them.
We don't know particularly where the common affects, so we can have a look.
So we can factor this out as X one two plus X one plus X two.
Except we don't actually have X one to. It's hidden behind the wall.
Where does it. Where does its its value go when the coefficients?
Does it go on X one, does it go next to you split it between them?
The linear model itself has no way to determine where the common component should actually be allocated.
And so one way we can deal with this and several other problems is by introducing what we call a regularization.
So rather than just solving the problem, minimize lost function.
And so if this is a linear regression, this might be squared loss or suspect B squared error.
This might be negative log likelihood. Log likelihood is a utility function, a negative log likelihood to be a positive value,
because the log likelihood they're negative is a lost function. You want to minimize your negative log likelihood.
And what we do is we add to that another term, which is we call the regularization term.
And all it is, is it is a parameter of the regularization strength times,
the magnitude of our parameters lost function now as two terms, the error and the and the magnitude of the coefficients.
When we're doing the squared magnitude here, we call it the ridge regression.
So quick detour on some of the notation. I'm using a norm as a measure of the magnitude of a vector.
So when we say X, we say the L2 norm, which is indicated with the subscript two, there's called it L2 Norma Euclidean norm.
What it is, is it's the square root of the sum of the squares that the elements of the vector.
If you take the L2 norm of Y minus Z, that's the Euclidean distance between Y and Axis.
If they're two dimensional vectors, it's the straight line distance between them.
So if you've got Y. And you've got X, Y, Z.
It's the straight line distance between them, the.
And then we can square it. So subscripts two means L2 Naum superscript, two means square.
And that's the sum of the squares of the element. So we get rid of this square root and we get the some of the squares useful, really useful.
It it simplifies the computation just a little bit. And it's how the retrogression normalization is defined or regularization is to find the L1 norm.
Subscript one is the sum of the absolute values and we call this the Manhattan or taxicab distance
because it's the distance you would have to travel if you could only travel in straight lines.
So if you want to go from X to Y, it's the it's the total length of that path.
So but it's also it's also useful, some of absolute values.
I'll want to some of absolute values. L2 is the sum as the square root of the sum of the squares.
You can generalize to get other norms as well. But this is what this notation means.
The magnitude of the vector. And so when we build up this rig, we build up our regularized model the way we increase.
The. The way we increase this component, the loss.
Remember the way we want to think about it. One of the tools we want to use for understanding a metric is how do you how do you make them change?
How do you increase them or decrease them? And the way you increase or decrease this part of the lost function is you.
You increase the coefficient and that can happen where having a strong relationship
that can happen by putting more the common factor on one than another. So when you have this multiple linearity,
one thing the retrogression regression is going to do is it's going to encourage the
model to distribute the influence of the common factor between the different sub factors.
Because if I put it all on one, that would increase the square more than if it divides it evenly between the two,
the way you minimize the squares as you divide the common the common components evenly between the two features.
It's it's a part of and it gives us a solution. So a multi linearity our system is under determined.
We don't have enough information to know where the coefficient is by adding regularization to our to our lost function.
We introduce this additional this additional loss that.
Tells it where to put it. By making the least expensive solution be the one where it's evenly distributed between all of the correlated features.
So where do we have this lost function, we have our our error loss plus our coefficient strength.
We can minimize this in two ways. We can minimize it by decreasing our error and we can minimize it by having small coefficients.
And what effectively, though, what that means is in order for a coefficient value to be large, it has to earn its keep and it has to earn its keep.
By decreasing training error. If if if if you've got a minimum, if you if you've got a particular value,
we're going to try to try to increase the coefficient and increase the coefficient.
That might give us a lower error. We only get a lower total loss if it decreases the error by more than it increases
the coefficient after take into account square and our regularization strength term.
And it gives this it encourages the coefficients to be small values unless a large value contribute significantly
to decreasing the models error on the training data squared error or increasing its log likelihood.
We're talking about a logistic regression.
The regularization parameter lambda is what we call a hyper parameter because we don't learn lambda from the data in general,
like within a single linear model. We don't learn lambda from the data.
We have to come in from outside the exact impact. The value depends somewhat implementation details such as how difficult one thing is,
the loss function itself, a mean or a some different psychic models actually make it.
You can't just take a regularization term for once I get model and use it for another,
even if they're both doing L2, because other details of lost function mean the value doesn't transfer,
because if it's using a sum of squared error,
then the regularization strength needs to depend on the data side because for the same amount, for the same amount of average error.
The sum of squared error is going to be larger just for having more data.
If it's a mean, then it's going to then you're right, Visitacion term is not going to depend on your data size.
Some Saikat models also use a concentration parameter C, which is one over Lambda Lambda,
and it's multiplied by the error instead of being multiplied by the by the, the coefficients.
Because the strict parameters. So an increased value of lambda or a decreased value of C results in stronger regularization,
a coefficient has to contribute more to the model performance to earn the keep for for a large value than it does with weaker regularization.
Now one good way to learn to write a good value for Lambda is to optimize with the training and tuning split of the training data.
Saikat learned. We'll do this automatically if you use.
So a lot of the repressors also of a CVO class logistic regression c.v you're going to have REJ CV.
Quite a few others have a CV variant.
And what happens with the CV variant is it will learn values for one or more hyper parameters by doing Krait when you call fit with training data.
It will cross validate on the training data to learn and you can give it a range of Perama,
a range of hyper parameter values to consider a list of them.
It will do. It will do the cross validation to automatically learn good values, the best values it can for these regularization parameters.
There is also a class grid search CV that allows you to do hyper cross validation to search for good hyper parameter values,
for any parameter, for any hyper parameter for a psychic. Learn model.
I encourage you to go play with that at some point. But logistic regression CV will do that automatically just in the fit call within
itself's with all it'll find a good and a good regularization strength value.
So the lasso regression. This looks very, very similar, except every place, that square at L2, nor in the sum of squares.
With the L1 norm, we're now looking at some of the absolute values and so the Elst, the square, the L2 norm allows it encourages values to be small.
But if the value is close to zero, it doesn't like it's close to zero. Fine.
What the oh one naum one of the effects it has is it doesn't like small noun's zero values.
If a coexistent value was small as L1, Naum is going to push it to zero.
And what this does is it makes the coefficient spot what we call sparse, sparse data is data with a lot of zeros.
And so. If a coefficient is not contributing very much to classification, it's going to go to zero.
And you can use that to see which class, which features are actually being used in the classification.
And it effectively becomes an automatic feature selection technique because it's going to push the it's going to push the.
Coefficients for features that don't contribute very much to decreasing your training error to zero.
You can then put them together in what's called the elastic net, which combines L1 and L2 regularization.
And you have an overall regularization strength lambda that controls your regularization or Seage was one over lambdas.
What's going to multiply the loss function by sea? And then we have L1 regularization and L2 regularization.
And they're balanced and they're balanced with this parameter ro.
And so you could parameter Ryze. It's you just have your L1 strengthen your L2 strength.
But most elastic net implementations have a regularization strength.
Your out your lambda area C. And some of the psychic docs that use Alpha for this.
And then you have a balance that says how much of the regularization to put on a one?
And how much to put on L2 and these parameters both need to be chosen by cross-validation.
That's really the only way to find good values if you use logistic regression.
So logistic regression and logistic regression CVA can do elastic net.
There's also an elastic net and elastic net CV classes. And by default, if you use logistic regression CV, it's only going to use.
It's only going to search for the it's going to default L2 regularization and search for the regularization strength.
If you want elastic net, you change the penalty option.
You also have to change the solver because only one of the logistic regression can you several solvers to learn the logistic regression parameters.
Only one of them supports elastic net. And then you're going to need some additional options in order to tell it to also search for for that L1 ratio.
But it can do all of that for you.
I refer you to the documentation for though, with logistic regression, logistic regression, CV classes to see how to do that.
You're gonna find it useful in assignment five. I'm also gonna be giving you an example in the synchronous session that is dealing with some of this.
So some notes on applying regularization, though.
Regularization really works best when you're numeric variables are standardized because the coefficients.
It's it's looking at the total magnitude of your coefficient vector.
And if one of your coey if one of your features is in units of millimeters and one of your features is in units of KG's,
the coefficient values have nothing to do with each other. And so looking at the total magnitude, treating them as elements of a vector,
it becomes really difficult and it's going to penalize one just for having to have a larger range because of the underlying units.
If you standardize your numeric variables, then each one is in terms of standard deviation.
The coefficients become a lot more directly comparable with each other and your regression is going to be better be your your regularization
is going to be better behaved than you want to select your hyper parameters based on performance and the tuning getter and the CV classes,
as I said, get help with this. I'm giving you an example and one of the notebooks that does so give you an example,
a notebook that does uses logistic regression CV to do hyper parameter search for L2 regularization.
So you can see that in action with a simple example. So to conclude.
So to conclude regularization. Imposes costs on the model for large coefficient values, either large squared values, the large, absolute values.
Squared costs, which we call Rig Ridge Regularization, encourages values to be small.
Absolute value loss, so to call L1 or lasso regularization encourages small values to be zero.
If you put those together, it encourages values to be either zero or large enough to be meaningful, but not super large.
L2 regularization or Vage regularization is useful for controlling the effects of multicam linearity.
And together they're useful for decreasing your moral complexity. Allow making coefficient values to earn their keep.
Another way.
So another thing that they do is if everything's standardized or at least means centered, then small coefficients results in small effects.
And effectively what it means is assume everything's average. Unless we have enough evidence,
enough data to justify stronger beliefs and beliefs and stronger relationships that
are justified in terms of their ability to reduce our error on the training data.