Bo and this video, I want to move beyond logistic regression to talk about some additional classification
models and also introduce the idea of putting models in features for other models.
So learning outcomes are to do exactly what I just said.
So so far, we've been estimating the probability of Y equals one by using a linear linear model, a Y hat equals actually would logistic.
Of this. And we can use any estimate of this probability or we can just use models that output decisions,
these may be based on scores, the scores that aren't estimated probabilities.
For example, a support vector machine uses distance from either plane as its score.
But we're not limited to just using a logistic regression, of course.
So for one model, a decision tree is a tree of nodes where each node is a decision point.
So I made a little decision tree here for the grad student admissions example.
And at the first node, it's going to check if the GPA is less than or equal to three point four three five.
And if it's less, it's gonna go to the left hand side. And there's extra nodes here, but it's going to deny admission.
And if it's greater than three point four, three, five, it's then going to look at their class rank,
their school rank, and if their school rank is less than one point five, it's going to do.
It's going to admit. And if it's greater than one point five, it's going to deny.
Really simple model. It would be absolutely terrible to actually use this model for regression, for admissions decisions, but for predicting the.
But here we aren't. We aren't trying to build a model that will admit we're trying to build a model
is gonna predict whether someone is going to get admitted it might work. But this illustrates how the decision tree actually works.
They can learn complex interaction effects on their own because you can have the threshold.
And what happens with the features changes as you go down to the node? Now, one of the problems, though, they have high variance,
they can effectively memory memorize all of the training data by building themselves a lookup table that looks up the outcomes for training data.
By the by the feature values, you can get extremely good training, accuracy.
I trained one on this data with with unlimited feet, feature depth and I got training accuracy of over 99 percent.
And I got tested accuracy of point five to.
But a random forest, what a random forest does is it takes bootstrap samples by default psych, it learns random for us.
We'll take complete bootstrap samples. You can tell it to take smaller ones.
It's not actually a bootstrap sample, but it's a subsample of the dataset. And it fits a decision tree to that sample.
And then it does that 100 times or however many times to get a bunch, you get one hundred decision trees.
And then for a final classification, when you tell it to predict what it's going to do is it asks all of the decision, trees to vote.
It's building up this random forest of happy trees. They're happy because they have a functioning democracy.
They all get to vote on the final outcome. And the random forest takes the vote and returns the majority of the classification.
Or if the if the individual values are producing scores, that it then it might average the scores and use that as an output.
So but you build up, you decrease your variance.
That you would get from training, it is, isn't she, on one set of data training decisions and another set of data by train?
The decision tree on a bunch of sets of data by sub sampling your training data and then averaging over that in order to produce your final output.
Brandon Forest is one of the classifiers that I want you to use in your assignment.
Another thing, though, that I want to introduce is that feature output features don't have to directly come from data.
So a lot of our features are going to come from data.
But sometimes they're when they come from other models, sometimes they're a transformation model, some kind of what we call unsupervised learning,
where it's computing things,
but it doesn't have an output class that it's that's known that it's trying to predict or prediction models for other tasks.
For example, in link to end their job ad recommender, the last I knew just a few years ago, it was it was at a high level.
It was a logistic regression. You're going to LinkedIn. It says, here's a job ad for you.
Well, that's coming from a logistic regression.
But that logistic regression has very complex features, some of which are the outputs of other machine learning models.
And so you're gonna get features from the job text, the job description features in the user's profile.
One particularly interesting feature they use is a transition probability estimate.
So they have a model. This is another. This is a statistical model that tries to predict.
So if you are currently working and Boise as a data scientist,
what's the likelihood that you would transition to a job title of senior data scientist in Salt Lake City?
And so it takes into account job transitions like data.
Scientists might leave the senior data scientists, software engineers to staff, software engineers or principal software engineers.
It takes into account current migration patterns in the industry and various things like that to get this.
How likely are you to even go move someone at a staff?
Software engineering position is unlikely to take a job that where the title is Junior Software Engineer.
And the output of this transition probability model is one of the input features to their logistic regression that's computed.
That's estimating. Would you like to see this job ad for a senior data scientist in Salt Lake City?
Also, you also get things where you might have might come from some kind of a deep learning thing,
a deep learning object detection mechanism, a deep learning image similarity mechanism.
So Pinterest gets a lot of mileage out of doing nearest neighbor calculations where the the neighbor nearest
is defined by a deep learning model for assessing whether two images that are being pinned or similar.
So we can there are many different models that we can look at.
Linear models with their extensions, a generalized linear model and the logistic regression that we've been seeing, generalized adaptive models.
There's also thing the support vector machine, which is another linear model, but it's not a regression model.
The naive, naive Bayes classifier, we're going to see those later, a neural net.
Whether shallow or deep, a lot of models, pretty like a lot of neural nets.
They do a similar thing in logistic regression. They're computing a score and then you pass it through a logistic function or some other sigmoid in
order to convert the model score to probabilities for making your final classification decisions.
So wrap up. There are many different models for classification and for regression.
I'm just the my goal in this class is to teach you what regression and
classification are and how to get started with applying them and evaluating them,
not to teach you a bunch of models in depth.
The machine learning class is going to go into a lot more about how these different models work and how to get them to work.
Well, model outputs also, though, can be features used as input features for other models, often linear.
Not always, though. And so you can get models that build on top of other models.