Oh, in this video, I want to talk with you about inference from auto effectiveness and introduced the idea of an inflation study.
So our goals are for you to be able to make inferences about model accuracy and underpin
understand a little bit better the interplay of cross validation and inference,
remembering that we can't be perfect. The goal is to do a good and an incredible job.
And then also to be able to use an ablation study to make inferences about the particular
contributions and value of different features or subsets of your subcomponents of your model.
So remember, we've got this train test split training.
We have the training data. We're doing all of our iterative process.
It's a big, loopy thing. And then we've got we evaluate our effectiveness.
One thing we haven't talked about yet is, is the is the effectiveness significant?
To go and wait for our test data, we have a few outputs.
We have the individual classifications of predictions and four classifications we have, whether they're right or wrong for predictions,
we have the error and then we have a metric value, accuracy, precision, etc. for each classifier.
One of the challenges is, though, for the classifier and the test data, we just have accuracy is point nine nine or precision is point four.
We can't significance test that value.
But I want to talk in order to set up how we can significance test, I'm first going to or otherwise do inference, I should say, because significant,
significant testing, as we discussed earlier, a lot of times we might actually care about like an effect size estimate with confidence intervals.
A lot more than we care about significance test.
But there's a few questions that we want to answer as the results of an evaluation. What does my classifier perform better than some benchmark value?
Well, you might have a value we want to beat, say, a value we know was good enough.
And we want to know if my classifier performs better than that value.
We might want to get an estimate of our classifiers, accuracy or precision or recall our pick our metric that has a confidence interval on it.
So we know how precise ice this estimated performance measure is.
And then we may also want to answer the question, is classifier A perform better than B?
Maybe B is our current system, or B is the existing known state of the art.
And we want to know if A does better. We might want to p value.
We might want a confidence interval for the improvement or the difference in performance between A and B.
So. To get started one way, we can compute a confidence interval.
We can treat each item as a binary measurement. So you are each test item.
So you've got hundred thousand test items because you've got a very large dataset.
And hundred thousand to 20 percent split. Or it's a 10 percent split.
You've got a million data points, one 100000 test points for each of these.
You have the true value. Yes or no. You have prediction. Yes or no.
If the metric denominator comes from the test data accuracy, it definitely does, because the denominate because accuracy is correct overall.
You can also do this for false positive ratio, false negative ratio.
Recall specificity, anything where the denominator is completely determined by the test data, not by the classifier results.
You can use a Willcocks confit or a Wilson confidence interval.
Stats models does this with proportion confident and a Wilson confidence interval is a confidence interval for a proportion.
Any metric you can bootstrap that you can take your to your test samples, you can do.
You can take bootstrap samples of them and then you can compute your classifier metric over your bootstrap samples.
Now, you have to be careful when you're doing your bootstrap samples to make sure that
when you're sample you're when you're doing the bootstrap and you keep the labels, the ground truth labels and the classifier outputs together.
And if you're doing multiple classifiers, you have to keep all the classifier outputs together as you're computing these bootstrap samples.
You can bootstrap from your test data and get a confidence interval for any of your classifier performance metrics.
You can also do a computer P-value for the accuracy metric. This specific technique only works for accuracy.
It does not work for any of our other classifier metrics. But you can get a P value for the null hypothesis that the two classifiers have the same
accuracy by using what's called a contingency table and a contingency table for this purpose.
You have you go from reclassifications to whether or not it was right or wrong.
So. Here we have the number of times both classifiers were right in here, the number of times they were both wrong.
And here we have where classifier one was right and classifier two was wrong.
How often did that happen? We can do the same the other way around.
And then we compute. What we do what's called a McNee ma test, and it uses these values and NY n is the value and one is wrong.
And two is right. And then why is. One excuse excuse me.
And this is. So here we have an.
And why? And here we have. And why an.
And so we take the squared difference and the their wrongness is and divide it by the sum of their wrongness is and this gives us a statistic.
And my test statistic and under H zero under the null hypothesis and follows what's called
a chi squared distribution with one degree of freedom to probability distribution,
you can get CGF from stat's models or from sci fi.
And you can use that to compute a P value. What's the probability of having an MS statistic, at least this large?
And it's it's you don't have to deal with absolute values on it because it's it's a non-negative statistic in a non-negative distribution.
We can't just. There is something called a proportion test, but proportion test is for independent proportions and independent samples.
But we don't have independent samples. We have one sample of our test data.
And for each test point, we have two measurements, class of a classifier one and classifier two.
So we can't use a proportion test.
But the Mackney MA test basically that says do this paired proportion test kind of thing and allows us to get a P value for whether this classifier,
whether the classifiers have the same accuracy or not.
And this one, the P value, does not allow us to reject the null hypothesis that they have the same accuracy.
The P value is about one. So.
We can also test regression. So each sample is a continuous measurement of the model's prediction error.
So we have Y minus Y hat Y.
I from C one for CROSSFIRE a. And we have Y minus Y.
Hat I. From Classifier B. And those are two different measurements,
we can use a paired t test or we can use an appropriate bootstrapping mechanism in order to assess the accuracy of a regression model.
Now, when we have when we do a cross validation, so one technique, the sun, sometimes you do cross validation, say 10 tenfold cross validation.
That gives you 10 accuracy's for each classifier and you can compute paired t test.
So each of your each of your folds and your cross validation is a sample.
Is one data point in your sample. So you've got N equals 10.
You can do a T test that actually doesn't work very well because your your samples are not independent.
If you're doing capable cross validation.
Also if you just repeatedly draw a 10 percent sample and draw a 10 percent sample and do that, say, 30 times,
you also have the same problem of the same data points are going to show up and you're sent to monitor your samples.
Also, your training data classifiers are being trained in the same data too much.
And the ideal is to be able to draw, say, 30 completely independent training and testing sets from your big population.
But yeah, but if you can't do that, you're trying to simulate with cross validation,
you wind up with the non independence just causes the resulting come statistical test to not be reliable.
One thing you can do is you can do repeated cross validation where five times you do a two fold cross validation.
I'm going to refer you to one of the readings I put in the notes for a lot more details on this.
Just wanted to bring it up so that, you know, it's there. Cross-validation is sometimes used for final evaluation.
You'll find this in papers sometimes.
One of the problems, though, is this allows data leakage because you're testing on data that was available and you're trying it.
You're testing on all of the data data that was available in your training set.
This is a this can be a significant problem if we've got a large enough data
set that we can just use a single test split or maybe two or three test split.
That's going to allow us to much better simulate to avoid leakage, much better simulate what's going to happen.
We put the model in production. Cross validation is really useful for a couple of contexts.
One where you're not doing much model design or feature engineering. You just want to take you have data.
Want to take a model. Apply it, see how it works. Cross-validation is great for that.
You're not. You don't have the iterative process of how am I really getting this model to work?
You can cross validate if you've got hyper parameter search,
do a hyper parameter search separately for each needful, like make it part of your training process.
Logit like that logistic regression c.v kinds of things. Help with that.
But if you've got a model and just want to see how well it works in the data, cross-validation can work pretty well.
Also with when you are doing cross-validation on the training data to iteratively, do improve your model and feature design.
That can work really, really well as well. The problem arises when you're doing a lot of engineering on your model.
And you get access to the test data, which you effectively have on a cross validation setup.
Because even if you've got it's your say you do 10 cross-validation, do you pick one of them that's gonna be your.
That's gonna be what you're really doing, your development? Well, all of your other test data is in this.
This initial development part.
So it's part of how you're effectively you're using the test data as part of your tuning process for your hyper parameter selection,
as part of your exploratory data analysis. And that that is a cause of leakage.
Again, though, I guess. We're can never be perfect, but it's important to be aware of as a cause of leakage.
I really recommend having the designated test set that you hold out.
You don't touch. That's the basis of your evaluation. Even if it makes the statistical inference a little bit harder.
Now, another thing, though, I want to talk about is suppose.
So let's suppose you've got a complex model and we've got we're detecting spam where we're working for, say, a.
Telecommunications company were detecting text message spam or were detecting an e-mail spam for any mail company.
We have text features. We've got made a day to features when they're sending you are else.
You've got features of the you are all itself. Maybe we even hit the server.
Let's say we've got another couple of sophisticated models that do that score.
You are else by their reputation and they're sent and also score senders by theirs,
by a reputation score that large e-mail search spam, antispam efforts such as the one built in the GMAT.
I'll do this. I'm not just making that up. It's a part of of antispam at scale is building reputations for you are else and centers.
And we've got let's say art, let's say our spam detector works well. Precision of ninety nine point five or ninety nine point nine.
Recall of 80 percent. But what makes it work?
Which of these features is contributing, how much to its success?
The answer is to do what's called an oblation study and an oblation study takes our model.
We take our whole model. We see how accurate it is, but then we turn off individual features of it.
So we might turn off the sender reputation. How what how exactly you turn off depends on the model design.
It might be if it's an honor. You just take that part out of your neuron, that graph syllogistic model, you know, everything's well standardized.
You can put it zeroes for the feature and not retrain or even just take that term out of the model,
trying to on your training data and try to predict your testing data. And what this lets you see and you probably want to do that just in case.
Just to make sure the parameters are being tuned without the peace. What does that seat you see, though, is how much each component contributes?
You can say, OK, my model gets ninety nine percent precision on spams and it gets 98 percent precision if I turn off the sender reputation.
Well, that lets you see, OK, the sender reputation is responsible for one percent of my precision.
Now, it's important to be careful how you use this, because you can use this for production decisions and for future work.
You do this oblation study, you discover, OK, the center reputations only contributing 98 or one percent,
or maybe it's contributing point one percent. And it's really expensive in terms of compute time and engineer time to maintain maybe stop using it.
You could also use it for your future research work. What you can't do, particularly within the scope of one study,
is use the results of your oblation study to go back and revisit your model design that gets you your leakage again.
As again, as I said in the academic setting,
we're doing multiple studies in the same data that we do get some leakage and we carry it forward to the next study.
We again, we can't be perfect, but.
There's a difference between the oblation study and the feature engineering, the feature engineering, I'm trying a bunch of things that keep things.
I'm not going to keep things up doing it with this tuning data. Things are going back. I'm not being keeping my careful firewalls.
In the oblation study, I have my top line performance monitor. Here's my model, I ran it.
It got 99 percent precision and then. I'm trying to understand.
Well, what are the drivers of that? I'm not putting it iteratively back into my life.
Going back and rerunning my my stuff in my training data with it, I'm just using it to get knowledge to carry forward.
That doesn't cause leakage within the context of the specific study we're talking about.
And it is of acceptable practice.
And it's a very, very useful practice for understanding the contributing factors to the performance of a complex model.
So wrap up inference for classified performance is not immediately straightforward.
There are several helpful techniques that pointed you here at pointing to you two in the readings and be careful about data leakage.
But again, sometimes tradeoffs are.