So in this video, I want to talk with you about dates,
learning outcomes are for you to be able to pass and transform dates and adjust dates using date offsets.
So first, I want to talk just briefly about the difference between a date as we say it, like.
OK. It's November the 3rd, 2020 and underlying time.
So dates to all kinds of funny things. When we change to or from Daylight Savings Time, we skip an hour or we repeat an hour.
But the underlying time stream doesn't repeat.
It's just that our way of mapping that to the way we write it down repeats.
So we can think of underlying time as moving forward at a constant rate.
Generally, there's relativity and all of those things.
But the time is moving forward and how we record it changes and is complex and subject to a lot of rules.
The key thing is like with text being different, like the text content is different from its encoding.
Time is different from its representation.
Well, one of the implications this says, is that we typically store time in more of its monotonic form, like seconds since a particular date, UTC.
And then we translate for presentation. And so you'll see your store the time it offset UTC and then you will you'll translate
that to the local time zone with all of the daylight savings rules and everything,
we are going to go actually display it.
So internally, there are a few ways we can represent time numerically, and sometimes you'll need to do this yourself.
So one one is Unix timestamps, which is time since or before that can be negative.
Midnight, UTC, January 1st, 1970. Often this is stored in seconds.
Pythons like not in pandas or not pie, but Python, the Pathfinder standard library tends to do time and second floating point seconds since midnight.
The reference point, as I said, the reference point for this is UTC. You can also store at milliseconds or nanoseconds since that time.
If you have a data, if you have a data file that has a file, a column that's labeled as a timestamp and it's an end.
It's a number. There's a very good chance it's a Unix timestamp. That's very common way to store dates and times.
We can also store Julian Day numbers, which are days since January 1st.
Forty seven 13 B.C. And you can you you can store a time by using a floating point numbers,
it might be twenty two million, three hundred and seventy five point eight days.
There's also other origins. You can use a lot of different origins. Pandas actually lets you specify arbitrary origins.
But the nineteen hundred system that's used by Excel and other spreadsheets stores days since January 1st.
Nineteen hundred. So we can also store data strings, so the ISO format is year, month, day.
This has the nice advantage that at least until the year ten thousand.
It sorts by date. If you sorted Alphabet Alpha numerically, it's it's going to sort the resulting dates by date.
So if you're going to name files after dates, this with dates at the beginning of the file name.
This is super useful.
There's also localized numeric forms such as eleven three, twenty twenty, which is how we write the dates in the United States, Europe and the UK.
Right. Generally right at day, month, year three. Eleven, twenty, twenty.
So if you see a date that's two digits, two digits year, that's not enough information to know when we're talking about.
Are we talking about November 3rd or are we talking about March 11th?
You need to know the country locale in which the date came from to know how to correctly interpret it.
Sometimes you can infer it by looking for, say, November twenty eighth,
because 28 isn't a valid month number that I'll let you figure out which one you're dealing with.
But this localized form, just if you get a date, it's often ambiguous.
You could also have longer string forms like you did right out November 3rd.
Twenty Twenty Panels provides a function called Date Time 64 that allows you to store dates and times.
And even if you just have a date, you usually store it. It's a date time with midnight.
At least that's how you work with it. And pan those pandas doesn't have a time free date type.
You can create a date time from number and units as an origin.
So you can say we want. We want two hundred and thirty million.
Seconds since the Unix epoch, we want three point eight million second days since the Julian Origin D Funk.
This function also supports the number can be a series or an array in addition to a single numbers.
You can create a series or an array of pand date time objects.
You can also convert it from a string. This also can be up a series or array of strings.
So in an assignment, if you've got it, if you've got a column that string dates,
you can convert that to a column of date times by using these functions.
And by default, it's going to pass the time for my S.O.
But you can also tell it to pass other time, but providing a format string that describes how the time is laid out.
And there's a link in the pandas documentation to the way these format strings work can also be provided.
That link in the notes that go with this video. Then so we've got daytime's pandas has also had an object called a Time Delta,
which stores of a difference between two times, if you subtract one date time from another,
what you're going to get as a time delta,
you can create one from a number of plus units or a string that describes that like I can create the the the time delta one day,
thirty minutes and twenty two seconds. The time Delta marks advances in linear times.
You can't create a time delta for example, of one month. The date offset is what you use to get one month.
So it's you can create it from a number and units and it correctly offsets the dates,
even if you it knows it can know whether it needs to extend by 30 days or thirty one or twenty eight.
It handles Daylight Savings Time, a Hannahs leap year, a handle's leap seconds and deals with being able to offset dates properly.
Date Offset does not natively support series, so date times and time deltas, both native pandas natively supports them in series.
You can't, however, create a series of an object series that contains data offsets.
So if Month series is a series of numeric series that contains numbers of months, then we can use apply.
And it's it's it's a little slow because it's doing a python loop effectively.
But we can use apply to convert these data, offset these numbers of month into data, offset objects.
We get a series of those which we can then say add to add to a series of date times in order to produce offset date times.
For example, to add if we've got a column that has the term the number of months on loan is for and when the loan was issued,
we can add we can convert the month to a date offset. Add it to the issue date and we can find when the loan is due.
When you're doing arithmetic with dates, if you add a date time and the time Delta,
you're going to get a date time, date time plus a tight offset is also a date time. You could subtract as well as add.
As I said, if you subtract two date times, you're gonna get a time Delta.
You can also multiply a date offset by a number and it's going to give you another date offset that's multiplied.
So you can if you've got two months, you can multiply it by five and you'll get 10 months.
You can also compare you can compare date times using comparison operators.
You do need to create date times on both sides. If you've got something that say strings, you need to convert it to a date time object.
So then you can do the comparison. So in conclusion, dates and times are typically stored internally using offsets from an origin.
Usually store. Usually we store them in UTC and then we translate them to local time.
When we go on display. PANDAS provides a number of functions and types for working with dates and times.
In addition, NUM Pi provides some of its own. I generally work with pandas, but not PI does provide time.
Delta date time objects at work just a little bit differently. Python also does it its standard library for our purposes.
I recommend generally sticking with the pandas ones.