Oh, again. Now going to talk about how to start processing unstructured data, particularly text data.
So this video, we're going to introduce the idea of processing unstructured text, unstructured data modeling,
going to understand a little bit about some of the different types of features we can try to extract from unstructured data.
So so far in this class, we've been dealing primarily with tabular data, fully structured data of various forms.
Or we have for each instance, we have an equivalent set of features. Some feature values might be missing.
Well, we've got all of these features.
As I just as we discussed earlier in the class, there's additional types of data, semi's structured data has defined fields got,
but they can vary significantly in terms of what fields we get for what objects and unstructured data doesn't have defined fields.
There may be these aren't mutually exclusive.
You might have some unstructured data like text or images that have structured or some a structure made, a data that come with them.
You can treat the meta data just like we treat or other structured data.
But we're gonna be talking this week about how to start working with the unstructured data.
So to get features from data, there's a few things we can do.
We can get raw features so we can get words. For example, we got text.
We might say, well, the words are features and the values associated with those features say are the number of times the word appears.
We've got image data. We've got pixels. Then we can get some features that are readily convert to a readily think.
We can think of them in some ten tabular form, like size or length like this.
The number of characters in a document is a feature. We could also use additional models like there's a sentiment and sentiment inference models that
will try to determine if a sentence or some text is positive as a positive or negative sentiment.
In other models that we can apply in order to compute additional features from some of our raw data this week we're going to be processing and strong,
unstructured text using words as features. The result will be tabular.
You'll have a column for each word, but we're going to be using words as features no when you use it to build classifiers.
There's an example notebook in this week's material that walks you through Luke using
the topics that we're learning in the videos to build a classifier for email spam.
So to wrap up unstructured data doesn't come with the nice data frame style features.
You don't get the rows and the columns that are all set up. You can do nice math on the columns.
We're gonna directly use content is a large feature space and we're using words as features.
We have as many features as there are different words in the content. We'll also see how to derive.
We also set up to be able to derive smaller set of features from the data.