This video I'm going to talk with you about Unicode and Encodings. How is text actually represented and stored?
We talked a while ago about encodings and codings for different kinds of data.
We forecasted that we're going to talk about text we've seen in some of our initial processing.
Occasionally we need to provide an encoding. What's up with all of that?
So learning outcomes for the video are few. To understand how text is stored in memory and in files,
encode and decode text for storage and communication and to distinguish between characters, code points and bytes.
So we have text, we have some input. We have say here with a first sentence of the book, The Trial by Franz Kafka.
Someone must have slandered Josef K for one morning without having done anything truly wrong.
He was arrested and this was a sentence of the English language.
It's a sequence of words. It's a sequence of characters. And we store it as a sequence of bytes encoding those characters.
Computer has to store everything in byte. We've talked about how you start flooding poll numbers a little bit here where the text is stored in bytes.
So for a long time in U.S. based computing, we stored text in what was called ASCII, the American Standard Code for Information Interchange,
and it assigned a number in the range zero to one hundred and twenty seven seven bits for all the English letters.
A number of symbols and control codes.
You'll find the numbers in in range 48 to fifty seven uppercase letters go from sixty five to ninety or lowercase from ninety seven
to 122 etc. to sign these codes that we could store in bytes and just the lower seven bits of the byte so you could use the top,
the upper bit for for other control purposes. It was able to store written English text using most of the characters and punctuation.
That's in common use. So few problems with this one.
The whole world doesn't speak English,
and we need to be able to encode a lot of different languages for our languages that use Latin, insert Latin or Cyrillic alphabet.
This is often able to be done with extended code pages. So Latin one extends ASCII, so the number zero through to 127 are ASCII, 128 through 255.
So when a bit in a bite, this is the difference where whether the first bit is set or not, the high order bit, is it set or not?
Are for used for characters with Western European accents and some control characters, Latin fifteen does the same with Eastern European windows.
Twelve fifty two combines both.
It's compatible with Latin one, but it uses a range of characters that Latin one reserves for control codes to store the Eastern European accents.
Califate eight are uses the uses the upper one hundred and twenty seven characters for
Russian Cyrillic characters and so allows you this to store Russian and English in KEYT r.
But many languages, such as Chinese, Korean, Japanese,
they have many more characters that can fit in a bite even if the entire bite was allocated to it.
And so you use a double bite in code.
A multi byte character set often uses two bytes per character, such as Big Five for traditional Chinese and Jeab twenty 12,
which is the Chinese national standard for simplified Chinese, and it also covers Russian.
Now for a sequence of bytes that's text. In order to properly interpret this text, you have to know the encoding.
So that's one problem. It's another encoding in order to decode it properly.
Also, it's very hard to mix encodings and therefore languages because if you've got text that's encoded in GIBI twenty three.
Twelve. Well, you can't write Turkish on that. So if you've got a document that you're trying to have parts in Chinese and parts in Turkish,
you have to have a way to switch back and forth between code pages within a single document gets very complex.
And so Unicode was developed to try to unify these.
Unicode is an international standard for text representation in which text is represented as a sequence of what's called a code point.
These code points basically can think about. You can think of a Unicode text string is an array of code points.
These are code points are encoded into bytes.
And so here, again, as we saw with other data types, there's this distinction between data and it's encodings.
We actually kind of have three levels here because you've got characters code
points and then the bytes that are used to actually store the code points.
We have universal encoding that can encode all valid Unicode. And as I said, we've got the other encoding that have historically been used.
Latin, one U.S. ASCII califate are they have been redefined as encodings for subsets of Unicode.
So if you if you want to process KEYT are in modern program,
what you do is you decode the K away eight R and Unicode process Unicode and then you can read encode into whatever.
Now not all encodings can take all characters.
So if you try to encode Russian text into Windows twelve fifty two, it will fail because Windows twelve fifty two doesn't have the Cyrillic alphabet.
Unicode is intended to cover all nonfictional human languages, so it includes.
Any in the goals include any characters use to write any human language spoken today,
it includes ancient languages that are no longer spoken, such as it has Phoenician characters.
It includes a lot of things like mass symbols, the international phonetic alphabet emoji and a lot of other symbols.
You'll sometimes find the people using these for various strange effects, like to get a italics in a tweet or something.
What it's actually doing is it's going and grabbing naff characters and using those,
if you want to see sometime, use your computer's assistive technology to read aloud such content.
And you'll see here what it's doing under the hood.
And it winds up being very, very difficult for for visually impaired users to engage with because the read aloud is gonna be completely mangled.
But you've got a lot of different symbols across the space that are being used for human communication.
Unicode specifically does not include fictional languages. You're not going to find clicking on our Elvish characters in Unicode.
People have there are portions of Unicode that are reserved for private use force of software, and there are people who have mapped,
cling on or Elvish characters into those into those code points and then developed fonts that are capable of rendering them,
but they're not part of the Unicode standard. So to store all of this, python has two string types.
The SDR is a text string when you write a string. This was your single or your double quote.
This is what you get. You get a text string and a string is a C ATEC string is a sequence of code points.
So SRF seven is going to return the eighth, the eighth character or code point does its character and does it as a single,
does it as a string of a single character.
But the Owada function o r d will then get you the numeric code point from one of these single character strings.
Bites as a bite string. And here it's a sequence of eight bit bites.
If you ask for B.S. subset of a bite string B.S. and you have four B.S. up seven,
you're going to get the eighth bite in the strings and start from zero. You can convert between them with the end code and decode function.
So ENCODE takes a text string and encodes it to bytes. Decode takes a bite string and decodes it to stir.
And both of these you need to provide the Kodak, the name of the Kodak that you want to use UTF eight ASCII,
Latin one big five, whatever Kodak it is that you want to use.
Pandas also provide string types historically for pandas one, and it's still supported and still the default,
you would use an object series to stat stores, python strings, either bite's or Sturr objects.
Pandas can work with both pandas also now has a string type.
You can convert an object type storying strings to a panda string type.
You can also convert a you can also use the string D type when you're loading CSC as V file and then it will.
Lowden's a panda string, Cullom, both of them. The pandas has these.
These families have access of type specific methods and accessors that stirred up whatever four
strings that works on both the objects Cyle Strings series and the the new string data type.
So, as I said, to encode and decode, you have a python, you can do bytes that decode,
insert and encode panda series also provides, encode and decode operations off of this Sturr accessor now.
So you've got these strings. They're sequences of code points. How do those relate to characters?
So the code points in the simple form. The code points record the numeric values used for different characters.
So if I write Joseph K, the name of our character from the.
From the sentence at the beginning, it's going to be recorded as this sequence of code points for A as J.
O is six F SS seven three E six five.
These are in hexadecimal. These are hexadecimal numbers. So that abiders. Exactly.
To two digits. And any character that's in Latin one.
So in terms of letters, it's English letters, it's Western European accent.
Their code point is the same as their Latin one encoding number. And so the ASCII numbers are there.
Unicode code points for the Western European accents. Their Latin one by value is is the Unicode code point.
So O with an mail out is F six use an amount is F c.
And so we get these accented characters being stored this way.
But code points and characters don't necessarily have a one to one relationship.
So if we have Motley Crue and it's we can encode it, as with the O is the, um, lot of SSX that is the character O with Rumaila.
But you can also encode. You can also store that same character as two code points, six F, which is O and three oh eight which is combining diary sis.
And so what that does when it sees that sequences.
Oh. And then it says OK, complete combining diaries is and put the diaries is on top of it.
These combined there are a lot of things combining characters that can add accents.
They can stack on top of each others. You can stick like diaries. Is Anatoliy around a hat or whatever?
If you see sometimes people writing text has like stacked accents coming off the tops and bottoms that supposed to look like Lovecraftian horror.
They're doing that with these combining the characters just stack more and more, combining characters on top of each other.
They can also, in some cases, modify the shape of a character. They can assemble complex emoji.
There's some other use cases as well.
But code points have can have these relationships with code point can modify code points that come before in rare occasions after.
So you don't when you ask a string for its length, that's gonna give you the number of code points, which is not the same as the number of characters.
So if you did if if we had Motley Crue stored this way and you did a LAN on it,
you're gonna get 13 instead of 11, even though it's only going to print eleven characters.
You're going to get you have 13 code points. This does let you assign lots to characters that don't commonly have them, for example, diaries.
The diaries of the unallowed is usually only applied to. Disavowals.
And so if you want if you want Spinal Tap. You need to use an which is going to be six B and you need three O eight.
The combined guy races, there are a few human languages that do use this character, but they have not added a pre combined character,
Unicode, and they don't need one because you can make one out of the raw end and the combining character correction.
This is not six. This is six e. So one a complex use for these are complex emojis.
So emoji can have a number of modifiers and layers on top of them.
And so if you have the woman with dark skin tone, running emoji.
The skin tone is actually amplify entered as a Unicode combining modifier.
And so this this emoji here is actually made up of six or a five code points in sequence runner.
The modifier for dark skin tone, a joint character, the modifier for female or the character for female.
And then the another character, which means display as emoji rather than text.
And it puts all of those together to get a woman running with dark skin tone.
The politics of this in terms of what's the default and what's the default for different emoji are interesting and worth contemplating.
But you can use but this idea of being able to combine code points allows you to build up arbitrarily modified characters.
And so they define many of the more complex emojis are defined by these sets of combinator of combinations,
rather than defining a separate code point for every possible configuration of a of a particular emoji.
So the key point here is that Kote points are not equal to characters, a character can require multiple code points.
And this comes in. This becomes relevant when you'd say compute the string length.
If you want to say line strings up there, OBC edge cases where it's wrong.
The only way truly to tell how wide a character,
how wide a string is going to be and display is to ask a rendering engine to render it in a fort and measure how wide it is.
Also, though, a character can be encoded multiple ways, as we saw, the oath diaries can be either F six or it can be six F followed by three or eight.
And what this means is that simple string equality will sometimes.
You can have equivalent strings that are not equal. We're gonna see in a little bit normalization techniques that let you let let me deal with that.
But there's no semantic difference between the two ways of encoding the O with a diary source.
But if when you compare the strings bite, when you compare the strings code point by point, they're not going to be equal.
Also, you have some things such as Roman numeral. There's a code point for Roman numeral one.
And there's it's indistinguishable from the Latin capital letter.
I and it's in their speak for compatibility reasons because some encoding.
So we had we had all of these different encodings that are encoding text in different ways before we tried to unify everything in the Unicode.
Jimmy, Twenty three. 12 had encoding, had characters for four latt for Roman numerals,
and so to translate that into Unicode, they had to have be able to map those into code points.
It's the code point is it's called a compatibility code point,
and it's not distinguishable from the Latin letteri, except that it's a different code point.
So there's a Unico database that tracks many properties of code point to get identifies,
which ones are these compatability code points and what they're what they're equivalent to?
It tracks the type you can marks for each code point is a letter, a number of punctuation, a combiner upper lower case.
There's a lot of different properties in the Unicode database. Also, the code points themselves are divided into blocks like the Latin one supplement.
The Python Unicode data module is a starting point for being for getting access to this
database and and making inquiries about your about your about different characters.
But another thing we can do with these and the Unicode data module gives you a function for this is you can normalize them.
So Unicode defined some normal forms and SFD normal form decomposed.
It always uses the combining characters. So if you if you have a A seven.
So if you have an F six. It's going to translate that to a sex F and a three o eight.
And the normal form composed using single code points whenever possible.
So it is going to go the other way around.
It's going to if it sees a six f three away, it's going to turn it into an F six.
Then there's also JFK variance, so JFK, DNF, Casey, they do the same thing,
but they also normalize compatibility character so that Roman numeral one is going to turn into a Latin capital left eye.
So once you've normalized strings, then it's a lot more likely that two semantically equivalent strings are going to also be
equal because you don't have the issue of like they're different just because the oh,
the new plot was was encoded differently. That's normalized.
So you can more directly compare them.
You can look up, you can say if you're using Unicode for file names, you can look up the file correctly and know they're going to get it right,
even if it was typed in or even if it was initially encoded in a different a different encoding.
So Unico data provides you a method to normalize.
So I can say a motley crew to normalize and F.D. and it will normalize it to the decomposed normal form.
PANDAS has normalization with that stirred up normalized normalization, super useful.
As I said, to in order to make sure that Mottley is only going to be encoded one way,
even if you've got files that are coming from different systems that might have defaulted to whether they use it composed or decomposed characters.
There's some other subtleties to Unicode as well, though.
So the lower method converts a string to lower case, but there can still be distinctions that don't make a semantic difference.
There's another function case foaled that converts to a lower case and goes farther to eliminate case distinctions.
For example, the German letter Stronsay will become two S's.
It's this, it's equivalent, but lower is not going to convert it because it's already it's already lowercase letter.
But it's going to convert it down to these two S's so that you get that there's absolutely no distinctions there anymore.
But there's other rules that are locale specific.
For example, if you want to sort strings and you want to do it correctly, the rules for doing that depend on the language, not just the characters.
And so your computer has something called a little count each.
Prosit, you can change locales for a process. Each process has a locale that it's running in.
The defines a number of things that could define your date formats and things like that.
But it also defines sort orders.
And the Python locale module gives you the sterkel function, which allows you to compare two strings based on their locale specific store order.
And it also gives you an X Asterix form function, which given a string,
it'll convert it into another string such that just doing a normal lexical graphic code
point by code point comparison on the resulting strings will sort them in the correct order.
So if you're going to Sawtell, if you're going to sort a lot.
It can be useful to say make another column of your data frame that has the store X foreign versions of your strings and then use that as your source.
Keep one thing to be aware of, though, that when you're doing that,
your program is going to have different results based on look how in which it's running.
And so for reproducibility, you might need to specify a particular locale to run your program in.
So as I said earlier, there are some universal encodings that can encode all Unicode characters,
UTF eight is probably the most common, particularly for storing files on disk.
If you have a choice, store your files in UTF eight.
Could points tape between one and four bites, ASCII is valid UTF eight, because the code points in the range zero through one twenty seven.
Ah, in the. The code point number is the same as the ASCII number, and also they get stored in one bite and you and UTF eight.
So ASCII just is immediately UTF eight. Anything outside the ASCII range gets encoded in two to four bytes.
UTF 16 uses two bytes per basic character. And so any character ins or any character inside what's called the basic multilingual plane,
which covers most currently spoken human languages, doesn't include emoji or mathematical symbols.
It will use two bytes. Characters outside of it will use four bytes.
A couple notes in the UTF 16 encoding and requires you to know the bite order because some computing systems are what's called big endian,
where the the higher order byte comes before the lower order byte in memory and others are little endian where it's the other way around.
Intel processors work in little endian.
And so there's a charac there's a two character or two byte sequence that goes at the beginning of the file that marks its brightwater.
UTF eight. So UTF eight is a great default in general, and it's particularly a great default for English,
for European languages, because a lot of them will take one to two bytes.
But if you're storing text that's written in Chinese or Japanese.
Most of those characters are going to require three bytes and UTF eight, but only two bytes and UTF 16.
And so UTF 16 can be a more compact format for storing files, storing text in those languages.
Then there's UCSF four, which stores four bytes per character. It also requires a buy order and UCSC for it.
It's just it's the sequence of four byte. It's an array of thirty twos or you and thirty twos.
And each one just stores the code point directly. There is no special encodings.
Internally, what Python does is it stores strings in the most compact form it can from the following list.
If if the string is Latin valid, Latin one, it stores it with one in Latin, one with one byte per character.
Is that so if if it's code points are all in the range zero to 255. It will store it as Latin one with one bite per character.
If they aren't. But all of the characters in the string are in the basic multilingual plane.
Then it all stored in UCSC two, which is two bytes per character, but it can only store text in the BNP.
And if it's not, if it can't fit in UCSC too, then it stores it in use.
Yes. Four. So it's an array of in thirty twos. And no matter.
This is transparent to you as he is a python. When you're writing in Python, you do not see the difference in how it's stored.
Unless you go get the size of the object. Land is always going to return the number of code points you can get.
It's just storing it more in the most compact form it can.
If you're writing a C ext module, then you'll see the difference between the different storage formats of a strength.
Other systems, many of them use UTF 16.
So Java, JavaScript, Windows and Mac API as they natively use usually UTF 16 for legacy reasons are often treated as UCSC too.
So you see, S2 was used in the 90s when there were fewer than 64000 code points in Unicode and you could store them in just two bytes.
UTF 16. First for four characters in the book Basic Multilingual Plane.
There's no difference between UTF 16 and UCSD two, Usaia,
UTF 16 extends UCSC to with the ability to say this character uses an extra pair of bytes to encode the additional characters.
So if you ask Java or Java script to give you the length of a string,
it's actually going to give you the number of two byte pairs UTF sixteen code units,
which will be the length of the number of code points if everything's in the basic multilingual plane.
But as soon as you've emoji or mathematical symbols in your string, it's gonna be wrong.
Also, the char at function that gives you an individual code code point is going to give you the UTF 16
code unit if you need the actual code point for a character that's in the upper parts of Unicode.
You're gonna need another function. So all this said, when you get some text, there's first two first steps of processing your text.
The first is to decode the text and convert the bytes into text that you can then process in Unicode.
Then we may want to normalize the text to put it into a consistent form.
Unicode normal form is often useful. We might want to strip accents.
This is going to lose some meaning, but it can make. It can reduce distinctions between words in ways that can occasionally be useful for processing.
We might want the case for it so that our text is all lower case and we don't have to deal with
deal with mixed case text because we don't if we don't want to make distinctions between case.
Some points that you need, you need to remember when processing tax, and I've also linked to a reading that provide some additional material.
You always need to know what you're encoding is when you're getting text from the
outside world or you're writing text back out on a modern Mac or Linux system.
It's going to default to UTF eight on a Windows system.
It's still usually defaults to code page twelve fifty to. You need to decode bytes in order to get a text string, which is a sequence of code points.
But even once you have your code points, they don't necessarily map one to one with characters.
And the length of a string does not mean the printed number of characters because you can have combine hours and things that are going to.
You can have combiner that are going to make multiple bytes of us. One character that zero with Joyner doesn't show up,
etc. You can use normalization to improve the comparability of strings so that you say to normalize that.
So you always use combiner, you never use combine hours.
And then case folding is a tool that allows you to make strings comparable case insensitively by removing distinctions between upper and lower case.
You have to pay attention to Lukow as well. If you want to sort things correctly for your current human language,
you need to do so in a way that's based on the specific locale because different ones have different sorting roles.
If you have single byte encoding of text and it's not UTF eight, not all byte sequences are valid,
UTF eight, then Latin one is a common one and Latin one will always succeed.
If it's wrong, you're going to have some of your accents and other non English characters.
They will be incorrect. But if you're just trying to get it read in.
You can start looking at them Latin one is common. Unfortunately, there's not a you can look at it.
Try different encodings and get the one that gets you meaningful text and language.
But there's not a there's not a foolproof way to detect the encoding used for text.
So to wrap up string is not a simple data type. Text is encoded both for on disk storage and in memory processing.
You've got these multiple layers. We have characters. Characters are represented with code points.
Code points are encoded in the bytes. There's not the one to one relationships that we might think going up and down the stack,
but it enables us now to, in a very flexible fashion, represent a wide array of written human language.