This video, we're going to talk about more of the text processing pipeline,
how do we actually get from tax that we've decoded into features and vectors that we can use in order to do computation?
So learning outcomes for this video feed understand the different stages of text processing and to be able to extract a
vector representation from text and also know some of the things that are possible beyond what we will discuss in class.
So we've got our input, a sentence that we saw in the previous video. Someone must have slandered Joseph K and we output.
We want to we maybe want to get some features from it as vectors, maybe want to get scores, decisions for some process.
So first, before we get into how to do that, I want to define a few terms.
A corpus is a set of textual data that to analyze and a document is a single document within the corpus of a corpus and it's made off of documents.
So the example that I give you is a spam filter example.
Our corpus is a bunch of emails. Each email is a document and then a term is a single word within a document.
We can think of the set of all terms is the vocabulary of of the corpus.
So we first want to decode a normalized text, as we talked about, in the encoding and decoding video.
Then we want to tokenized it or split it into individual words. We want to do some filtering on those tokens.
We want might want to further process them and into some kind of a normal form.
Then convert these the sequence of tokens, the output of that stops a sequence of tokens.
We want to convert it into a vector that we then may also further normalize and we can use for various types of processing.
So that's the pipeline. We're gonna be talking through previous video talking about decoding a normalization.
Sometimes we might delay some of the normalization until after tokenization. Oftentimes we'll do it first.
So that we've got we've got the code, the text decoded, the code points.
We've put them in a normal form. We've maybe lowercase everything or case full of everything.
We might even have stripped accents at that process as well.
And then the input, the output of that is the sequence of normalized text that's ready to be tokenized and so on.
Tokenization where we want to do is we want to split text into individual tokens.
And these tokens often are words. So we want to grab the words.
Someone must have slandered Josef K.
And so Sacket learns default.
Tolkan Isar uses a sequence of alphanumeric characters that actually use it requires there to be at least two so it will not extract K as a token.
But but we split this text into individual tokens and still at a sequence of tokens.
But this becomes the basis basically for any further analysis.
The next thing we do is we might want to remove stop words and so common utility words like and or or are often not useful depending on the task.
If you're trying to do an information retrieval task or you're searching for text finding documents that include the word,
and it's probably not useful because almost every documents going to include the word and or or but or if you want to do document classification,
the vast majority of your documents are going to have these words. So they're not very useful for.
Distinguishing between one class of documents and another.
So we can remove them either with a list of stop words, Saikat learn includes a list of stop words or by using a frequency based analysis.
So we remove the words that appear the most often.
Whether or not you do this depends on task and it also depends on the other analysis you're going to do.
If you're going to be doing an analysis that drink that recovers sentence structure, then you need these words.
If your. If you're but if you're doing information retrieval, you may well not need them if you're doing classification.
They're often not useful for a classification task and so they're worth removing.
Then after we've leave tokenized, we might have removed our stop words. Then we'll do something called we might.
I'll get it again. Whether or not you do this depends on task. But you can do something called stemming or limitation.
And the idea here is that words have multiple forms in English. Change changes, change changing.
These are different forms of the same word. They're different tenses of the same verb.
And so but if for some purposes, especially search purposes, a lot of this pipeline has its origins in search.
But then it's used for a lot of other purposes as well. There's no difference if you want to search for change in the corpus.
You probably want to find documents. It's a changed or changing.
And so there's two ways of doing this stemming is a relatively simple technique that transforms words into common stems.
The result is not necessarily a word like a stemming algorithm may well change all of these forms of the word change in CNG.
But the what the stemming does give you is that different forms of the same word are going to go to the same steps.
So if you stem all of the word that all of the different forms are going to result in identical tokens in ink for English,
snowball is a common stemming algorithm. Saikat learned does not provide you with any stemming or limitation.
To do that, you're going to need to go to another package, limits zation, accomplishes a similar purpose,
but it transforms words actually in what's called Alema form, which is an actual word, and it's the root form of the word.
And so these will all become change most likely in your lamma Tizer limited zation is more computationally intensive.
But the upside of limitation is it gives you actual words rather than these stems.
So once we've got our tokens, we've we've dropped the ones we don't want to use.
We've stemmed or DeMatteis, if we if that's appropriate for our task, we then want to vectorized that.
We want to create what's called a tom vector or a term frequency vector.
And this vector has one dimension for every term in the entire vocabulary, and its values are the number of times the term appears in the document.
So. And our example tax, someone must have slandered Joseph Kay.
We're gonna have a one for someone, one for mosta, one for have a one for slandered, one for Joseph.
It's also so sparse because each doctor is probably only going to use a fraction of the terms,
and so we'll use a sparse representation that doesn't actually store all of the zeroes.
But mathematically, this vector has an entry for every term. And if a term never appears in the document, it gets a zero.
So in psych, it provides a class called the Count Vector Ricer, which gets us to this stage.
It tokenized this text. It can do transformation. It can do lowercase.
And it can decode your Unicode if necessary. Erica, decode into Unicode if necessary.
The fit method learns the vocabulary and transforms transform turns.
An array of tax sets a one dimensional ray. Each element is a text string into a sparse matrix that looks like this.
This is called a Tom Doc or a document term matrix we have on the Y axis.
We have documents and on the columns, the different columns are terms.
And it's not recording the zeroes, the empties here are zeros and the term one document one is term one five times term three,
two times in term for its term for three times.
And so you get this transform. You get this. The sparse matrix.
And now for each documents a row and each column is a word. Basically now our words are features and their values are how frequently they appear.
So when our pipeline. Here's what Count Vectorized can do for you decode lower case.
It can strip accents if you tell it to strip accents, it's also going to normalize your Unicode.
It can then tokenized. It then tokenized is your tax.
It's default tokenization strategy is it treats any sequence of two or more alphanumeric characters as a word.
And then once it's tokenized it vectorized is and you get back these values that are the term frequency's,
how often did the word appear in each document? This is what count vector rhetoric gives you super useful.
You're going to use it as the basis for some of your processing in the assignment.
Now, there are a few problems for some purposes for using raw term frequency.
The first is that all words are equally important. If the word have appears tens times and the word hippopotamus appears 10 times.
It makes no distinction, even though if you're trying for a lot of purposes,
the fact that a document says hippopotamus, which is a far less common word,
is probably more meaningful for distinguishing it from other documents than the fact that it has half almost every document has have in it.
And so this is a solution. There's two pieces of the solution. One is we wait words differently.
We're going to give uncommon words, words that don't appear in very many documents.
Higher weight. And this is this winds up being broadly useful because if you're trying to retrieve a document,
the words that are more unique to that document are probably more useful for trying to retrieve it.
If we're trying to classify a document, the words that are more unique are probably also going to be more useful for dividing
distinguishing between one class of documents for another than another example,
if you're trying to. If you have a collection of of scientific reports and you're trying to distinguish between zoology and botany,
the word have is probably not useful because both classes of documents probably have it,
whereas hippopotamus is probably much more common in zoology documents than in a botany document.
So the other thing that we're going to do is we're going to normalize these
vectors so that rather than just using an absolute counts in a longer document,
it just has higher values everywhere. We're going to normalize it so that every documents vector has the same magnitude.
And this is going to mean long documents don't have substantially higher values than short documents just on the virtue of their length.
Which makes it easier to compare documents. So the first part of it waiting more waiting,
giving more weight to less common words is done through something called term frequency, inverse document frequency.
And the idea here is that we compute a feature value by multiplying the term frequency t.f.
By the inverse of the document frequency D.F.
And we take it the way we compute, the way Saikat learn computes the inverse document frequency is if we have N and that's the number of documents.
We take the log of the number of documents divided by the number of documents
with the terms of D.F. is the number of documents that have the term tea. And is the total number.
So. And it's the inverse. So rather than saying D.F. over D.F. of tea over N,
which would be the fraction of documents that have the term, we do take the inverse of that fraction.
And over D.F. of tea, we take the log Saikat learn add some ones to both the numerator and the denominator in order to prevent.
If you've got a term that doesn't appear in any of the documents which the Count Vectorized isn't going to give you one of
those terms because the vocabulary just doesn't have words not going to be in the vocabulary if it's not in the document.
But in some other cases, we have a vocabulary that comes from somewhere else. You might adding a one.
Just make sure you never have division by zero and you're never trying to take a log of zero.
Other common ones are you're gonna take the log of an over one plus D.F. of T so
that you just have the one plus in the denominator and not in the numerator.
That little change is not going to make a significant difference in terms of performance.
It's a subtle difference in how it's implemented, but it's not going to make a significant computational difference.
But what this does is a document that appears, if you think about what you have to do to make the value go up.
The document appears more frequently. You can increase the value by having the document appear more frequently in the terms of increased T.F.
That'll go up. You can also increase the the value, the TFI D.F. value, which we're calling X.
You can increase that by having the document appear determined here in you were documents.
So the more documents it appears in, the closer this is the one where it has,
if it's if it doesn't appear in very many documents, it's going to be a large number.
Say a million over 50 or a million. Over five hundred.
The log of that's going to be high and you can have a much higher TFI D.F. value if the term does not appear in very many documents.
And that reflects that if the term is more unique to this document than it's more useful for distinguishing this document from other documents.
That's the key insight here. Less common words are more useful for describing what makes this document different from other documents.
And if two documents have the same eyes, have the same uncommon words.
That's really useful for saying they're probably similar if they have the same words.
But those words are super common, that the documents are probably not very similar.
So we then normalize our TFI D.F. vector to be what's called a unit vector.
And what this means is we just divide the vector by its L2 norm.
If you use the T.F. IDF Vector Isar instead of the Count Vectorized and Saikat, it's going to do everything to count vectorized.
It does. And then it's going to apply T.F. IDF and it's going to normalize them, the unit vectors by the default.
You can change some of that, like have it not in do the L2 normalization, but use the TFI the effector.
It's going to give you unit vectors that apply. They use TFI,
D.F. adjustment to down wait common terms and give you these factors that are useful too for
for characterizing documents in terms of how frequently they use relatively uncommon words.
So now we have our whole text processing pipeline for getting to a term vector.
We decode normalize. We tokenized. We remove, stop words. We may do some other token filtering as well, like throw out numbers or something.
You can stammer lemon ties. So both of stopwork removal and the stemming and limitation are optional.
You don't have to do them. You can. This is the template for the pipeline.
Different applications and different tasks is going to use different steps of this of this pipeline.
Then we vectorized the text and we normalized our resulting vectors that we get these nice vector representations of a document.
The result is each document gets this vector that assigns scores to terms for their relevance to that document.
And this this is a very high dimensional vector.
Ten thousand hundred thousand dimensions. So if you stick into a linear model, that's a large number of coefficients.
But it gives you this vector representation of the resulting text that we can then use for additional tasks processing,
classifying, clustering, etc. our text. So a few alternatives to some of the design decision for some of the pieces of this pipeline.
First, we can we don't have to tokenized the words. We can tokenized into what's called an end.
Gramp's such as a Bigram or a Trigram. And what they are. There are sequences that were so a bigram as pairs of words that appear next to each other.
You can also do character level bigram. So it's pairs of characters.
You can also do what's called a skip gram, which pairs of characters that appear in proximity.
But there might be another word between them.
You can also do sentence level analysis rather than just splitting into words and putting the words into a vector,
which is called bag of work, by the well way.
It's called a bag of words model because you just take the document, we throw it all the words into a bag.
We don't have the relationships anymore. We can split it not only in the words, but in the sentences.
We can tag words by parts of speech. We can look at analyze relationships between words.
Various natural language processing toolkits give you tools for doing that.
Stanford MLP is one that gives you the ability to do those word relationships.
Currently, there's a lot of work in an AP Natura. So A.P. natural language processing is the field for studying this.
If you want to learn a lot more about this processing pipeline and things you can do with text the classes you want to take out an LP and I are.
Information retrieval. Transformer architectures are deep neural networks that can deal with sequences of words.
They have significant power for modeling how language works and modeling.
What's going on in text. But that comes with significant processing cost.
The Python package and K gives you a lot of tools. It doesn't give you the full sentence analyzer, but gives you a lot more sophisticated tools,
such as parts of speech, tagging, stemming in limited zation, etc. Then you haven't like it.
You can also integrate with Saikat,
learn who can replace the psychic lern count vectorized or TFI the effect Dreiser with a vectorized that uses NLC K to do the analysis.
If you need more sophisticated text, processing is a part of your application.
So to conclude, term vectors treat each word as a feature for which documents have scores that often normalize.
The uncommon words have higher weight and that longer documents don't just have larger vector values.
Where then when you use these vectors downstream in order to do a variety of computations.