So now that we have some term vectors, what can we do with them learning outcomes for this video or for you to understand the
value of vector representations and instances and the compute similarities between vectors?
So we've talked about vectors from time to time throughout this course.
But. And you've probably seen you may have seen them in a linear algebra class or statistics class, but a vectors just an array of numbers.
Got a vector X that's got values X one, X, two, three, X.
Then we say that it has N dimensions. This can be the row or column of a matrix.
And we often then the length of the vector, the length of the vector is usually not as dimensionality, the length is usually the L2 norm.
The sum of the squares, the value of the vector we can think about.
So in instances, features form an array of form of vector, an array of values like the role of a data frame.
It's a vector. We can treat it as one. We could create the column as a vector.
But when we with the features you've been seeing so far on this, we standardize,
then the features often have different scales, different meanings, not necessarily meaningful to relate them to each other.
One of the things that's a little different about our about the vectors that we get out of tax is that they're more homogenous, like each.
Each dimension corresponds to a term. But they all mean the same kind of thing.
It's the number of times that term has been applied or the relevance of that term
to the document and the both the voelz heterogeneous and homogenous vectors.
They they record of that. They we can think of them as giving data points a position in some kind of a vector space.
So if we've got a two dimensional vector space here, we have vectors A and B,
we can think of them either as a point in space out here at the end of the arrow or as a line from origin to point.
So we've got a is at two, three and B is it for one using the standard X Y notation.
We can compute a variety of things. We can compute C, which is A minus B.
Which is a factor that would go from B to A. We can computer distance between them, which is the length of that vector, the Euclidean length.
And we call it would you that is the length because it's the it's the length of this arrow.
If Pythagorean it's a multidimensional generalization of Pythagoras, of the Pythagorean Theorem.
Because if you want the length of this arrow,
then you need to compute the square root to the sum of the squares of its two sides, which are four and one.
Square, the square, the Miach, some them take the square root and you're going to get square root of 17,
which is going to be the length of this vector, the length of that that arrow.
You can also compute what's called an inner product, which is the sum of the products of.
So two vectors have the same dimensionality. They're both n dimensional vectors.
If you go across the dimensions and you multiply the vectors values for them and you sum up all of that, then you get what's called the DOT product.
So for these particular vectors, it's going to be two times four plus three times one, which is going to be you leavens.
The inner product of these two vectors is 11. You can also think about the angle between them so they have an angle theta.
And you can often, in terms of what we do at that angle is we compute its cosine.
We want to get the angle itself. We can compute the arc cosine of this cosine.
But the coast between two vectors is their inner product divided by the product of their lengths.
And so it would be that eleven divided by Route 17 and the other A has a length of the square root.
Of four plus nine, which is 13. So that's going to be the angle between these two vectors, this angle is a common measure of object similarity,
and we aren't we could do this with any kind of a vector.
It just happens to be especially useful for these kinds of homogenous vectors, like text vector.
You can do it for any you can at any data point. You can computer cosine similarity between them.
If you've got vector representation, it looks at how related are to vectors and it has a useful relationship with the the two
vectors are have a mean of zero then it's equivalent to the Peerson correlation between them.
It's very common though to do this with TFI D.F. vectors and a T.F. idea vector is.
It's going to always have a value of it.
It's always going to be a positive values. They're all in that upper right quadrant. But it lets you compare.
It gives you a measure of some very common similarity measure between documents.
You can also take the distance between the two documents and the vector spaces, the relationship between them.
A couple of useful tricks first.
If the two vectors are unit vectors, then the inner product is the cosine because both of the length is a length of one.
The denominator is one times once. You can just compute an inner product. This is one reason that normalizing TFT effectors to unit vectors is useful.
And oftentimes, if we're gonna do something that's going to compute cosine similarities,
we normalize the unit vectors first, then we get these very efficient, cosine similarity.
Because you just have to compute the inner product between vectors. This is also a useful reason why it's interest.
It's useful to normal sometimes to normalize a set of feature values, for instance, to a unit vector unit vector normalization that we talked about.
Transformations in normalizations unit vector normalization is almost never something we want to do to a column in one of our data frames.
We only want to do it within a row that the feature values of a particular instance, either all of them or some subset of them.
If we have a matrix whose rows are all unit vectors, then we can compete.
We can use a matrix multiplication to compute the pairwise similarities between all rows of M and a very optimized fashion.
We start talking. We're thinking about how you really.
Lean hard into vectorized and computations, being able to use a matrix matrix, multiply two to compute a large number of similarities at one go.
It's a very good example of that kind of that kind of thinking.
And Sipi provides sparse matrix representations to a super, super useful for that view account vectorized or TFI de'ath vectorized.
Or you're going to get a sci fi sparse matrix out that it doesn't spend space storing all the zeroes.
So to conclude, vector representations allow us to do a lot of useful computations.
And one of those is that we can compute the similarity between two documents by taking the cosine between their vectors, their TFI, D.F. of vectors.
And this gives us a powerful mudgett. We can compute similarity or distance or difference between documents by using their bag of words.
Term frequency renormalize term frequency remembering.