This video, we're going to talk about how to classify text,
so learning outcomes are to be able to use vector space representations to classify text and also to classify in a more than two classes.
So there's a lot of various reasons you might want to classify text. You might want to distinguish between spam and not spam.
We might want to identify news categories. You're going to be doing that in the end.
The assignment might want to say separate news from opinion or identify fraud or
a lot of other reasons why we might want to classify texts into different kinds.
And we're going to be using for this process as our input term vectors. There's been work lately on using more sophisticated representations.
But we're going to start just with using our term vectors. So really simple way to do it is to use what's called a K nearest neighbor, a classifier.
And what what it does is it finds the K nearest neighbors to a data point that are closest to the vector space.
So if we've got some vector space and we have some data points.
And we maybe have some data points of another class. And we've got one that comes in and we want to classify it.
Let's say it's here, what it's going to do is it's going to go find the closest data points.
Maybe it'll be these three and it's going to take a little vote. And inside this green circle, it's a little hard to see.
But two of them are purple and one of them is red. So it's going to the vote is going to be purple.
This is K is three, three years neighbors. Two of them were purple. One is red.
And two, it's going to classify our new data point as purple. He uses some metric.
Often this metric is the Euclidean distance between the two vectors.
And it also easily extends to more than two classes because you can have three, four or five classes.
You can see what the most common class is in your neighborhood. This works fine with TFI, D.F. vectors.
So you can you can use the TFT effect. Dreiser this. The psychic K neighbors classifier and you can get.
But don't put those two things in a pipeline and you get a working classifier that can work well on a variety of tasks.
That uses the term vectors extract from your text in order to do classification.
Another way is to use what's called a naive Bayes classifier, where here the goal is.
It tries to estimate the probability in this case, as is spam, the probability of spam given a particular documents text.
And the way that you and we can use Bayes Theorem to say if we have the probability of a dock of a particular document given tax,
the probability that if we said, oh, we want to make a spam, what would these words appear in it?
And the probability of making a spam. And we can divide that then by normalizing constant.
We can compute the probability of spam given a document. And there's a couple of things that go into this.
First, we have data. We have a bunch of documents that we can learn what how terms relate to spam.
And second, we make what's called the naive Bayes assumption, which assumes that terms are independent of each other.
This assumption is false. But this assumption is very useful because it makes it very computationally simple way to do the classification.
That also happens to work remarkably well.
And so then I leave base assumption is that if I say I'm going to write a spam and then my spam, I say Apple.
The next word I use is the frequency of any other word occurring as independent of that.
It's the fact that you saw that I said Apple in my spam has no influence on the probability that I am going to say cash in my spam.
And so since they're independent, we can take the product over the terms and the document of the probability of each term given spam.
And so what we do is we have four spam. We have a probability distribution over terms for not spam.
Well, the probability distribution over terms,
we can learn those probability distributions from labeled data just by counting how common each term is and spams and not spammers.
So how are words we ever span's you are not spams are labeled as count how often his term appears in each one,
we use that to derive a probability of using that term.
If I'm going to write a spam, if I'm going to write a non spam email, so we do that,
we learned our prior we either we can either set it to even or we can learn it from the data.
This is called sometimes empirical Bayes psychic learns it from the default.
So if if 70 percent of our emails are spam, then the probability of spam will be point seven.
The probability of not spam will be point three. It does that automatically.
And then given a new document, we compute this probability of spam.
We also compute the probability of not spam.
And did we use our prior we use the term probabilities from the data, we can compute the normalizing function by by computing these two probabilities.
This works well with not you don't want to do TFI D.F. before this,
you can do it and it mostly works, but to really compute the probabilities, trillion.
It's going to work on your term. Your term.
You're just your term frequency vectors. How often the word appears.
And it's going to naturally learn which words are more useful for distinguishing between spam and not spam.
Psychic learn implements this in the multinomial and the classifier class.
So Tarapur, both CNN and Naive Bayes can predict multiple classes from vector data such as term frequency vectors from text.
If you want to do multiple class accuracy, it's the same as binary accuracy.
It's just the net, the fraction, the time it was correct.
The spam filter example notebook demonstrates naive Bayes with the count vector Isar that we've been talking about.