But in this video, I'm going to introduce you to the idea of unsupervised learning.
This week we're going to learn about the difference between supervised and unsupervised learning.
You're going to learn how to project data into lower dimensional spaces with matrix factorization and to cluster data points.
So so far, we've been focusing on learning what we're trying to predict a label.
We have a categorical label where we're trying to predict. And this is classification we're trying to classify as spam, not spam fraud.
There's a couple of the examples we've been using.
We can have a continuous label we're trying to predict, in which case we call it, in which case it's three regression.
But this is called we can also try to predict ordinal variables, et cetera.
But this is all called supervised learning. Where we have the key idea here is we have a ground truth for the outcome.
We have observed outcomes for our training data. This is sometimes called a supervisions signal.
And we're trying to learn to predict these known outcomes.
That's that's the heart of what it means to do supervised learning. But.
We can do things without having a supervision signal.
And some of the things we can do without access to a supervision signals, we can try to group instances together what's called clustering,
where we try to find related groups and clustering and multiclass classification are related.
Because if you've got multiple class labels, then you're trying to divide them into that.
Clustering is where you're trying to buy the Met, but you don't have the class labels.
You can try to learn vector spaces for items in order to say,
learn the relationship between items in some cases, also to learn the relationships between features of items.
There's also a middle ground called self supervised learning where you don't have labels in the sense that we use them in supervised learning,
but you extract something that looks like a label from the data and use that as a supervisions signal.
Word and beddings are one example of of self supervised learning.
So why do we want to do this unsupervised learning? There's a few reasons.
One is that it can be useful as a data exploration tool.
If you can find clusters in the data, then that can help guide where you your investigation to understand what's going on in your data.
It can help to reduce data complexity for either visualization or for subsequent learning tasks.
You can use them as inputs into other models and sometimes it's all we have.
We don't have access to labels and we're trying to make sense of our data source. Unsupervised learning techniques can be helpful in order to do that.
So to wrap up unsupervised learning learns patterns from data.
We don't have labels available. It's useful for grouping items together, exploration and as input into other models.