Blow in this video. I want to introduce the idea of Matrix decompositions.
There's a couple of notebooks that go with this to demonstrate the concepts more and to give you some additional readings in this.
This video is going to explain what's going on. So goal here is to view matrix multiplication and decompose a matrix into a lower rank approximation.
So if you've taken a linear algebra class, you may have seen a matrix.
We have a it's a two matrix is just a two dimensional array of numbers.
We say it's dimension is M by N Rose always go first. When we're notating matrices, this is also the convention used by NUM Pi.
And so it is. It's Rose R and dimensional row vectors.
So that's a row vector. It's columns. R m dimensional column vectors have a column vector there.
We can also compute its transpose if we swapped the rows and columns. Vampyre exposes that as the exact capital T operation.
But a matrix is it's this two dimensional array of numbers. We can do a few things with them.
We can add them together. We can subtract them. One of those things we can do is we can multiply them.
So if we have two matrices A and B and A is M by K and B is K by N.
This is important. The inner dimensions of the two matrices have to match.
Then we can compute the Matrix product and it's gonna be M times and so for multiplying two matrices.
Unlike multiplication of of scalars.
Matrix multiplication is not commutative. You can't switch B get the same result.
You have to have the same the same matrix or the same dimensionality on the inside.
And what you get as the result is the dimensionality of the outside.
So what it's defined as is is CIJ Row, Row I column J is defined by the SARM.
Across the row of A and down the column of B of the pairwise items.
So it is it is the DOT product of Roe A.
And Column B. Or and of column Jay of of Matrixx Base.
You compute. You compute the DOT product. So see what C is, is it is the dot product of every row of A with every column of B num pi.
You can compute this with the A and B operation. That's the Python Matrix multiplication operator.
So this is a fundamental operation for matrices that you can multiply them together.
We also can have what we call sparse matrices and a matrix is sparse.
If most of its values are zero, that's what it means mathematically for it to be sparse.
Computationally a sparse matrix is a matrix with a zero. Values are not stored.
And so Saipov provide the sparse Matrix class that we can a number of sparse matrix classes that we can use.
The number high ENDI array is a dense matrix. Data frame is also a dense matrix.
S data frame.
It's very serious, can't be sparse, but if we need to do sparse computations, we can use this Sipi that sparse package to give us sparse matrices.
This is what Saikat learned does under the hood.
When you do, when you tokenized text with its with its count vector Dreiser or its TFI D.F. Vector riser,
its giving use Sibai sparse matrices as a result.
Now one of the things we can do with another thing we can do with a matrix is do what's called the dimensionality reduction.
And this follows from a theorem that if we have a matrix and intown by hand,
then we can compute a decompositions into the multiplication of three matrices P Sigma and Q Transpose.
And this gives us we can break down any matrix into this, Sipi provides us with functions in order to compute this decompensating given an ax.
It will compute piece Sigmon Q or Q Transpose. We can also then truncate this.
So Sigma is what's called the singular values.
We can truncate this matrix, only keep the K largest ones and set the rest of zero or just cut them out so that.
To so that we can get we get a narrower P and a narrower cure, a shorter Q transpose.
And this gives us an approximation of the original Matrix X.
There's a few useful properties. So the rows of P rows of P correspond to rows of X rows correspond.
So what Pier gives us is a K dimensional. Representation of rows of X, if X has a lot of columns.
This is super useful because if case more than no columns of X, then we get the smaller,
more compact representation of the original rows of the Matrix.
Also, it preserves distance things that are things are approximately as far apart in the in P as they are in the original X.
So why do we want to do this? One reason is for a compact representation. As I said, we get this k dimensional representation of our values x.
It can be useful to remove noise. I'll talk more about that in a little bit.
It can be useful for plotting high dimensional data to show relationships. If you've got 50 columns of X.
You can plot just like two columns of it. Or you can take the SDD to find columns that are particularly hard to project it into another.
Another vector space that you can show it in two dimensions that maximize the maximize the
amount or the extent to which the data points you can be spread out in those two dimensions.
It can also improve our ability to compute distances and fine and then it can provide.
It finds relationship and it can be helpful for finding relationships between features.
So if we have correlated features, we have multiple features that are partially measuring a similar thing.
They're correlated with each other. Principal component analysis is an application of matrix composition that allows us to find those relationships
and combine those correlated things and extract non correlated components out of these correlated observations.
So how do you actually do this? So Saikat learn provide a truncated SPDM class.
It's a transformer. If you call fit, it learns Kute transpose.
If you call transformatory turns the rows of P for the instances you pass in the anthraces,
you pass and don't have to be the same instances that you gave to fit.
Fit. Transform does the whole thing at once. I'm giving you example Kobel that you see this in action.
And then there's also the SEVIS function inside PI that computes the SVOD of a sparse matrix.
So one of the applications of SFD, as I said, is something called principal component analysis.
If you mean center, your features are you can standardize them. But if you mean center your features and then you compute the S.V. D.
What you get is the columns of P or what we call principle components.
So columns zero. Is the position of the data point along a vector that has a maximum variance and you're over?
You can go over to Q and find that vector in the original of the original data space.
And so what it does is it finds you've got this you've got this data in space and it finds it aligned through the data.
That explains more variance over a long which is not that it explains more
variance along which there is more variance than there is along any other line.
You could draw through that data point through that that space. That can be the axis at axis and a vector space.
And then if you see projekt all of your points onto that line, then you can find another line that explains most of the remaining.
The more of the remaining variance than any other.
So here I have I have data projected in two dimensional space, it's actually three dimensional data.
There's some correlation. We get this line here that runs through it.
And this line, if you go along so that the variance along the axis,
there's a fair amount of variance is a fair amount of variance along why there's more variance along this line.
So it gives just this line that this is the line through which there's most of the variance.
We could transform the data. So this line is now our X X-axis.
And then we could look at where's the where's the rest of the variance? So we can see here.
Here I'm showing the vectors the first and the second principle components.
The first one is along this line. I showed you the first place. It can go either way.
PCI does not guarantee which direction the sign is going to go. It does the same flip.
You can point the arrow the other direction, but you've got this this vector here that lets us.
Is this line along which there's more variance than any other?
But then there's this second line and it's orthogonal to the first and it's OK, where's the next chunk of variance?
What direction do I go to find the next amount of variance? You and The Notebook was online that generated these plots along with the simulation.
You can play with a little bit. So why do we want to use this? There's a few different useful use cases.
One is to compress and genoise our data. So as I said, we truncate we can truncate DVD.
We keep the K largest singular values. This means that P and Q are much smaller than pretty liste.
P is much smaller than X.
Then the result is that when we multiply them back together, it approximates X and it is it is the best rank approximation to the rank.
The rank of a matrix is basically a measure of how complex it is.
What it is, is it's the number of non-zero values in the singular value decomposition.
And so if we zero out the smallest values, what we get is.
If least squares error is our measure. Of how good an approximation of the original matrix is.
There is no better approximation than the truncated SPDM.
Another thing that happens is if there's noise in X, if X is some strong signal and a bunch of noise.
The largest singular values and singular vectors are probably going to pick up the signal and not the noise.
Always both for the most part. And so if you add the noise will be learned in the smaller vectors.
And so if you drop the smaller vectors, then you're dropping a bunch of the noise.
And so it can be useful to clean up data for some various purposes.
If X is sparsely observed,
you can use this also to impute values if you're careful about how you set up the composition because that he got but this you have to have
the full matrix if you're careful about how you set it up or use an alternative means of learning one that can deal with missing data.
Then you can multiply them back together to predict what the values you weren't able to observe of X are.
Really useful technique for imputing that data.
And for filling in unobserved values.
This is how a lot of recommender systems work. Actually, if we observe your preference for some movies,
we can use a singular value decomposition or a derivative of it in order to fill back in and estimate your preference for the movies you haven't seen.
And then if X is the document term Matrix or the Roeser documents and the columns or terms and we take the SFD,
this is what's called latent semantic analysis or latent semantic indexing.
And it's a way for understanding.
What we call the topics in a corpus, because these these dimensions and in the reduced dimensionality space, the metric, the.
This inner vector space and talk of another video about what a little bit more about what that means.
They correspond theoretically to different kinds of topics.
And so if that document becomes represented rather than the words, it becomes represented as a vector over topics.
And each document is a mixture of these topics and words correspond to topics as well.
The model there is that a document produces a word or contains a word because the document is about topic and the word is relevant to the topic.
And so you learn these topics.
And it lets you compare documents even if they don't have as many words in common because you can establish this in enemies, OK?
These words are on the same topic. Then if I use some of them, I'm on that topic.
And another document uses other ones that it's on that topic. And we can learn the topic relationship by doing a matrix, the composition.
Another one is for visualization. So low dimensional vectors can be visualized.
And I show this in the example notebooks.
But if we take an SVOD, then we can you say the first two columns of the SFD to visualize our data points in a space.
The space is not human interpretable. But let's see how spread out the points are.
We can also use it to get better neighborhood. So one of the problems, there's a couple of problems with high dimensional spaces.
We're trying to compute distances.
One is that distance is more expensive to compute because the more dimensions you have, the more compute you need to do.
But also, as the dimensionality of a space increases, the number of features,
the number of columns in your in your Matrix point start to look about the same distance from each other.
It's called the cursive dimensionality. Decomposed matrices can help with this.
So doing SFD can help make either a K and then classifier or a commune's clustering approach work better if you work on the.
If you do the K and N or the K means clustering, which we're going to talk about in the next video.
On top of. The transformed data using an SVOD, it can sometimes be more effective than if you just use it on its own.
The fourth case is the model categorical interaction. So if we want to models say the likelihoods of words to appear together,
like what's the likelihood that apple and fish appear within three words of each other in a sentence?
We can think about this as a probability, but there's N squared of them because we have no probability for every pair of words.
That's a lot to learn if we were going to learn.
If you want to learn a matrix that maps the probability between every pair of words in the English language, that's a very, very large matrix.
So instead, what we can do is we can learn of reduced dimensionality, space, and we usually don't do this by actually taking the NCD.
We do it with with approximation method that just directly optimize these vectors.
But we can learn vectors for words so that.
You basically using a logistic model of the probabilities so that the DOT products between them is the law gods of the two words appearing together.
And so words that appear together are going to have similar vectors.
Words that appear far apart are going to have very different vectors. And this is called a word embedding.
This is what a word embedding does. Like word the vac glove. These various word embedded.
This is what they do. And more sophisticated versions of this are at the heart of a lot of machine learning models.
So a lot of neural architecture is a lot of deep learning.
Models have various embedding and all in embedding is it's a vector representation of something.
And they're often done through these kinds of dimensionality, reduction techniques or approximations of them,
so that you get you get these vectors, these low dimensional vectors that are in a space like they're 10 dimensional vector.
And the 10 dimensions don't mean anything. They're just dimensions that are useful for explaining this.
This this instance is relationship to whatever we're trying to do with it.
And so they take you a long ways and a lot of machine learning.
And then they're the core piece of a lot of different models.
So to wrap up Matrix decompositions, which is also called a matrix factorization or dimensionality reduction,
breaks a high dimensional matrix into a low dimensional one. And it's useful for compressing data.
You've got a more compact representation. It's useful for making it more well behaved numerically.
We can compute better distances. We compute distances more efficiently, can reduce noise in the data.
There's a lot of different purposes for which decomposing data into this lower dimensional space is super useful.