This video I want to introduce clustering, so learning outcomes are for.
To understand the idea of clustering and to interpret the results of clustering with K means.
So the idea of clustering is to group things together. So if we want to find groups in our data points, but we don't know what the groups are,
many clustering techniques require us to know how many groups there are. But we don't know what the groups are.
If we did, we would just use a multiclass classifier to find them. We want to find them from the data.
This is what we call clustering. So there's a couple of different kinds of clustering in terms of the membership of the clusters.
One is mixed membership where a point can be in more than one cluster.
And it has a different degree of affinity for the different clusters matrix factorization we can see as a kind of mixed membership clustering.
Where do the values in the decomposed and the lower dimensional space are?
How strongly the matrix is associated? The data point is associated with that cluster, but single membership clustering we want to find.
We want to find clusters. And we want to put each point in one cluster. So we might have movie types, different types of movies.
Want to put each movie in a different type. These might align with genres. They might align with something else.
So the idea one technique is to do it based on what we call centroid and the centroid is just the center of a cluster.
And so to do this, we typically need a distance function between two data points, between two vectors.
Often this is the Euclidean distance, but we have to define the vector space properly.
We need to do the feature engineering, have the features appropriately normalized and standardized so that the distance between them.
The distance between their vectors actually reflects how far apart the vectors are, the instances are with regards to our clustering goal.
If the distance does not relay, if it isn't so, that more similar items in terms of what we what we hope the cluster is going to uncover,
those more similar items need to have a smaller distance between each other than they do their distance to a not a less similar right along again,
along whatever it is that we hope the clustering is going to uncover.
We can do clustering on on dimensioned after dimensionality reductions that we can get.
We can get our ah. We can work in a lower dimensional space and sometimes that'll make where our distances be better behaved.
So the goal is to find the centroid of these clusters. And then what we'll do is we'll when an item comes in, we'll find which of our clusters.
So we have 10 clusters. We're gonna fi compare it. We're gonna measure its distance from the centers of all of the clusters.
And we're gonna say it's in the closest one. And so the K means algorithm does this by.
So we tell you how many clusters we want. We want five clusters, 10 clusters.
And it picks ten points. And says, these are my cluster centers.
And then figures out what cluster all of the data points are in.
And now that it's got all the data points clustered, it uses the it takes each cluster and recompute the new center.
It takes all the data points, computes the center of that set of points. And that's the new cluster center.
It then does this again because then you move the cluster center.
It might be that some points on the edge between it and another cluster switch clusters.
And then once you've switched clusters, you compute the center centroid again and you repeat this several times until what we call convergence.
And so this is a this is an example. We've seen a couple of others of what's called an iterative method,
iterative method as a method where you start somewhere and you incrementally improve your result.
So we start with some cluster centers, cluster the data points, move the centers to reflect the data points.
Try again. And convergence basically means it stops moving.
We've rerun another round of it. And our cluster centers haven't moved very much.
This does require us to know. Okay. It can't figure out how many clusters there are supposed to be.
And they're optimizations that can improve it various ways, particularly picking a like the simple way to do it.
If you pick K points just completely at random. There are more sophisticated ways to pick those points that can result in better clustering behavior.
So to do this, since I can't learn the K means class or do K means clustering fit learns, the cluster centers predict,
will map a data point to a cluster no super give it predict with some data and it will give you numbers, cluster numbers, cluster centers.
If you look if you go into and get the cluster centers attribute out of the escolar an object, that's the center centroid.
If your clusters of other clustering algorithms and Saikat learn of a similar interface.
Now we've got these clusters. How do we see how well they work?
Well, look at them like the purpose here is we want to uncover data, uncover connections and groupings in the data.
But we don't have labels, so one thing you really have to do with clustering is just look at it.
Do the clusters seem to be finding coherent? Do they seem to be finding coherent sets of things that we're clustering?
If you do have labels, sometimes we will have labels and we can like we have labels for a little bit of data.
We can use it to compare clustering behaviors, clustering systems also, or cluster clustering results.
Also, it can be useful when we're experimenting with clustering techniques to cluster data
where we do have the labels to see how good a job it's doing at recovering labels.
And we do have them to get some idea of how it might do. And we don't have them.
And then there are some quality scores.
There's a score called silhouette that compares the distances within a cluster to the distances between items and items and the closest other cluster.
And if things tend to be closer to each other than they are to other clusters, then you've got a better clustering.
These can be used to compare clustering, but there's not an absolute quality value like,
oh, a silhouette of point five means they've got a good clustering. No clustering is a really, really evaluating.
Clustering is a really imprecise thing. But the basic it basically is the clustering useful for what you're trying to do with it.
So to wrap up clustering allows us to identify groups of items in the data. These clusters may or may not make sense.
You have to look at them really. Cluster quality depends on a number of things.
Your features and your metric are super important because if you don't have a feature space and a
metric such that things that are similar to each other are close together in the on your metric,
then clustering is not going to be able to find the relationships you're looking for. Also, the cluster counters superimportant.
If there are eight natural groups and you try to find five clusters, clusters might not work so well.
Now the natural gropings and the cluster count do not necessarily need a map.
Sometimes you can get good cluster rings with an extra cluster or not having quite as many clusters.