This video, I want to talk a little bit more about vector spaces, we've talked about them a little,
but we're going to talk about the concept in a little more detail now.
Want to formally introduce more formally introduced the concept of vector space and understand the idea of a vector space transformation.
We're only going to scratch the surface for a lot more. I recommend that you read a good linear algebra book.
So remember, vector is a vector is there's a sequence of numbers, an array, basically a one dimensional array.
So X X one X two X and that's the vector real's to the end is an end dimensional vector space.
In the real numbers, you vector spaces over other things to integers over.
Complex numbers over weird things, but it's an n dimensional vector space and we can do a few operations, the vector.
We can add, subtract, we can multiply by a scalar. That's a real number, we can compute the inner product.
You cannot multiply multiplying two vectors, just I'm going to multiply defector's together is not an operation.
If you both apply to vectors and know what you're actually getting is the pairwise
multiplication like it multiplies the elements together if they're compatible sizes.
That is not actually a linear algebra operation. There is the inner product, which is the sum of the element Y's products.
And then there's a distance, which is the inner product of a subtraction with itself. And so we can have a matrix.
So we've got a sample exit rows and instance, each instance is a row vector.
As a row of this matrix X, we can do all the vector things with these rows.
Matrix, a matrix is, as we said in an earlier video. Is this this two dimensional array?
Of numbers. It's a collection of row vectors and it's a collection of Cullom vectors.
It's also a linear map from one vector space to another. And the other one might be the same the the the same vector space in terms like it
might be n by n subtle map are an N dimensional vector to another N dimensional vector.
But it's had some transformations applied to it. There's a bunch of things we can do with matrices.
We can add them, multiply them by either a scalar or by a compatible matrix or vector.
We saw that earlier. You can transpose them, et cetera. There's a number of special matrices.
So we have column vectors which are m by one, remember, we always have rows first.
So M rose by one column is an M by one column vector.
One row by N columns is an it is a one by N row vector.
We can have a square matrix where the two dimensions are the same.
We can have a diagonal matrix that only had that zero everywhere except the diagonal.
So you've got your big matrix. It's got. The diagonal is non-zero.
All of this is zero. You can have an identity matrix, which is a diagonal matrix where all the non-zero values are one.
You can have a triangular matrix where either the upper right. Or the lower left corner is non-zero and the other side is zero.
So it's the everything above and to the right of the diagonal is zero for a lower triangular matrix.
Everything down the left of the diagonal is zero for an upper triangular matrix.
Also a symmetric matrix, which is a square matrix where it's equal to its transpose.
So the top right corner is equal to the top bottom left corner.
You flip it. You flip the rows in the column and you get the same Matrix backout. You can also have what's called an orthogonal matrix,
where if a transpose times A is equal to the identity matrix, then you have an orthogonal matrix.
Matrix vector multiplication is super useful operation.
So if we've got an M byan matrix and we've gotten N dimensional column vector, then we can compute Y equals X and we can.
And this is going to be an M dimensional column vector.
And what we've done here is we have mapped X into another vector space or we've transformed it.
And even if even if the even if a a square. So it's from R and R n.
What we're doing we can apply this can transform the vector so that it's in it's in the same space.
But it is its relationships to other vectors have changed.
And it's effectively a. In the different organization of the same space for lack of a better term.
I'm trying to avoid getting deep into the linear algebra terms like so like change of basis and things.
Because I'm trying to give you the intuition for it.
And linear algebra class is gonna really eat either a class or a textbook or an online course is going
to help you shore up a lot of the details that you're going to need to dove deeper into linear algebra.
So multiplying by a matrix can give us a bunch of different transform.
We can reduce dimensionality. We can basically project, project and do other transformations.
So a projection is when you just strip off vectors. So if we have X.
So if we've got one seven. The projection of this under the first dimension is just one.
But you can also do some additional transformations at your besides just projection to get it down to a lower dimensional space.
One of the things you can do is translate. So if we've got here. We can translate it.
We've got Vector's. And we just shift them, same relationship to each other.
They're just moved. We can scale them so that they're going to this vector is going to.
Get a vector here. We can scale it.
You can skew the space. You can also rotate within the space and any combination of these, you can do any linear transformation.
And actually this is what it means for something to be a linear transformation of linear
transformation is the transformation you can express through a matrix multiplication.
But also, we have linear systems, so linear systems are written as matrix vector operations.
We can solve this for Beda. So why is X better than Beda is equal is X inverse times Y.
If we want ordinarily, this is this is the direct exact solution to the linear equations.
But if they don't have a solution, we can get the least squared solution by solving a different system.
Multiply. X transpo solve, X transpose, Y equal to X transpose, x beda.
I missed it x there, I just wrote it in.
Now one particular note though is so I wrote a matrix inverse here matrix and versus an operation but usually don't actually want to perform it.
Matrix and Versus are almost always used for solving a system.
Linear equation solving the system is usually a better solution than actually inverting a matrix.
So wrap up vectors represent data points in a vector space. These can be manipulated and transform, particularly by multiplying them by a matrix.
I recommend that you can salties Lynge some linear algebra learning resources to learn a lot more.