Hello. In this video, I want to introduce the idea of information theory and particularly the concept of entropy
that we use to measure information or to measure the complexity of a distribution.
So learning outcomes for this video are for you to understand the relationship of entropy and uncertainty and to be
able to use entropy to measure the amount of information in a signal or the complexity of a probability distribution.
So want to start by thinking about what does it mean to quantify information? If I tell you Apple, how much information did I just give?
You might seem like a kind of abstract question, but it turns out to be a question that we can work on answering.
Would the amount of information you would say that I gave you by saying Apple Change, if you knew in advance that I would say an English word?
Would it change if you knew that I would say the name of fruit? Maybe the name of a regional fruit or that I would name the fruit in the picture?
The idea we want to get out of here is if you knew already that I was being named the fruit in the picture,
then me telling you Apple gives you less information than it would if your previous knowledge is that I would give you the name of our fruit.
It's the key principle here is that information is the resolution of uncertainty.
If we want to start to try to quantify information or talk about how much information is in a message or is in a signal or is in a possible message,
what we want to do is we want to measure the amount of uncertainty that it resolves.
If you already know that I'm going to say Apple, when I tell you Apple, I'm giving you no information.
But if you know that I'm going to name a fruit,
then I give you the amount of information communicated by the fact that I say Apple is based on the space of possible fruits that I could give you.
If you know that I'm going to say the name of a fruit that grows in the Pacific Northwest.
Then, you know, I'm not going to say banana. I might say Apple.
I might say blackberry or huckleberry, but bananas and tropical fruits are not going to be in the sets.
You have more information, which means that there's less you have more background knowledge,
which means that there's less uncertainty that's resolved by me communicating the message Apple,
which means there's less information in what I'm communicating. We measure this in bits and the fundamental a bit one bit.
It's like the bit on your computer. If we flip a fair coin, so the probability of heads and probability of tails are equal, they're both point five.
If you know, I'm going to flip a fair coin, I flip it and I tell you heads, that communicates one bit of information.
And this is computed with the formula. The probability which is zero point five.
Times the log, which is negative one logs of values that are less than one are always negative, so.
Zero point five times negative, one, zero point five times negative, one push that all through and you get one.
This is one bit of information and we call this the entropy of flipping a fair coin.
The entropy of this probability distribution, the probability distribution characterizes the uncertainty.
There's two outcomes. Both are equally likely. We have no one from.
All we know is it's going to be one of these two outcomes. Both are equally likely.
We have no information about which one it's going to be. Uncertainty that's being resolved,
is that which coin of these two equally likely possible or which which of these two equally likely possibilities occurred?
That's the information we can receive. We call that one bit of information. One bit is which one of two equally likely possibilities.
The general version of the entropy formula looks like this. It's the sum over the possible messages of the probability of that message.
Times the log base, two of the probability of that message.
And this is the result of this is in bits.
You can do it with a natural log in which case it's called gnats, but usually we use the base to log for computing entropy.
There's a minus sign before it because probabilities are between zero and one.
All of our log probabilities are going to be negative, so we stick a minus sign in front of the whole thing.
And now we get we get positive number of bits.
And what it measures is it measures the expected number of bits that's needed to encode a message that resolves this uncertainty.
Using an efficient encoding and then efficient encoding takes advantage of the fact if the outcomes are not equally
likely in efficient encoding takes advantage of that fact to use shorter encoding for more common messages.
And so if you if you have this kind of an efficient encoding, what's the expected number of bits that are required to come in to write down a message
or encode a message that resolves the uncertainty in this probability distribution?
So if we're going to apply this, we have a fair die each six outcomes.
Each one is equally likely than the entropy of this. Die is two point five eight five.
You can run this computation through Python with your calculator to confirm that.
Now, if we have an unfair die where the probability is proportional to a VAT to its value,
so rolling a six is six times more likely than rolling a one.
We can represent this with the probability is going to be the probability of six is equal to six over twenty one.
Probability of one is equal to one over twenty one. The entropy of this distribution is two point three, nine eight.
It's lower so that the uniform distribution over a set of outcomes is the maximum entropy distribution over those outcomes.
Because if if some outcomes are more common than others, we can use shorter sequences to encode those.
For example, we could use one four to encode the most common value of six.
Or we could use zero one to encode a five. And if we do this kind of an encoding,
more common outcomes are shorter so we can decrease the average number of bits it requires to encode a message
that resolves the uncertainty of which die outcome is going to happen based on this shared background knowledge.
So a couple of a few of the key points here, so entropy measures the distribution,
and we're treating this distribution as a measure of uncertainty or of a measure of certainty or uncertainty or a measure of belief.
It quantifies how, how likely. Prior to receiving the message,
it quantifies how likely we think that how would likely different messages are based on our current knowledge is quantifies the uncertainty.
Someone received the message. We know how much uncertainty was being reduced.
This is a very Bayesian perspective on on probability, and it approximates the information requirements.
We usually do not have a full, accurate probabilistic model that completely and accurately describes our current state of knowledge.
We have an approximation, usually that approximation is as higher entropy than the actual full model will be,
but we have this approximation and we can use that then to approximate the information requirements.
The actual exact, precise amount of information is very, very difficult to compute.
But if we have a distribution that does a reasonable job of characterizing our prior knowledge,
we can use that to estimate the amount of uncertainty reduced. We can use that to quantify information we can use.
Though entropy is a building block, particularly as the measure of a complexity of a distribution,
we can use it or the uninformative ness of a distribution. We can use it to build a number of others, a number of other constructs.
And I'm not going to give you the definitions of all these in this video. My purpose here is just to introduce you to the idea of entropy.
You can go read a lot more about these if you'd like, you're going to see them in other classes,
but we can talk about the conditional entropy, which is if I know the value of X, then how much information does Y?
How much uncertainty does why reduce, which is different than if I didn't know the value of X. We could talk about the mutual information,
how much the two variables tell us about each other. We there's can I give you the discrete formula?
You can also apply information theory to continuous random variables. We can talk about transmission rates.
So far, we've talked about bits. We can talk about the number of bits per second that you can transmit over over a communication channel.
Information theory originated in or out of the early information theory.
Work was done in the context of quantifying how much information you can transmit over various kinds of radio channels and things.
We can talk about the difference between two distributions so far, these have talked about different Spacelab events,
but we have the same space of events, but two different distributions.
We can talk about the difference between them with either what's called the cold back leave,
their divergence that measures how different they are or the cross entropy, which we can derive from the K.L. divergence.
We can use these for a variety of things, we can use them to measure the complexity, the distribution,
the uncertainty that's going to be reduced by observing a draw from that distribution, we can use it to measure the differences in distribution.
This can be good for optimization. If we have some empirical data and we want to learn a distribution that approximates it,
we can do that by minimizing the scale divergence or minimizing the cross entropy to get our our our distribution as
close as possible to say the empirical data that we're observing or another distribution that we have access to.
So to wrap up information reduces uncertainty, and we measure information by measuring the amount of uncertainty that it reduces.
There are a number then of derived metrics that allow us to compare distributions,
compare or allow us to see how much observing one outcome informs us about another outcome,
and we measure all of this through a framework called entropy.