So this video, we're going to talk about what we're really looking at this week,
which is moving beyond what we've been doing in individual notebooks to being able to have a workflow that crosses multiple modules,
multiple files and is version controlled. So learning outcomes for this week are for you to be able to break code into scripts, modules and notebooks,
to design a data pipeline, to run and reproduce and analysis and use get to version control your code.
So. Notebooks are great. We've been using them all semester.
Been getting a lot of use out of them. They're great for interactive with testing code.
You can view results right with the code. The notebook is great for displaying charts and visualizations.
It can display pandas data structures very nicely. We can combine discussion methods and results for.
For documents where the methods, the computational methods are right there for exactly what we're doing.
But they don't scale terribly well. There's a few problems with them that we want to try to address.
Which is one. One is that it's hard to reuse code from one notebook in another.
There are mechanisms that you import a notebook as a module that are a little weird.
They're also not great for long running tasks. The notebook you're try to use kick off a job from the browser.
You lose your Internet connection, you go home, whatever. It's not a great environment for running a long running task.
Those are better run in a Python script directly without the notebook infrastructure.
Also, you can there are you can run a notebook from the command line,
but it's going to be overwrite options and things like that to reuse the code in the sense of a program, not just functions that you reuse.
The options are a little limited there. So to move beyond this,
we're gonna look at in this video or in this week are being able to write scripts
which are Python programs that run on their own and then to take our python code,
our functions, our classes, et cetera, and put them in the modules that we can then reuse in our scripts, in our notebooks and in our other modules.
So in this context, we're going to be thinking about data pipelines.
And so if you've got a you've got we've seen diagrams like this earlier, but if you've got some raw source data,
if you have a data integration step that's going to get you some prepared data that you analyze,
then you're going to want to do some descriptive analysis. That's a great use for a notebook right there.
You want to do descriptive analysis of the results of your data integration, data transformation.
You also want to be able to do some statistical inference. You want to be able to do some predictive modeling where you're generating predictions,
classifications, etc. Maybe you're doing inference on their accuracy.
We can think of each. So far, we'd we would put all of this in one notebook.
But in practice and a lot of projects, you're actually going to want to split that apart so that you have different stages in their own files.
You'll have likes a script or more than one script that will do your data transformation.
You'll have a notebook that does data description. You'll have a script that runs one of your predictive models.
You might have different scripts for different predictive models, etc.,
so that you can rerun individual pieces and you don't have everything in one big file that's difficult to edit and maintain.
So to wrap up significant data science projects usually have multiple components in a pipeline.
Get is really useful for tracking, for tracking and versioning the code that used to generate these components.
The rest of the video, this video's this week. We're going to talk about more about how to do these different pieces.