So in this video, I want to introduce using get to save versions of some of your project and share code with others.
So learning outcomes are for you to be able to use get to save versions of your scripts and notebooks.
Sherko to get hub and merge code changes from collaborators. This video introduces the concept.
It's not Hands-On and I'm not going to walk through the specific details of how to do each operation.
There are a lot of tools of resources online for learning get.
And I expect a number of you probably already know it, although certainly not all of you.
So I'm going to fried some links in the resources with this video to more of places where you can do hands on learning of the details of get.
I'm going to be talking about the concepts that you need to know to put it all together.
So we save files, we have scripts, you have notebooks, they're saved files.
But there are a few things we might want to be able to do. Maybe we made a change.
It didn't work. We want to get an old version of the file back. Maybe you want to make sure that we have the current version saves as we make changes.
We can't go back. Maybe we want to make sure that you have the right version of the file on multiple computers.
You've changed it and you changed it at home and you changed it at work. You want to make sure you've got the same version everywhere.
We also want to be able to share changes to our files and our projects with collaborators if we're working with others on a project.
And so give us a tool for storing versions of software or versions, a snapshot of the current state of your code.
And then it has a history of these versions. It's the first version, second version, et cetera.
So a comet. It does this with what's called a comet.
And a comet is a snapshot of your correct code with a pointer to the previous commits usually one,
but it can be two if it's the result of merging two divergent branches of code back together, the chain of commits form a history.
You can go back to previous commits, commits,
then form the basis for sharing and merging changes between multiple computers and multiple collaborators.
Few of the core concepts of Get Out First is the working tree, which is your directory of files ready to run or read it.
So you've got to work. If you aren't using get yet, you already have a working tree and then get has a repository that stores the history.
This lives inside a get directory in your working tree.
There's also remote repositories such as GitHub. You have an index which is a staging area for changes to be committed.
So you got your working treats, you stage files into the index, and then you commit them to a repository.
You also then have a branch, which is a line of development that points to a commit.
So if I've got a first commit A and then I've got a second commit B and a third commit C.
And I have my main. Main points to see, and that says OKC is the branch and it has its history going back through B and A demerging happens,
well, maybe somebody else makes a B prime from A,
and then I say, well, I want both B, NDB Prime and I merge the changes, resolving any places where they conflict and I get my commit c the domain.
The branch is updated as you make new Kimmet. So if you're on Branch Main and you make a new commit C prime.
Or as new, commit deth. Then it's going to update Maine to point to D.
So you have a local repository where you make him work your changes.
So you're working tree has a guy get directory that get directory contains the entire it contains your local repository.
It has a complete history. You have a complete copy of the history locally. You can then have configured remotes where you push and pull changes.
So if you're using GitHub, then GitHub will be a remote that your local is set up for KIPP to push to other options besides GitHub,
include BitBucket and get lab. You can also run your own server to host get repositories.
A few of the operations you're going to need to be able to perform and again,
I'm going to refer you to the resources I'm linking online to learn more detail about each of these operations.
A commit records that the commit operation or command records, the current version of your files creates and you commit.
Clone creates a repository and working tree by copying another.
So if you say if there's a repository on GitHub and you want to work on it, you clone it to your local computer.
Push sends commits from your repository to a remote, and so if you've made some changes and you want to push them, if you want to share them.
Either push the new repositories so you can access them on another computer or that your your collaborators can access them.
You use push and that's make sure that pushes you push a branch.
And what that does, it is it makes sure that the remote machine, the remote mote repository has all the changes in your branch that you have.
In fact, retrieves a different remote repository, merge merges two.
So if you've made some changes and someone else has made some changes and pushed them.
You need to merge those changes together before you can push your code backup and update your common branch pull fetches,
emerges together to update your current local branch to include the remote.
So now to talk through a few use cases here. First, the simple use case is just tracking history and a repository on your local computer.
You work on your code and notebooks. You commit when you have a version you want to save.
I recommend doing this very frequently, multiple times a day, possibly even multiple times an hour.
That way you can always go back and you have the security of if you if you accidently make a mistake, you delete the wrong file, you can get it back.
The result of this is you've got a local history to go back and recover old versions.
I also sometimes see I go K through three days, a complete week's worth of work and haven't committed.
I'd strongly recommend commit early and commit often. So another another use cases.
You've got multiple computers, you work on one machine.
You can make your changes, you push through a remote repository, maybe it's GitHub, maybe it's somewhere else.
Then on the other machine you pull to make sure you have the latest changes and you continue working.
This is significantly less error prone than manually copying files because GET is tracking your
versions and it knows that the remote is more current than your current version or vice versa.
And so if you're just copying files around, you have to keep track of which one is the latest and current version of the file to make sure you
don't accidentally copy an old file on top of a new one get since it's chaining the commits together.
It knows old versus new, and it can also merge if you made changes in both places at the same time.
It can help you merge those together. So it's a much more reliable way to share a code between multiple computers than copying files around.
You cannot directly push. I can't push from my laptop to my desktop.
I have to push from my laptop to get up and then pull from GitHub to my desktop.
I can't. You can't pull like I could pull for my desktop to my laptop.
I don't do that. I always go to get help. Another then use case is collaboration.
So you work, you commit changes from time to time when you're ready to share your work with your collaborator, you push to a remote.
You both have access to. Maybe it's your GitHub repository. Excuse me, first you poll, because you need to make sure you have your collaborators work,
because if they've pushed changes you don't have, you can't push get will say your branch isn't up to date.
I can't push. And so you pull from your local.
You collect your report remote repository to get your collaborator's work.
You merge if necessary, if you need to merging of tests, run the tests,
make sure things to work, and then push your work with the merge changes to the shared remote.
Now your collaborator can get them. They'll need to pull before they can push again.
But you can only you can only push if your Brant if you have a current copy of everything that's on the remote.
And so you have to do the pull in the merge before you can push if you have an especially active collaborator.
And it takes a little while to do your merge, then you might wind up OK.
I pulled the total merge. I'm ready to push up. They've pushed more code.
Since I pulled I have to pull again. And then your collaborator can pull down the changes.
One note here. Always commit before merging.
You can pull with uncommitted changes. But if something goes wrong in the merge process, if you've committed everything before,
you start to try to merge your divergent lines of code, then you can always go back and try again if something goes wrong in the merge.
So another thing you want to pay attention to is ignoring files.
You don't want to commit every file to get. So a repository usually has a file called get ignore to specify files to ignore.
You could also have your own settings. You can have a ignore file that's applied to all repositories.
You work on it. Say if you have a text editor that makes a particular kind of backup file.
I recommend putting that in your personal get ignore. But the things you some of the things you should ignore editor temp files some times
like Emacs when backup mode save a file that ends until the VM creates swap files.
You want to ignore those, you don't actually accidentally commit them. Macko asked, likes to create directories called Dot D.
S store. You'd never want to commit that to getting share. It's useless to your collaborators.
Python creates a variety of temporary files.
That cache transformed versions of Python code.
You may have a project recompiling some code you don't want to commit.
The compiled files, in part because you committed compiled on Mac and someone else is going to run on Linux most of your generation.
In general, if the file is generated from another file, you probably don't want to commit.
A key exception is notebook's and then some data science project.
You may store the results of analysis and get. It's not a hard and fast break if you do it.
It says if you can quickly and easily regenerate the code, it's often a good idea.
You commit source get a designed for tracking source code, not generated files.
And so. So these are some of the files you're going to you're going to you often want to ignore in the resources.
I'm going to give you an example that get ignore file. That's good to toss in a lot of Python data science projects.
So some of the interfaces and tools that you can use to work with get first the get command
line tools to get the command line tool you can use in Unix or Windows command show.
You're really going to need to learn the command line tool, even if in most of your day to day work you use other tools.
Because if you're running code on a server, on a cluster or something,
you need to be able to pull at least and probably make some changes and commit sometimes.
Also, you need your repository getting a state where you need to fix things that aren't easy to fix from the gooey.
The degrees are getting better and better about that.
But occasionally I find myself needing to go into surgery or something just faster on the command line.
But the big reason you really need to learn it is when you've got larger projects,
you're probably going to be doing some running on a remote server, not just on your local machine with graphical interface.
And you really need the command line to be able to do that. There's good get support and a lot of editors and I.D.
I used Visual Studio Code for a lot of my editing. It is very good.
Get support. And then there's get dedicated. Get DUIs like tower or source tree or get crackin.
Some of those cost tower and get crackin.
Both cost money, but they're both also available for free to the GitHub student developer PAC.
If you register your university email address, so wrap up get allows you to record versions of your code so you can track history,
rollback changes and you can share with others and with yourself across multiple computer computers.
I strongly recommend that you commit early and often to prevent lost work as you're working on your projects.