This video, I'm going to talk with you a little bit about, you can get specifically for data science projects,
so learning outcomes are understand some of the limits of get ignore data files and know some additional tools to look out for managing data files.
So it gets very good at tracking modestly sized files, far smaller than the few megabytes and text files.
It's not so good for binary files or large files, especially large binary files.
It also has some difficulties with files that are hard to emerge, such as notebooks.
A notebook is stored in text, but its text is a lot of Jason merging.
All of that is really touchy and easy to get wrong. And so it requires a little special care when you commit your notebooks to get really good idea.
Get Hub lets you view them in line on online, but you have to take a little care if you're going to be needing to be merging them.
So first, is it a data science project? We often ignore more files.
So a lot of heads, the data files, input files, intermediate files, large output files, all of those are going to ignore.
So we're going to have ignore lines for CFS fees. Yes, Fijis. We're usually going to keep the notebooks, quite possibly other documents,
and that may involve keeping outputs like the notebook source, the source code and the output in the notebook file.
We may also store other notebook outputs, etc. and get just that.
We you can view the results without having to rerun everything when you check out the get repository.
So but for dealing with these large input files, you've got your input file, it's maybe two gigabytes.
You're going to create a few hundred megabytes of output. There's a few methods.
One is that you can just expect anyone working with the repository to recreate all the intermediate output files.
So you ignore all of your data files. You include either a script or instructions on how to fetch the input data.
Maybe it's a script that downloads data from a database or fetches it from a Web site.
Then you have scripts that reproduce the intermediate files. You've documented how to run them.
The read me is a very good place to do this. You may commit outputs or summaries of the files.
You may save the results into a database or shared repository. But if the analysis is relatively cheap, this can work well.
Fetch the project. Make sure you have the current input data rerun. But if the data is not so cheap.
If you've got processes that can take a while to run in there,
then you also want people to be able to get copies of the intermediate and output files.
Maybe you've got a classification model that takes four hours to train.
What you can do then is you can, again,
ignore your data files and you can include scripts that fetch both the current in inputs and intermediate files from another server.
Maybe it's a file share on your network. Maybe it's an Amazon s three server or Buckett.
And then you could also include include scripts to update inputs of you update the input files, you update the intermediate files.
Sort of the current versions on the other server. You might again commit your outputs.
You might commit information about the versions of your intermediate files.
You can do this just by writing about just scripts yourself, or you can use this tool that does a lot of it for you.
I take this approach to a lot of my own work using a tool called Data Version Control, but I'll talk more about later.
And then the third method is to use get large file storage, so large file storage is a system for managing large media files.
And it looks like they're committed when you're working with it and get it just. They act like any other file that's committed to get.
It's just that all that actually gets committed to get as a short stub that says what the contents are supposed to be.
And the actual file content gets stored in a separate server, get ELA fast, pushes and pulls that other content to this separate server.
And when you check out every places the stub with the actual contents, you have the large file.
It works great for big files. You can commit output. You might want up committing outputs if you use this.
And if you change it and you recreate your new output files and re push.
One of the one caveat to this or one of the caveats to this is that if you use if you can run your own get hosting,
you can run your own get out fast hosting server. All the storage you want.
But if you use GitHub, their default accounts have limited space and bandwidth and the pricing on expanding that can go up relatively quickly.
And so it's often not terribly cost effective. You get L-A fast and GitHub for a lot of large data science files, but get off as is an option.
So I want to talk just a little bit about notebooks. As I said, notebooks are taxed, but they're complex, Jason.
It's hard to compare and merge them. Also, they change. You run like you rewrite. It changes the images.
It might be bit forbid, identical. It might be running with a slightly different version of the software.
So it compresses differently. Also, it has it the Jew Jupiter stores like how many times each cell has been executed in the Jason.
So there's roughly two solutions for dealing this.
This one is just committee's normal merge by taking one version or like often merged by taking one version or another or doing manual merges.
There's a tool called NDB Dime Notebook. Different merge. That gives you support for actually merging notebooks.
It's a little weird, but it does work. I have used it successfully. Also, you can coordinate, notebook, edit.
So if you if you're a small pool of collaborators, you can just coordinate, send a message on slack, say hey.
I'm really working on this and hoping for a little while. Maybe don't change it, we'd have emerged problem.
You're done. You push it and then the others just stay away. It kind of breaks a little bit of the bird Frehley with get because it's easy.
But notebooks are a little hard to merge.
Another option that doesn't fully fix the problem but makes it merges easier is to only commit the notebook without outputs.
And so there's a program called NDB Strip Out that strips the output from a notebook content.
You can wire it into gets that anytime you commit. You still have the outputs in the version you're working free.
But the version that actually gets committed, it's like you ran clear all cells before saving and that can decrease the amount of conflict
because the only thing that changes your textual descriptions and your source code,
they're both options. I tend, which when I use really depends on which project I'm working on.
A lot of my projects I commit as normal and use NDB dime. If I have a notebook murd situation.
So wrap up. Gil works great for data science but requires a few tricks.
You need to be thoughtful in how you handle data, notebooks, things like that, and get works great.
But there's a few things you need to pay attention to. Notebooks can be a little annoying.