This video, we're going to talk about the extract, transform load pattern for handling data transformations and integration.
So learning outcomes for you to be able to use standard design patterns that think about your data integration and transformation.
So we saw the pipeline at the beginning of the week.
If we have some raw source data and we want to transform it into prepared data of some kind, that's ready for further use.
Using the techniques that we've discussed earlier in the semester,
turns out that there is there are standard paradigms for thinking about how we structure that process.
And it involves breaking it down into three stages.
So extract the extract, transform load pattern takes as input a source of initial unprocessed data, the extract process or stage.
Gets the data, it exports it from the database, it scrapes it from the Web site, it downloads it from wherever the data comes from.
And it's how you get the actual raw data that you're going to be working with.
Then you transform that data into maybe you transforming data from multiple sources into a common format.
You're integrating data. You're doing some initial cleaning, like deleting invalid records.
And then finally, you load the data into a system for analysis.
And the setups we've been talking about so far that a lot of times this is going to look like saving
it in the file like a part kept file or CSP file that you then can load in the later stages.
But you might load it into a database. And the result is that you have cleaned and integrated data ready for analysis or modeling.
And this may seem certainly fairly straightforward,
but it's what we call a pattern and a design pattern is a common structure for design in general, but in our purposes for software design.
And it serves as few useful features if it accomplishes a few useful things.
First is, it gives its common language for documenting and understanding software.
So if you document I'm here's my extract my transform my load for this for processing this data,
then others will know what you're talking about because you're using familiar in standard language.
It's also provides context for developing best practices because you can document, OK, here's good ways to do extraction.
Here's good ways to do transformation. It could also in some cases benefit from the automation support.
There are automate. There are automated tools that provide extensive support for doing various types of extractions, transformations and loads.
Another example, the design is a little bit tableau between an interface in a design pattern.
But the pattern we're using this, Kate, learning of a model. You fit the model. It updates in place.
We can think of that as a design pattern for machine learning models in Python.
So in context, ECL may live in a standalone instead of a project and may live in your repository.
So you have one or more scripts to do your EDL stages.
You might have separate ones like an extract, transform and load stage that save the data in a format that's ready for subsequent stages of analysis.
You don't have to have getting things into easy to work with format, deleting invalid records,
making sure you have tabular data in your train, a predictive model stage because that's happened in your E Taliban.
All of your you can do multiple things with your clean data. And you may also, though,
have a dedicated ECL pipeline project that to give repository that just does your ECL pipeline for big win
contexts where the loaded data is going to be used in multiple different projects across an organization.
And so if you've got if you've got an organization where your processing say you're processing some
government records in a form that's going to be used for informed decision making across the organization,
then you might have an ECL pipeline that fetches the current version of the government
records from the from the the the official source does whatever transformations
you're going to you need to do with them and then load them in a database so that other people in your organization can go and make use of that data.
And maybe you rerun this once a day, once a month, once a week, whatever the right timeframe is.
So that then. Anyone in the organization who needs the data can just go to your database.
Or sometimes it's called a data warehouse or data warehouse is basically a database that's often larger and capacity
and not designed to support real time production level systems is designed for more long term querying and analysis.
But anyone can go to the database and get the data as of the most recent result or the most recent import.
And you've got this ETF pipeline that takes care of that and you can rerun it from time to time as your source provides new data.
A variant of ECL is extract, load, transform.
So sometimes you're actually going to want to do the transformations in whatever place you're storing the data.
An example of this is if you want to use ask you all queries to do your data transformation.
So you extract your ross' or your raw source data and then you load it directly into initial database tables and then you use your database system.
If it's a rescue old database, use ask you all queries, but something else, use it.
It's native data processing capabilities to do your transformations in the database.
It's usually good to do a layered schema designed to it's clear what tables in your database get the raw or get the data directly out of the load.
And then what table store the results of your transformations. But it's a very useful variant of ECL for.
For situations where you've got the capacity and the desire to do your data transformations in a database.
The book data tools that I used as an example, we were talking about data integration.
That's an example of an EMT pipeline because we extracted from several data sources.
We piped that data directly into PostgreSQL. Well, and as night native a format as we could.
And then we used escudo queries to transform it into integrated tables.
And that gives it its own get repositories that we have this database that has our book data and any we can.
Any student in my research group can use that same set of book data for whatever book related projects that they want to work on.
And then if they need new data extractions,
we'll add them to the transform layer in the core projects that others can benefit from those changes as well.
So wrap up design patterns provide a common language for talking about software design, extract, transform, load and extract,
load, transform our two patterns for doing the data pre processing stage of a pipeline for a data science project.