This video, we're going to talk about another pattern that's useful in building our data science pipelines, split, apply, combine.
We've actually already seen it a little bit,
but we're going to talk about the split of I can apply combine a pattern as a general pattern to analyze and transform data.
And so you've seen group by we we group some ratings by movie idee and then we
count the user I.D. group by is how you do split a fly combine and pandas and
we split the data by movie I.D. We apply the Operation Count user I.D. and then
we combine the results into a data frame or a series of movie rating counts.
This is another pattern and it's a pattern that does have direct computational support.
If you can fit your data in the split, apply.
Combine that pandas will take care of a lot of the bookkeeping for you in order to do a complex data transformation.
So the split stage, so partition splits or partitions, a data frame into subsets grouped by as how you do this in pandas.
So you give it a column and it's going to group by distinct values of that column.
If you want to do something like group by a range of values, then you would create another column that has the original values rounded,
that each range is represented by one value and then you can group by that. Each group results in a data frame.
You can see this if you iterate over a group by. So if you just for X or in group by data, frame that group by a column.
Then you're going to get a tuple of a grouping key.
There's a distinct set of values that indicate that of your gripping columns that defined that group.
And then a data frame that is the subset of the original data frame containing the entries for that group.
You then have the apply stage and the name, this name comes from programing languages, programing, language theory where you call flunked.
You apply a function to data is what you call it when you call a function. And pandas provide several ways to do apply.
One is AG. We've seen this many times. You at aggregate function and aggregate function returns a single value.
A transform applies a one to one operation. So the output size matches the input size.
If it gets 20 rows, it will be turned 20 rows means entering data would be an example of a trend or subtracting a value.
Be an example of a transform. So you could make a split of all I combined.
That means center's data.
By using transform compute, it takes a series, computes the mean of the series and that subtracts the mean from all the values and returns.
The result that's gonna be a transform apply applies an arbitrary function that
can return anything and maybe turn a value a series and maybe turn a data frame.
The only thing is that if we should return the same type for every partition, it shouldn't return of value sometimes in a series others.
It always needs to return the same kind of thing, but it can do any of the above.
If you know you have an aggregate right transform, it's better to use that it's a little more efficient.
Pandas actually called the apply function twice on the first group.
The first time to figure out what kind of value it's going to get. And then it goes and does the apply to all of the groups combined.
Then you've split the data into partitions. You've applied some operation to each partition.
Combine combines the results back into a final data structure. So if you're if your apply stamp returns of value,
then pandas combine is going to give you the combined stage of pandas is going to give you a series that's indexed by the group in columns.
If you're if you return to a series from the aggregate,
then you're going to get a series that is that indexed by grouping columns and the index of the result series.
And then if you're a data frame, you're going to get a data frame that if you're apply return to data frame,
you're going to get a data frame that's indexed by grouping columns. And then the index of your result data frame.
Apply your fly data frame should generally return the same columns for every partition.
Now, why do you want. Why do we think about this in these terms? If you if you formulate your data in terms of split, apply combine.
Then first, you can pandas takes care of a lot of the bookkeeping. All you have to write is your apply stage and pandas will do everything else.
It's also easier to understand the code that you could write some loops to do some complex things.
But then you have to pass out what is the Sloup doing? If you write it in terms of split up like mine and then someone reading the code, oh,
this is applies a split of like a lineup combine operation and it's easier for them to understand what you're doing.
And split up play combined is not unique to pandas. Pandas implementation is with group by R has support for split apply,
combine many different platforms in many different environments, have support for some kind of split apply combine operation.
Also, it's trivial to paralyze because there's no reason you have to do the groups one after another.
You could apply to multiple groups and parallel pandas doesn't do this.
But the package called Dask provides an API that's very similar to pandas.
It is. Well, it's a subset of the Pandas API.
It does split apply combine and it can run your apply and multiple processes or on multiple machines in a cluster.
And by putting in a split, a fly combined paradigm, you can take advantage of that parallelism very easily.
Want to talk very, very briefly about a related paradigm that's also useful for parallelism in some contexts.
Pandas does not directly support it, but it's the basis of YouTube and it's called Map Reduce, where you define two operations.
Map transforms the data and an instance into key value pairs.
One or more or zero or more actually, and then reduce transforms key,
a key and then a set of values that key to a single value you might need to reduce multiple times
because it might it might get off of what I do as a map one but one machine do the mapping.
You reduce everything to the key. Isn't that machine to reduce. So you don't have to trance transmit as much data off the pipe.
And that can be done parallel across a very large scale systems. If we want to count ratings again, what we would do is in the map stage,
we would yield the movie I.D. and the number one and then the reduced stage, we would sum up the kouts, we're gonna sum up all of these ones.
And if one is the result of another reduced, it's going to we're gonna sum that up as well.
So this is not code for any particular mass-produced framework.
It's just to show you the flavor of how Mass-produced works. Example of another pattern where if you can make your code fit this pattern,
there exists tools to automate and enhance your use of this pattern, for example, by paralyzing.
So to wrap up the split, apply a combined pattern. Let's transform groups of data and fitting code into patterns like this,
improves the understand the biology modify ability and in some cases parallelism of our code.