Let's talk about tuning hyper parameters, learning outcomes are for you to be able to apply different techniques,
to tune hyper parameters of your model and to understand the principle of random search.
So as we've seen with some of our models, we need to be able to pick good values for hyper parameters.
That might be the regularization strength in a regularized linear model. It might be in a random forest.
The number of trees with the maximum depth in the forest might be the number of neighbors for a canyon classifier.
Or if we're doing something with a with a matrix factorization or SVOD the dimensionality of the latent embedding space.
And so we need to pick good values for these. The general principles that we try different values.
We measure the effectiveness in some way, maybe the classifier accuracy,
maybe the classifier area under the curve or some other metric on some tuning data.
Often with cross-validation, we'll split the training data into multiple partitions.
So we've seen this with logistic regression CV where we try every combination of lists of values,
where we have some values for our regularization strength. Lambe They hear or see in the.
And the structure for Saikat learns logistic regression, some values for our L1 ratio row.
And then we compute the accuracy at each value and we pick the best as we see it.
It's built into logistic regression CV.
And then there's also the grid search c.v class that allows us to search any parameter of any Saikat Learn model.
So long as the model provides it ability to a score function that returns a at
some kind of an accuracy or performance score that it can try to optimize.
So grid search has a couple of issues. It was has a couple advantages.
It's simple and it's trivial to paralyze if you have access to multiple processors.
But it's expensive. If we've got any parameters, then values mean.
And then test its combinatorial explodes as particularly as we add more and more parameters.
It also only test selected values.
So here where we're selecting rows in intervals of point one, point two, and if the actual best value is point to three, we're not going to find it.
So random search is a way to speed up grid search.
It doesn't help with the well. It doesn't help with the.
Well, maybe the best values between them very much. But it does help with the the time complexity of the comments.
Horrible explosion as we acquire more and more points to sample.
The idea is that you randomly pick end points from either grade or from intervals.
You define that, you define your different parameters and you define a way to pick values,
to hybrid parameter values to try and you just pick and different combinations.
You then measure the performance and use the best one you can use.
That equals 60 the default. And so I could learn as N equals 10. If you want to.
If you want to do some more, you can do end equals one hundred. The idea though of random searches based on a couple of principles.
First, the idea that we actually don't need the best hyper parameter values for most applications.
We need good enough hyper parameter values,
values that are going to get the model to perform well enough for our business purposes or organizational purposes.
Another principle is that more than one setting is probably good enough.
And so if if we have a search space here, let's say this is lambda and this is.
And this is Roe. And we have this space here that's good enough.
If five percent of our space is good enough and we sample 60 points at random from the space.
In this case, it's uniformally up random.
But the space takes into account your probability mass of five percent of the volume of your probability is good enough.
Then if you sample 60 points, you probably have at least one good enough point.
And that set in the probability that probability is point nine five.
So the reason that's true. So G is the set of good enough points. Then the probability of picking you randomly pick a point.
The probability of picking one that's good enough is point of five.
And this is our fundamental assumption. This is.
The mark,
this this approach assumes that this particular approach to selecting how many random points you should try assumes that that this is what it means,
that five percent of the space is good enough.
The probability of a randomly selected point, according to the distribution you're using being good enough is point five if you select.
Then if we say that s 60 is this is the event random, 60 randomly selected points have at least one good enough good enough point.
Actually, completing that probability is a little bit tricky because you need to compute the probability of having one good
enough point at any one of the positions and the probability of having to good enough points at any pair of positions.
It's a fairly complex expression, but it turns out we can turn it around.
So if there's at least one good enough point.
That means it's not the case that there are no good enough points.
So the compliment of there is at least one good enough point is there is no good enough points.
And if we can turn this probability around to get the probability that randomly selected point is not good enough,
point nine five, we can just take the compliment.
And so the probability of at least one good enough point is one minus the probability of no good enough points.
And the probability of no good enough points is the product. Over 60 points of the probability that that point is not good enough,
because the only way you none of the points can be good enough is if every point is not good enough.
So this is the probability of not good enough to the 60, which is point nine, five to the 60,
push that in a calculator, going to get point O four six, which is less than point five.
So with probability better than point five, at least one of your.
Sixty randomly selected points is going to be good enough. So random search needs allows you to get away with only 60 to 100 points,
regardless of the number of parameters that sometimes go to 100 just because it allows us to get away with a smaller fraction of the search space.
Having that is good enough points. It's trivially paralyzed, but like good search because you can just paralyze over these hundred points.
It may not find the best solution. It requires us to this assumption about good enough, Saikat learned, does provide randomize search.
The random I search c.v works just like grid search CB tip. You can give it distributions of your of your points to try.
And then another one is that we can also think of hyper parameter searches optimization.
So when we're training a model or fitting a model, we're trying to find some parameters that minimize a lost function.
Hyper parameter search, we're really trying to do the same thing, we're trying to find hyper parameters that minimize the lost function,
but the lost function is cross, validate the model and compute a misclassification rate or and accuracy metric or whatever.
And we're training a model or training one model.
We've we have all this training data and we can just look up a data point and see its actual outcome and we can see our prediction.
But if we want to see the outcome of a.
Hyper parameter, we have to cross validate a model using that hyper parameter.
That's very expensive. And it also has no derivative.
And so a lot of the techniques that we use for optimizing models and solving this argument problem don't work anymore.
Or they're prohibitively expensive. So there's a technique called Bayesian optimization that works by testing the model with a few
initial points to get a starting point for how the accuracy is reflected in the search space.
It then maintains what's called a surrogate model that tries to predict the performance of new ABS unobserved hyper parameter settings.
And it uses this model to pick the next points it wants to test.
And this allows it to be more targeted in its search than just random search.
And it can it can sometimes find better solutions. It's implemented by a package called Cycad Optimized.
They have based search CV that works like randomized search or grid search c.v.
They also a function called g.P minimize.
That's a general purpose function, minimize the like psi PI is optimized function that we saw a while ago that uses Bayesian optimization.
It trades off parallelization for optimization ability, it might find better solutions.
But the next search points depend on the results so far. You can do some batch searches rather than just trying one new point.
You can say try four and then you could do that in parallel. But it's useful for complex search spaces if random search isn't good enough.
And also, you can't like random, doesn't have the ability to early stop because you need in order for the proofs,
the whole sheet to try to 60 unless you know the threshold for good enough.
But with Bayesian optimization, since it's continually trying to improve, then you can use of early stopping to say,
okay, our last five runs haven't gotten us any better, maybe we can go ahead and stop.
So in a work, I want to talk brief very, very briefly about using hyper parameter tuning in a workflow.
So far we've just included in our notebooks.
We have a pipeline that the cross-validation is just part of a model fitting process that can be useful, especially for relatively simple models.
But. We might want to not redo the hyper parameter search every time, say, we update our data.
We might want to do it on a less frequent basis. What I often do is I have a script that does hyper parameter search.
And so it'll take the training data.
It will cross validate or I'll use a tuning set and it will do hyper parameter searches and that tuning set or the cross validation.
And then at the end of that, it's going to save the optimal values it learn through the cross validation to a file, often a Jason file.
Oh, here's my parameter values and then other scripts can read it like my model training or
my prediction or whatever script can read those optimal values and use those to train.
The real model that I'm going to use for actually testing on my data.
Works great. So to wrap up, hyper parameter tuning is an expensive optimization problem.
That's really what it is. It's it. Each sample is expensive because it's costly to evaluate that loss function.
Because you have to train models on cross validated data and also it has no derivative.
And so a lot of our techniques for a lot of the techniques that are used by other
packages in the fi ecosystem in order to do solve optimization problems don't work.
But there are several techniques that are useful with good automation for integration into psychedelic.