This video, I want to talk with you about how to make a reproducible data science pipeline.
I'm not going to be getting in a lot of the details here. I mean,
are we talking primarily about concepts and giving you a pointer to some software I use that you might find useful and want to study on your own?
So learning outcomes are few to understand the value for reproducible pipeline for both science and industrial purposes.
And nowhere to read more about tools. Help build and automate them.
So reproducibility, what do we. What we mean by reproducibility is that we can rerun the code and get the same conclusions and results out of it.
And reproducibility and its related concept replicability are cornerstones of current scientific philosophy, basic ideas.
If you can only observe things all at once, it's unlikely we Valadares, but we need to be able to rise to observe it multiple times.
We need to be able to reproduce the observation. And we also, from a practical perspective, in many cases, we need to be able to rerun with new data.
Maybe you're building a forecasting model for.
For traffic at your business and you need to be able to update it based on the new data you collected this month and re for next month, you need.
You've got it, Weldy, but you just need to be able to rerun it each month as new data comes in.
You need to be able to check for bugs and sensitivity if it's easy to have a stage where maybe some P.C. or pipeline,
you ran an old version of the data. You you don't have results on the same copy of the data.
Maybe you have your rerunning things in different orders.
And so you actually have an artifact of the order in which you ran things.
Maybe you have sensitive, you random seem unlikely, but it can happen if you can rerun your whole analysis front to back.
That ensures that your actual final conclusions are based on what you thought you did because you reran all of the steps in order.
So the goal that the high level ultimate goal, four four four on reproducibility is that you can rerun an entire analysis and end with one command.
I have achieved this in one or two of my projects where there is one command and I've run it on the AA2 cluster and.
A day later, I have a fresh copy of the results. Reproduced from the from the input data.
Including rerunning the notebooks and regenerating the figures that day doesn't include hyper brammer tuning,
hyper parameter tuning would take another week. But we want to be older, rerun it past with new data, new softer versions, new settings,
a well-documented set of steps like a read me that says, OK, run these five STAP.
Do these five steps to reproduce the analysis. That also accomplishes the full one script reproducibility.
That's kind of the ultimate easy go rerun the whole thing.
You can get a lot of value out of reproducibility just with documenting of a few steps that a human can run.
But this is the idea that you can rerun the analysis end to end,
possibly on another computer, possibly new data, and you're gonna get the same conclusions.
Requirements to be able to do that is first you need to know what steps need to happen, what scripts or notebooks do you need to run,
what arguments you need to provide with those scripts, what are their inputs and outputs?
What order do these script steps need to happen in? And then there's an optional thing for optimization is my step up to date.
So it might be that one of the steps the step hasn't changed, the inputs haven't changed.
The outputs are there, so you don't need to run it again. Might sound a lot like make.
And in fact, you can make these kinds of pipelines with make if you've used that tool before.
I use a tool called data version control for this. And in data version control, the pipeline is made up of stages, each of which has input files,
output files in the command that will produce the outputs from the inputs.
And the stages are defined in DVC files that are committed to get.
You can also have a stage that only has outputs and that basically just records the presence of a file.
And then you, DVC can reproduce, stages it or checkoffs stages up to date it check looks,
it's it records the check sums of the inputs and outputs and the commands so we can see.
Has anything changed since the stage last run? Am I missing an output file as one of my input files changed.
And if anything's changed or rerun the command to update the outputs before it does that, though, it first make sure that all of the dependencies,
all of those input files it looks and sees is is for each input file, it looks, and for a stage that produces it as an output.
And if there is one at first, make sure that stage is up to date so that you're building off of the current dependencies.
And then once it's commits the checksums, all these checksums get committed to get as a part of the.
As a part of the run, so that you get there as a part of the DVC files that at stores you store in get here is the check.
Here was the input check. Some here was the command that ran and he was the output checksum.
Then you reproduced the entire pipeline by ensuring the final stages.
Maybe your notebook, along with all their dependencies, are up to date.
And that's what the DVC repro command does. DVC can also help manage data because it's committing these checksums to get so it's got an M.D. five.
Check some of the data file. Then it will.
What will you do is that you have get ignore all the output files it gets not going to manage them, but DVC will look at those output files.
Anything that's an output of a stage knows about. And it will copy those outputs to and from a data server like Amazon S3.
That makes it really easy to ensure you have a current copy of the data because it ensures your current file, the DVC files.
The DVC file says I need the data output file with this checksum and DVC knows how to
go get that from your from your data server and make sure you have a local copy of it.
So all of the things that get gives us for make sure making sure we have the right version
of the code working across multiple machines when we're working with collaborators.
DDC gives us for the data files. Some practice.
I have my entire pipeline and DVC experiment with manual commands, and then once I have the script, I want it.
I created DVC stage. It's going to run it. And then I've run expensive models on the universe.
One of the university clusters, either R2 or Bora. And I.
And so I run that. I come and I. I commit my DVC steps.
I get push. I DVC push to copy the output files to our data server.
And then on another machine, either my desktop or are our research group server.
I will pull down those data files and then I'll do my statistical analysis.
I'll work with my notebooks and things. Their notebooks are annoying to use in the cluster.
So I just do the big models in the cluster. DVC saves the data. Make sure I know what version of the data I'm supposed to be working with.
And then I get pulled DVC pull on our on our research group server,
which isn't as powerful as the cluster, but it's good enough for Jupiter notebooks.
And I make sure that I'm running on the current version of the results from the cluster.
So it makes it easy to make sure that I've got the right version of my data files across all of my different machines.
And I don't have to worry about accidentally copying a file the wrong direction.
There's other tools that can do similar things. The tool called M.L. Flow, that's one of DVC competitors.
You can build your own your own pipelines out of make if you're always in a UNIX environment.
If you're in a Java Bay, if you're doing a Java based project, Gradle was a really useful integration tool.
When my before I switched all my source code to Python,
a lot of my extensive models were in Java and I was using Gradle from my automation at that point.
There are many other tools as well. You've got this and some of them will just do the pipeline management and you have to take care of the data files.
The right system that can just do the data management. You have to do pipeline with another system.
DVC does them together. There's a variety of options, but there are tools that can help you build this pipeline.
End to end. I'm providing a few links in the resources. So to wrap up fully reproducible data science pipelines,
help science and practice and tools like DVC and make and things can help you build such reproducible pipelines.