Welcome. This is the last week of CSI 533. I want to start us off by doing some recap of what we've learned this semester.
The point to where we're gonna go in the last week or so are learning outcomes for this week or to tie up the class content together.
Give you a brief summary of what we've done, how it fits into the broader,
how it forms a broader picture into which the further topics you're going to study throughout your graduate degree will fit.
We're also going to tie up a couple of loose ends. We're going to talk about time, serious operations and modeling correlated regression errors.
And we're going to talk about how some of the things you need to do to take data science analysis,
results and outputs into publication or into production.
And then finally, I'm going to talk about some topics to study further to expand your data science skills.
So we've talked about the data science where I want to bring up the state of the science workflow again,
because it provides a context in which a lot of the things that we've been talking about fit.
We talk about how to describe data. We talk about how to integrate it, source it and transform it.
We talk about the various kinds of biases and you have to pay attention to throughout this workflow.
We have different kinds of tasks, such as modeling and inference.
I also want to return us, though, to our question at the beginning of this semester or our definition from the beginning of this semester,
that data science is the use of data to provide quantitative insights on questions of scientific business or social interest.
So the goal of all of this, what we're doing with data science, is to produce insights.
Now, there's a lot of overlap.
There's a lot of predictive predictive tools that are not necessarily being used to provide insights back to the operators,
but are being used to, say, generate predictions about customer transactions,
about whether something is fraud, whether something is a cybersecurity attack,
that the the action itself is not necessarily the model itself is not necessarily providing insights.
But we need to gain insights about whether it's working, how effective it is, where we need to go, try to improve it.
But also the techniques that we're using are applicable to other purposes as well,
such as training, machine learning models that can do various types of predictions.
We've talked about data management, so we've put primarily focused on reading from static files.
We do a little bit with obtaining data from the web. We've been processing and integrating our data with pandas.
Really useful utility skill. To take this a step further is to actually to be able to work with a database.
And so in the CSA five 10 class databases, you learn how to design data models and relational databases, how to query them, how to put data in them.
You're also going to see in other classes information about managing data that is particular to different applications and types of data.
We talked about some mathematical fundamentals, probability theory.
We talked a little bit about some linear algebra and we've used bits and pieces of it throughout the class.
You can learn a lot more about these taking math 562 and taking the linear algebra class as well.
Four. We've talked about statistical inference. We did some basic parametric pairwise comparisons with T tests.
We learned how to bootstrap confidence intervals and P values.
We learned some sampling theory that underlies a lot of statistical inference and underlies the bootstrap.
And we talked about doing inference with regression models to learn a lot.
You'll learn a lot more about this and the probability and statistics class. We've done some predictions.
We've predicted continuous outcomes with regression models. We've predicted binary outcomes with classification models.
You will learn a lot more about different models for doing. For doing these kinds of predictions in the machine learning class.
And they're also going to come up throughout a number of your other data science classes,
such as recommender systems, natural language processing, information retrieval and social media mining.
We talked about evaluating your your predictive model, your classifier or your regression based predictor.
We talked about how to do. How to do train test splits, why we need those.
We talked about metrics for assessing the effectiveness of your model.
We talked about strategies that set up to choose your models, hyper parameters. Again, you're going to see a lot more of this in C.S. 534.
We also introduced unsupervised learning.
We've looked at two different unsupervised learning techniques where we don't oppose the predictions that we're trying to do,
the supervised learning where we have a classification outcome or a label.
We're trying to predict the classifier. We have a value. We're trying to predict with a regression model.
We don't have a supervisions ignore a label that we're trying to predict. We're trying to allow the model to obtain.
To learn structure just from the input features,
we've seen how to do this with lower dimensional embedding with Matrix composition, and we've seen how to do this with clustering.
Again, you'll see more about this in machine learning and it'll appear in other classes.
We talked about workflows. We talked about the data science pipeline.
We talked about how to break code into scripts and modules, how to use get how to design, has some design pattern for your code workflows.
You're going to use this throughout your data science work, both in your studies and in your applied work when you're done.
I encourage you to take what you've learned here, refer back to the material in order to structure your assignments for other classes.
So to wrap up, this class has been designed to lay a conceptual foundation for the rest of your data science studies.
So do you take other classes? You have these concepts. You know what a classifier is.
You know how to evaluate one. You know how predictive models and statistical inference fit in the broader space.
You have a good working base to start to work with data, be able to ask questions, be able to think about how.
How to answer them and represent their answers. Other classes are going to build on these concepts and ideas.
And there's a number that you can take in the computer science department,
the math department and other departments as you complete either your master's degree or your HD.