This video I want to introduce to concepts you need to be on the lookout for when you're trying to do models and particularly in production abound.
Caught the drift of your data and your concepts. Learning outcomes are few to know critical assumptions of machine learning,
evaluation and deployment and understand how models can direct degrade over time.
So a fundamental assumption that our machine learning evaluation makes or that machine learning makes.
Excuse me, is that the test data?
Looks like the training data. The test of specifically the test of the training data are drawn from the same distribution.
And one of the really crucial parts of this is that the conditional probability.
So the probability of y given a particular set of covariates or features X is the same.
Between the two. Otherwise you couldn't do machine learning because the idea is to learn that conditional probability.
Remember that we're trying to do estimates of just conditional expectation or estimates of conditional probability.
If it's not the same and the training gave it to the test data, then you can't learn.
The training data to predict the test data. But also, if the probability of Y is not consistent, then it's we're gonna be looking at different data.
The class weights may be wrong.
If the probability of the covariates are different, effectively, we're learning from data that's distributed differently.
It might work, but it very well may not. We have this fundamental assumption.
If you're trying to learn from Trinny data to predict to predict test data, you're assuming the test data looks like the training data.
There's also then another assumption when you're trying to when your purpose of your talent testing
your model is to determine if the model is going to work well when you actually go try to deploy it.
So if you're trying to test a spam filters, accuracy you what your goal is not to build a better spam filter that works well on a test dataset.
The goal is to build a spam filter that's going to correctly classify spams as they come into your system.
And so they're we're making the crucial assumption that the probability of data, it's actually going to see the live data that the live data.
Strong from the same distribution as our test data. Because if it's not, then what we've tested it on isn't what it's actually going to run on.
And so we haven't actually evaluated the model for the perforates task,
if the the actual data is going to see come from a different distribution than the data that we're testing on.
So a few different ways that this can drift. So the crap class private lens can change.
It might just be that spams become more likely. The feature distributions can change.
So emails start using Pertti, messages start using more of a particular kind of text or the geographic
distribution of the sender changes or other features that you're using changes, but also the relationship changes.
What, like the way people write spams may change. And so then how you predict a spam from the features changes.
One particular example. So examples like December purchasing is different.
A model that is trained on January through November.
You try to predict December, December looks different because the holiday season.
Also, if you've got a model that was working great, you had seasonal effects, you had cyclical effects.
You are doing really good at forecasting. Your sales revenues for four years.
Kofod has so fundamentally changed how we go about purchasing both in person and online,
that you have a massive distribution shift in your model is no longer gonna be valid.
So how do you deal with this? I'm going to talk briefly about two ways to start trying to deal with it.
The first thing zero to do is to be aware of the proof of the assumptions that
you're making and the potential problems of a violation of those assumptions.
You even noted, go look for them. But then off line, one thing we can do is we can temporal if our data have timestamps, we can temporarily split it,
because in production, your goal isn't to predict a randomly selected set of data points from the other data points.
Your goal is to predict the next data point from historical data points.
So what you can do is you can simulate that. You can say. You're trying to predict sales.
You can set as your test data November and use trading data everything before November.
You'll want to use the Sambor because you don't want your if you like your model to look into the future.
You're violating the simulation stuff. Fidelity. And but this is the basic idea.
You train on the data before the test data and you test on on that day.
You need to hyper print are tuning. You can test on. You can use the month before as tuning data or because of seasonal effects.
You may want to use the same month, the year before. As for your hyper parameter tuning, but this is the idea.
You do this temporal split upside, you get this increased fidelity of your what you're actually trying to soft new salt.
Can you predict next data?
Given the historical data, drawback is that we're not randomly sampling the results and so we have to be a lot more careful.
But the statistical inference of the results. But. The trade off is often worth it for understanding problems that are going to be things that are
going to be deployed in a temporal setting where we expect data distributions to change over time.
Then when you go online, need to continuously monitor what your system is doing.
If you have the ability to measure its online accuracy, its making its predictions of whether incoming messages on your platform are spam.
And you can test whether that was right or not. Watch that.
But even just watching other metrics, like the frequency with which it's classifying something as spam.
If that jumps or if that drops. That doesn't necessarily mean your model performance is different, but it means something's changed.
So if. Fifty percent of your messages are spam on usually.
Or the spam reporter spam classifier flags 50 percent of that spam. And suddenly it starts only flacking 40 percent of spam.
You should look into. That's a signal that you need to look into. Why?
To see if you've got a data set shift, a status shift that's causing your model to no longer perform properly.
Also, you need to regularly retrain and reevaluate your model.
You can't just say, oh, I've got a model. It's got this accuracy. Good. Let's put it production.
Let's run it for two years. You need to retrain the model frind with new data.
And then also, you need to periodically reevaluate your model to see is it still giving the accuracy.
So we're running it for a year, collecting more data. If we tested out some new data, is it still giving the accuracy that that we expect for it?
So to wrap up. Machine learning, training and evaluation assumes that the training data and test data match each other and match real life.
You can't always rely on that. You need to pay attention to shifts in your data and in its distributions.
That makes your that either cause the model not to be able to learn from training to predict test data,
or that cause the test data to no longer be an accurate assessment of what's going to happen when you try to use your model for real use.