And this video, I want to introduce the concept of a time series, some basic time series operations in pandas.
There's a notebook also in the resources that gives you a demonstration of the PANDAS code that actually works with Time series.
Learning outcomes are for you to be able to summarize and plot time series data
with pandas and understand that Time series data is often not independent.
So at times, serious is a sequence of observations over time,
these observations may be periodically sampled, like maybe having one measurement for each day.
Or they may they may not be. You might be that you record a sequence of events like every time someone uses the card scanner at a door.
Typically, their observations are the same kind of thing. Like we have our instances in a normal data frame, the same kind of thing.
The observations we're looking at a time series are homogenous,
like the price of a stock or revenue of a country or some kind of user activity and mathematical notation.
We typically refer to a time with the letter T. And we have the current time as T t t minus one T plus one.
We often speak of times steps. So we might time as in years or months, days, seconds, whatever is appropriate to our particular application.
And it is. And we can talk about the value at time T X of T.
We can talk about X, T, minus one, etc. for the previous value, the value of the previous timestamp.
This particularly applies when we have a periodically type sample time step.
So to show you an example of a time series, this is from the movie lens data that we've been working with.
And it is by month the number of each ratings in the month.
So our time steps are months. And our value.
Is the number of ratings. For movies in time are in month t.
We can see those values. There were some spikes of growth. There were some spikes of activity here.
We've got a few one month spikes. We had a significant jump there.
And we've there's been declining month over month activity as we go into 2000 or in 2018, 2019.
So there are many ways, as we talked earlier, that are many ways we can represent time, we can have string dates, years, months.
We can have timestamps to work with a time series, though, and PAN does.
We have to convert it to a time to a date time.
We can't use pandas time serious operations without converting our time into a date time somehow first from whatever format it's in.
So the setup steps to be able to start working with time, serious data and pandas are to first create or convert a date time column.
It might be that you need to put it together multiple columns.
It might just be the you need to convert an existing column so that you have a timestamp
column of type date time for each for each of your instances in your data frame.
Then typically you're going to want to index the data frame by timestamp and then sort it by index using the sort index method.
And you can use it. There's a lot you can use a lot of date time operations without setting an index.
But setting an index is often the most convenient way to work with time.
Serious data in Pandas and Time series data is an exception to our general guideline to prefer unique indexes because pandas will have some memory,
can have memory and performance problems with non-unique indexes. You might have multiple events that happened at the same time.
The utility of a time series index around looking up things by time and by date over what that overrides.
The general concern of don't use duplicate and of avoid indexes.
A duplicate keys. So if you operations that we can perform at this time series, data one is re sampling and re sampling works like group by.
But it works on time intervals. And so in this in this code here, what we're doing is we are re sampling by interval one month.
We could sample by day, we could sample. By week.
But this is telling us that we want to group the data by one week or by one month periods so our groups will be or it's indexed by a timestamp.
But our groups are going to be October of 2000. 13.
November of 2013, and then within that, we're going to do exactly the same thing we do with any group.
We're going to pick a column and we're gonna count it. And this is going to count the number of ratings in each month.
So after the recent the results of a resample work, exactly like your group, buy into all your Google group,
I think that's just rather than being grouped by the distinct values of a column.
They're grouped by a time period of the index. Or you can also group by a column.
There's an on option for every sample that allows you to specify the column that you want
to do the re sampling on if you have not indexed your data frame by its time stamp column.
So this is our first operation. We can take it. We can sample our day.
If we have this particularly works for data that is. If this works well for data that is events, it works well for data, that is.
It can also work well for it, for data that is already sampled,
that if you've got daily measurements of something and you want to take it by month, you can re sample that by month.
You can also up sample and have it fill in missing values for time period that you're missing.
If you want to increase the resolution of data.
So another thing we can do is plot and matplotlib and Seabourne both render timestamps on their x axis relatively well.
So if I just do X and that's that line plot and I give it a series, it's going to mark the x axis by an appropriate time,
derive value in this case because my data starts in two thousand or nineteen ninety six and runs until relatively recently.
It is it's, it's, it's marking the X axis by year.
So they, they know what to do with time data, with timestamp columns.
And they will the air, they will render the x axis with appropriate labels for time, serious data.
Another operation is to be able to do a range select so time series indexes, support range operations and so we can select by range,
you can say every we want everything from January 1st through December thirty first.
Now, one key thing to note is that when you're doing a range selection of a time series column,
unlike basically every other slicing context in Python, it includes the end point.
So this this query is going to include December thirty, first all and it's going to include all day on December thirty first.
It's not going to be the usual stop right before.
We can also just pass in a partial date time in order to select by a period.
So if we want to select July 2010, we can you do that lock.
And we can look up 2010, Dasch 07. It's going to give us the ratings that are in July.
Another operation we can perform a set of operations, we can perform our diff and shift.
So the diff operation computes X sub T minus X, T, minus one.
So what it does is it computes. So we've got our it's basically the opposite of cume.
So we've got our data points. And what it does is it computes each one minus the one before it.
The first one gets narm. So your first value becomes more than your second value becomes the second minus the first et cetera.
Shift is an operation that just shifts data points by one or more time steps.
And so a shift of one which is the default, if you don't specify parameter is what we call a lag operator.
It move points down once that each one has its previous value. So def is just X minus X that shift or it's it's X minus the lag of X.
Shift of minus one is lead. So each one has the next value, if you want to compare each value with the one that's gonna come after it.
But so these are this. This diff operation and then shift, which is its building block, allow you to compare data to the previous data point.
This is particularly useful for data that is periodically sampled to its day by days or by seconds.
It doesn't it's not quite as useful by events, but. You can convert event timestamped event data into period data.
Just the library sampling. So there's a few different effects that we want to think about in Time series data.
One is a trend, which is a period over period change in values.
So if the price of something is going up and it'll be noisy around that,
but often noisy around that, but the overall trend is up as you go through time.
You can have linear trends. You can have exponential trends. When you have an.
You might hear the value are not being used sometimes in discussing disease, transmit disease transmission epidemiology.
That's a multiplier for an exponential trend.
We can have seasonal and cyclic effects with our periodic effects in the data and seasonal ones are are around this time of year.
So like holiday, if you're in a commerce setting, holidays look really, really differently than June.
There can also be cyclical effects like on a week cycle, et cetera, that does that affect your data?
People behave differently on weekends than during the week, etc.
There's also shocks which are impact events that impact the time series and change data going forward.
And these can have short term effects or they can have continued effects. But a shock is like an outside event.
Like if your time series is, say, the the price of a stock, a shock would be an event that affects the stock price.
One thing that's important to know about time, serious data, is that as often what we call auto correlated, which means correlated with itself.
Because it's X, sub T plus one at exit two, plus one, an exit T are not independent.
Today's weather is probably more likely correlated with tomorrow's weather than it is weather in three months.
So if you have observations of a variable over time, especially that you're trying to predict the future with today.
It usually violates independence. And so we're going to need to take special care in order to model what's going on when we have data.
And even if we have other predictive variables.
There's a non independence between from one step to another that we need to account for when we're doing statistical modeling.
So to wrap up repeated data over time requires particular handling and are distinct operations to work for it.
PANDAS provides access to daytime columns, daytime indexes to allow you to do various times serious operations.