This video, we're going to talk about correlated errors,
so the previous video we talked about time serious and we talked about autocorrelation where its value is correlated with the value before it.
This video, we're going to talk more generally about the idea of correlated errors and how they can be addressed.
Now,
I want you to be able to know when you need to look for a model that can handle correlated errors and know a few of the models you need to go study.
So observations, linear regression has this assumption that we've particularly our errors are independent, but often they aren't.
So if we've got time series data, we have this autocorrelation that will manifest in non-independent errors.
We don't control for it within subjects, designs and experimental design, where you have each participant gets more than one treatment.
And you want to compare how the treatment performed within the same person. You're not independent because.
Do you have. There's a person level effect and the the the person has a certain propensity to the outcome that you're trying to measure.
And then the treatments also go into effect. You can have other data that can be grouped as well.
If you're trying to to study medical outcomes and you're assigning people to a treatment or a control group, even though within the same hospital,
like people that are being treated by the same medical staff,
might have different outcomes than people who are being treated by different medical staff.
And so if you just pull all of the participants together, you can have this non-independent,
that student that participants at one hospital are more likely to look like each other than they are likely to look like participants,
more random other hospital.
And so, for an example, to talk about this more concretely, I want to talk about you're trying to measure search engine effectiveness.
So you have to search algorithms. Maybe you're working for Google or you're working for for Microsoft on being working for some
other somewhere else where you have a search setting and you've got to search algorithms,
maybe ones your current one and one's your proposed new one, or you're trying out two different possibilities.
Users issue queries and you're trying to measure and the search systems return results and
you measure the accuracy of the result list that you get back from each search system.
And so your data point, your instance consists of a query and it consists of the responses from one of the search systems,
along with which system generated those responses. And it might be that we somehow have experts assessing how good the results are.
It might be that we're looking at quick click logs to collect. We actually have users. They issue a query.
One of our systems returns results. So we see how likely they are to click a result and how high up in this is in the search list.
The result they click is that we use that as the basis to measure how good the searches are.
The problem is that these results are not independent.
We have these queries and if the same a query appears multiple times, not all queries are easy to are as easy to answer.
Maybe one query has more documents that are relevant.
Maybe one query has no documents that are relevant. Maybe queries have language that matches your documents or matches too many documents, too.
It's hard to figure out which one in particular the user is looking for.
There are many different reasons for query difficulty. You can take the information retrieval class to learn about a lot more about that.
But this is the setup for that. I'm going to use as an example here we have queries.
Query might happen multiple times, like people will probably search Google for Pendas Time series a lot.
And so you're trying to measure the effectiveness of your two systems at these repeated queries.
So a naive solution without taking into account the correlated errors is what you
might try to build a linear model where you might try to try to do a T test,
but you might try to build a linear model where you have Alfa's your intercept and you
have a variable that says whether it's provided by the new system or the old system,
if you have more than one more than two systems, it will be a dummy coding of which system is as providing the results.
And we have our errors and we're trying to predict our outcome outcome as some metric doesn't really matter which one for our purposes right now.
And so beedis of new is going to be greater than zero if the new system performs better than the old one.
We're gonna want to check the confidence interval of this. But the problem is, as I just said,
these epsilon's are not going to be idee normal because the Epsilon's for the same
query are going to be more like each other than the Epsilon's for a different query.
That's a lack of independence. So the solution to this is to use what's called stratified errors or group effects.
There's a lot of different names for a similar concept, but the idea is to allow the query to be a predictor variable, too.
Now, one way to do this is something called repeated measures.
Enova or repeated never measures in other requires you have a very balanced and matched design.
The next effect's model is a little more flexible. And what it does is we've got our model before.
We've got our intercept. We've got our Beda. But then we also have this query effect.
And so this is a per query value and you're talking to Wilma about how you actually find it's actually coefficients.
On the one hot encoding of query as a categorical variable.
And then we have our error. So what this.
This is called a mixed effects model because it combines two types of effects.
The fix effects, which are what we control, the experimental condition.
The thing we're wanting to test, we are looking for the coefficients on the fixed effects.
In our example, it's which search algorithm we're using.
And then we have the random effects, which are the experiments, natural sources of variance in this case.
It's the queries. They said this is what this is actually coefficients on a one hot encoding the query.
And so we're effectively we're making a query as a predictor.
And what's going to happen is the intrinsic difficult relative.
Difficulty, your years of the query is going to be encoded here.
And this is going to capture the concept of given a query of a particular difficulty.
Does the new system perform better than the old one,
and that's going to give us a much more accurate picture of the performance of the new search system.
And ideally, once this is done, we saw you always check your assumptions.
We have a much better chance that the epsilons of eyes are going to be idee normal.
Not necessarily. Still might not be enough to capture everything that's going on in the model.
But if your primary source of variance that you have a problem with or your primary
source of structure or correlation in your errors is effects within a group.
You have your observations come in groups and there can be a group level effect.
The mixed effects model allows you to control for those group level effects to get a much more accurate estimate of your actual experimental effect.
So the basic idea here is that when you've got correlation or structure in your residuals, you can.
You can try to model that directly. So random effects capture these natural but known sources of variance between observations.
And then the performance becomes the system effectiveness, plus or minus the query difficulty.
And then, as I said, hopefully you're a man who wears the jewels or idee normal. And now you're linear model interpretation works again.
So we've taken something that didn't work as a linear model. You've got structure in your errors because you've got this within query correlation.
Or non-independent. But you can. We've now taken that effect out and now our errors are just the remaining error.
So when do you need to use this kind of an analysis design?
Basically, any time your data points come in groups, you need to think about using this kind of an analysis design.
Well, any time you trying to do a regression and your data points come in groups,
you want to think about this kind of analysis design, you might have multiple measurements for the same object.
The key thing, though, is that if you're trying to assign understand the difference between measurements,
you're trying to understand the difference between objects.
You're just measuring them with multiple devices, then the object would be a fixed effect and the measurement device would be a random effect.
Remember, the fixed effect is the thing you're trying to study is the thing you're controlling and manipulating in your experiment.
And the random effect is the other sources of variance that you need to account for.
Also, if you have an extra feature that's being shared, you've got a feature that's being shared between instances.
You might want to model that as a random effect as well.
If you don't care about learning the effect of the feature, you just need to control for the effect of the feature,
then it can work as a random effect of the mixed effects model.
You can also have nonlinear mixed effects models for doing categorical regression, buisson regression, etc.
So now to go back to the autocorrelation that we talked about in the TIME series, video time series data that says correlated with itself.
So it raises the question, can we predict exit time T with X at time T minus one?
Also, if we removing that prediction, removing the autocorrelation may let a linear model work for other effects in the data.
And so the idea of auto regression is that you predict data point with history, so X sub T,
we try to predict it with a linear model vadis of zero and Y Gamma one, x T minus one.
So basically each one is a linear function of the previous value. You can generalize this to more than one previous value.
So.
If the aiyah k auto regressive category or the auto regressive model of order K is going to look at the K previous points, I'm summing one Dekay here.
And what this does is that it me, it was a shock or a change and it changes the value of your time series.
That effect will accumulate and carry forwards. If you got a change, then that changes.
That changes at time, T. So then time T plus one since that has the odds is based on time t it key.
It carries the value forward and then carries it forward and the T plus two etc.
A moving average uses the area from the previous prediction to predict the next point.
So X of T is our intercept, plus a coefficient times the error at T minus one, and then it has its own error.
And then likewise, we can have a K which looks at the previous K errors.
What this does is that an adjustment or a shock wears off.
So it'll affect it for the first few points and then it will its effect will wear off in the.
And the data will regress back to its mean. Now we can put the auto regressive model in the moving average model together into a model Koldo Rhema.
And so it is an A.R of P model. So the Rhema peak you are is a R of P and a moving average of R,
so we can model can capture both long term effects of a change and short term wearing off effects of a change.
And then also it's applied to diffs.
So Q If Q is one, then rather than modeling the time series data itself, we're applying the ARMM models to the diff of the Time series data.
If it's two, then if the diff of the diffs oftentimes that the auto regression in moving average acquire the model to be what's
called stationary and sometimes duffing that often defining your time series can bake it at least stationary enough.
We can also think of the auto regression and the integration parts as a type of feature engineering.
So if our data points and we've got these X values, we're engineering the feature, the value with the previous timestamp or we're X of we're.
We're engineering the feature difference from the previous timestep or.
The difference at the previous timestep, so time t we have the feature X, T minus one, minus X, T, minus two.
That's one way you can think about the auto regressive part and the integration part of the Arima model.
Now, we can integrate then this with prediction, because we can use a rhema to model the natural time series behavior of the data,
and then we can combine that with additional variable from features,
maybe is during a holiday or you've got a feature that it turns one at some point in time
and then stays one throughout the rest to capture a change that happened in the system.
And you can use it with this design, then beedis of one is going to be the in fact,
the influence of that feature after we've controlled for the normal temporal behavior of the data.
And then hopefully our Epsilon's some Ts might be idee normal now.
And we can get back to the point where our linear model works again.
Now, I've tried to give you the rough shape in the rough structure, which is that you know what, you need to go study and you have a starting point.
What I told you was not enough to go effectively apply a rhema.
There are resources. I'm pointing to you to one extended slide deck that that talks a lot more about Rhema.
If you need to use Erina four times serious modeling, you do need to go do some more study.
There's also a time series, analysis class that you can take in the math department and spend an entire semester learning how to do time,
serious analysis with models like a rhema.
So to wrap up, we often have structured errors in a regression problem and in some cases modeling that structure.
This is a structured. Errors mean our errors aren't. Independents were violating a key assumption for the inferential validity of linear regression.
But in some cases, we can model that structure. Either the rant, the random effects of a mixed effects model,
modeling the effect of which group a data point is in eurema model modeling temporal
effects of the data in order to yield a model that is inferentially valid.
Again.