We've talked a lot about how to do the analysis part of data science.
I now want to take this a little bit of time to talk about what do you need to do in order to take that and actually put it into a publication.
So we're going to talk about you.
I want you to understand what's needed to go from analysis to a published report and also to be able to outline a research paper.
So a lot of different audiences that a document that comes out of a data science project can before it might be an internal document.
Just for our collaborators to update them on some analysis you're doing as part of a project.
It might be a report that's intended to be used by decision makers in order to make a data informed decision.
It might be a report for other elsewhere in your organization or else other organizations.
It might be a scientific publication for the scientific community and or it might be a document intended to educate the lay public.
So there are a variety of formats that these can come in. One is that it could be a written document that's either electronic or printed.
It can be a presentation that you're giving live or that you're recording as a prerecorded video.
It could be an interactive online demo or dashboard. These happens for product dashboards and internal monitoring all the time.
They also happen sometimes in journalism where a.
A news organization will make an interactive data visualization to allow people to explore the data that underlies some of their reporting.
The goals of a publication of any of these forms, any of these audiences is that the reader needs to be able to understand what you did,
what you learned, and then what they should do or take away with it.
This is in general, not every analysis is going to have actionable. Here's what you need to do.
Kinds of insights, but your readers need to understand what the takeaways are and why they should believe them.
That's the part of the being able to communicate your methods is to show.
The evidence behind showing your work at showing the evidence behind the conclusions that you're drawing.
So the typical outline for a lot of publications, particularly scientific publications.
But a lot of other publications are going to have so many of these same outline elements
is that you first have an introduction that sets the stage for why you're doing this.
Oftentimes an introduction will also for.
Foreshadow the conclusions of the report of a data analysis, particularly a scientific publication, is not a mystery novel.
You should not keep your reader guessing until the end. What the conclusion is, you can just say it and need action.
We're trying to solve this problem. Here's the bullet point summary of what we found.
And then you get into the details, then you've got background and related work and background and related work are not the same thing,
but they're often put together in one section. Background is background information that people need to understand what you did.
Background on the problem. Background on the methods that you're using to apply it.
You know, there is common knowledge that you can assume. And what that common knowledge is varies from audience to audience.
But the background is there to the background is the material that they need to understand.
On top of the common assumed knowledge in order to understand what it is that you did.
Related work is other work working on similar related problems that might be working on the same problem with different scope, different methods, etc.
It might be using the same methods for a different problem,
but it fills in the place of the other knowledge that we have about the problem space that you're trying to study.
So people have a context for how your Rinella assess is filling in a gap in our current knowledge.
So the background is the prerequisite knowledge and the related work is the adjacent knowledge.
And between them, your readers will be able to understand what you did and understand how what you did contributes to knowledge.
The methods are where you explain what you did. What's the data? What's the statistical methods you did?
What's the machine learning methods you did? As I say, in the variant side, methods may sometimes be split.
So if you've got something where maybe you have a new algorithm and then you're doing experiments on it.
Those who usually be separate methods, you've got your. Here's my new algorithm.
And then maybe as an experimental result section, you'll have methods and then results.
Then you have your result. So the methods are here's the experiment, I'm going to run the data, I'm going to use Hymes setting up the experiment.
Results are OK. So I did that. What do we learn?
It's where you have your key figures and charts, et cetera. You're presenting the results and run the experiment.
Discussion, then, is where you talk about what the results mean.
So you have the individual results of a chart that shows the accuracy of a model, you have a chart.
You have a chart that shows what's happening in some data over time.
Discussion is where you pull it together and you connect the results that you have
back to the original problem context that you put forward in your introduction.
And then finally, in the conclusion you summarize takeaways of the paper and you often point to what some future work, maybe some variance on this.
Some research communities put related work at the end right before the conclusion.
Here's everything I did, by the way. Here's what other people did. Now we conclude.
If you're doing something that's not not a scientific publication, but it's an institutional report.
A lot of those often lead with an executive summary. That's one to two pages with the key points and takeaways.
And it does not get into all of the methodological details, but it summarizes.
OK, here's the key. Here's what you need to know. If you trust me that I did all the details.
Right. Well, the analysis. Right. Here's what you need to know, where here's the recommended course of action.
And then the rest of the report. Backs that up.
And so if they have a question of how you know, the things you're telling them,
they need to know why they're where their recommendations are coming from, they can go read the rest of the report.
And some writing you might merge discussion with results, you might talk about the results and talk about what they mean together.
You might merge discussion with conclusion. We have a longer conclusion that does the discussion integrated.
But these are the key pieces usually in this order for the typical kinds of research papers,
but also other kinds of documents that come out of data science projects.
Another point you need to pay attention to when you're going into publication is rendering your plots,
especially if you're going to a publication, they might be printed or anything.
That's where you're delivering as PBS. And so this key thing is that you want high quality images.
And when practical vector images are good. Python plotting software can export an image to PDAF low tech and pull in the PDAF.
And there's nope, it's not rendered to pixels, it's actually includes all of the paths, the circles, the letters.
And so you can zoom in that PDAF as far as you want and you're never hitting pixelation.
If you have very complex image, it can overwhelm pdaf,
you wind up with a PDAF that just takes forever to render because you've got an image that's trying to render five million data points.
So in those cases, or if you're working with software that you were, you don't have a good vector image path,
high resolution images, PMG, you don't want to use JPEG, never use JPEG for a figure because J.
Peg loses information in the compression use PMG or TIFF and at least 300 Deepthi.
Six hundred is better. Your typical printer is around 300 S.P.I.
And so if your image is 300 DPN, most people will be able to print it.
Well if it's six hundred GPI, basically anyone can print it.
Well and also look very good on high resolution screens. You want to make sure you have clear labels and captions, distinct colors, shapes, et cetera.
So the image is clear, readable, self-contained.
Oftentimes we'll have it like outdraw seven different versions, image or holle a bunch of different figures.
But then I'll combine them together. I'll have the one clean picture that has all the pieces, all the bells and whistles.
Everything's very, very.
I pay particular attention to the precise wording and consistency of the labels and everything that's gonna go into the final publication.
Then you also are going to want to experiment with dimensions in aspect ratio.
So if I've got a two column paper so that my columns are about three in that three point seventy five or so inches wide,
I might have a five inch wide image and then I'll scale down a little bit to fit in that column and it'll look really good in the final paper.
Another thing, though, that you need to be able to do is to check the writing in the presentation, step outside yourself.
Forget that you did all of the work and wrote the document.
Forget all of the knowledge you have or set aside all of the knowledge you have as the person who did the work and read what you wrote and ask.
Do I understand this is if I was not the one who created this?
Can I understand it? Could I reproduce it? Is there information that's missing?
Other readers help you with this. And you should get input from other people who weren't you.
But as a first pass, in order to make the most use of the time, the best use of their time as you can.
You need to be able to to set aside your knowledge as the creator and evaluate whether what you wrote is clear and complete.
And in a coherent order. And this applies to any kind of writing you're doing,
both presenting the results in a report from a paper, but also in other writing like documentation.
Writing a read me about how to run your experiment.
You need to be able to step back and ask if I followed the instruction, the steps of these instructions, one after another.
What I get the result or is there a piece? Is there are there steps that are missing?
Are there pieces or knowledge that are missing?
So if I just read this, these instructions say in this read me file, I would not have enough information in order to complete the expected activity.
So to wrap up internal and external publications require special attention to writing and the visual presentation.
Hopefully this gives you a little bit of a start for learning how to do that.