This video, I want to talk with you a little bit about what you some of the things you need to consider in the
design patterns in order to be able to take your data science results and then put them in production.
So the learning outcomes are for you to understand how data science outcomes can be used in
business settings and think about what you need to do to put models and outcomes into production.
So variety of purposes, data science, conservative business.
We can use data driven reports to inform decisions we can do forecasting for internal purposes to inform internal decision making,
internal planning purposes.
We can also have data set out science outputs for Real-Time, decisions either internal for making internal business decisions or customer facing.
Part of your e-commerce platform, providing recommendations, doing fraud detection,
various things in order to make your customer product, your customer experience, work smoothly.
So one of the first things is that reproducibility is crucial.
If you've got if you've maybe if you're running regular forecasts of future business activity or future demands,
you can do inventory planning to be able to rerun those reports.
You need to have a reproducible pipeline so you can rerun this week's report quickly and easily without having to do a bunch of manual labor.
You also need if you're if you have something that's online, making online decisions, you need to be able to retrain it as new data comes in.
So for online use, we're building an app or building a data science product that's going to be making decisions
in an online fashion as as new users come in or as new decision requirements come in.
There's a variety of modalities for delivering. It might be a Web app, a mobile app, a desktop app.
It might be something that just lives in server side infrastructure, like the spam filter that's built into email, infrastructure, etc.
But in terms of the technology structures, there are some exceptions. But mobile and desktop apps often use Web technology to connect to models.
So even if you're targeting mobile apps, even if you're targeting desktop apps,
learning to build Web based services for data science outputs is going to be a really useful skill.
Multiple audiences can try to use these. You might have an internal recording dashboard that talks about your customer volume or it talks about the
throughput on your assembly line or other aspects of the of the functioning and health of of your factory setting.
You can use it for internal decision making and then also either to help your customers make
decisions or as you're making decisions about your customers in an online interactive setting.
So one architecture that's common for these kinds of applications is what's called a service oriented architecture.
And what a service oriented architecture means is that your infrastructure is split in the different services, different individual pieces.
So you've got a Web server and you're your customers or your users come in with a computer,
with Web browser, maybe with a mobile platform, talks to a Web server that serves up the application.
The mobile, the mobile platform might talk directly to backend.
Then the Web server talks of various other services in order to complete in order to fill out.
It's the user experience.
Those services then go and they get data from various databases in your back end in order to serve up the responses to the requests.
So a lot of organizations use this.
Amazon uses service oriented architectures extensively.
So when you go to a page on Amazon.com, there's one service that's providing product details and other services,
providing people also bought recommendation and other services handling the shopping cart.
And so each of these services are working and are working independently and the Web server is putting them together into a composite experience.
So from a data science perspective, a lot of what happening is you need two pieces, you need a UI.
And in the Web server, it might the UI might come from the service itself,
but you need a user interface component and then you need the service itself is going to serve up the data science.
Usually it's going to be some kind of a prediction.
It's going to serve up the results of running the model that you've trained, the machine learning model that you've built and trained on the new data.
To answer that particular request. So a lot of your work is going to be building up service.
And one way to design it.
And this goes well with the service oriented architecture is each different model that you have can live in a different service.
So to deploy, the predictions are made available with a Web service like your Web server.
Might it you might use other things. You might use something like zero MQ or some other or thrift our or some other RBOC
protocol or you might use it HDP rest API for the Web server to talk to these services.
One example is tensor flow serving if you're building your machine learning model with Tenzer flow.
There's a program called Tensor Flow Serving that allows you to upload your saved model and and service requests based on that model.
So you got to train the model offline and other hardware so that your your online system can just keep running.
You're not using it. C.P.E. power to train the model.
It's just dedicated for serving up responsive, serving up recommendations, making decisions about new incoming messages, etc.
On other hardware, you train your model on your model you like, you save that train model to disk somehow.
Well, or you might actually upload the model directly. Some have a model server, but you save it somehow and you make it available to the service,
which will then reload the model and start serving up predictions from the new model that you just trained.
So a few useful capabilities for building out this kind of infrastructure are to be able to train
models and live or freshly exported data CENI be able to get your current data from the database.
So you've got all the current customer transactions and then you train your statistical model on them.
Part of that process, it's useful to be able to hold out test status.
You can train this model, you can test it again before you to fly it to make sure you didn't accidentally train a model that performs badly.
It can be useful to version your models so that you have the ability, particularly in the rollback to old model version.
Maybe you train the model, you test the model. It doesn't work. You and you find out you can put it in production and suddenly your spam filter
metrics change to be able to as a stopgap rollback to the previously train model.
So you can then go figure out what went wrong with your model without leaving your customers at the new bad experience.
The exact details of this depend a lot on your institution, your product, your infrastructure.
But these are some of the things that you need to be able to keep in mind skills that are useful to learn in order to build this.
So Web back end programing to build the service web front end programing, you know, better build dashboards to build the user interface.
It's pieces that are going to make your service visible and available to users in some organizations
that kids are going to be handled by other people on your team or by a completely different team.
But in some many cases, it can be useful.
You at least need to be able to talk with those people and then also be able to do performance measurement and tuning to understand.
To be able to debug if your model's performing too slowly. So to wrap up many data science projects,
result in online production capabilities is often done by training a model and deploying as a Web services or some other kind of network service.
And it's useful to be able to learn at least some of the skills in order to do that,
or at least be able to talk with the other folks in your organization that are handling that deployment and monitoring.