So you've learned a lot this semester, I hope this video I want to talk with you some briefly overview,
some more things to go learn and give you pointers to places where you might be able to go learn them,
learning outcomes or which you used to know some topics and some software to study for expanding your data science skills.
You do not need to study all of this to be a competent data scientist, but also to have some input,
some data points to be able to help select the classes you want to take to complete your graduate degree.
So to learn more about machine learning and statistics, we've just introduced the basics.
As I said early in the semester, basically every almost every week of this class could be an entire class on its own.
So six, five thirty for the machine learning class.
You're going to learn a lot more about different machine learning models, how to build them, how to optimize them, how to evaluate them.
We've learned that the concepts, what they do, what they are, how a couple of them work.
534 is going to teach you a lot more about the insides of machine learning model math, 562 probability and statistics, too.
If you want to learn a lot more about statistical inference, that class will teach you five.
Seventy two is going to teach you a lot more about computational sides of statistics, particularly a lot of simulation things,
Monte Carlo simulations that are useful, the kinds of things you do with simulation, the kinds of things you're doing with bootstrapping.
That class is going to go into a lot more detail on Time series analysis.
If you want to learn a lot more about that, we have an entire class on it.
If you want to learn more about working with text to key topics, to be looking at our natural language processing and information retrieval,
computer science class has a department, has classes on both of those.
For working on specific application areas, if you want to do work on social media, you can take CSI 539, the social media mining class.
If you want to do work on information retrieval, we have two classes on it.
Five thirty seven, which is the how information retrieval works in six thirty seven, which is an advanced research class on information retrieval.
If you want to one about recommendation and personalization, you can take C.S. 538,
which discusses how to build recommended building, evaluate recommender systems to recommend products to people.
Software engineering skills are really useful for be able to take data to take your data science and connect it into product.
So to that end there, CSPI 73, the advanced software engineering class, it's useful for learning the process of software engineering.
It's also studying programing practices in software engineering in general on your own and practicing practice,
practice, practice, write code, do modeling, build web applications around or build applications around your data science analysis that you're doing,
but also then reflect and think about things as you write code.
Think is this readable? How can I learn? What do I know? What could I do to try to make this more readable, more efficient?
What do I think I need to go learn in order to expand my ability to do that advanced machine learning.
So we have a class on deep learning. See a six thirty three also learning software.
So Tensor Flow, Pi Torch are both useful for each useful pieces of software to learn to go beyond what you can do in Saikat learn.
And they are often associated with deep learning and they're used extensively for deep learning.
But they're not just deep learning packages. What they really are is it is very effective optimization engines that are useful for
modular differentiable like you set up a differentiable model and they optimize it.
So a lot of those models are deep neural nets. But there's a lot of other kinds of models.
I've used a tensor flow, for example, to build advanced matrix factorization.
There's nothing neural going on.
It's just a matrix composition, but it's taking advantage of tensor flows optimizers to build a recommendation engine around that.
And so either Tenzer flow or PI Torture's very useful software as you're trying to build your own machine learning models.
And it's a lot easier to use one of those pieces of software than to build your entire optima, your own optimizer from scratch.
I personally do a lot of work with Bayesian inference. That's a useful statistical paradigm and philosophy to learn.
Unfortunately, we don't have a class here that teaches it really.
But the books, Statistical Rethinking by Richard McIlwraith is a good book for learning that also software standard software is really good for doing.
It used a lot for Bayesian inference. That's not the only thing you can do.
It's useful for a lot of scenarios where you're trying to do what it is, isn't it?
It's it allows you to draw from arbitrarily complex distribution, not arbitrarily complex,
but allows you to draw from complex distributions connected to data.
PMC three, a similar software that works directly in Python Stand, has a good bridge to Python as well.
It's also really useful to learn causal inference and we don't have a dedicated causal inference class.
But you will learn a lot of causal material in the advanced econometrics class, in the economics department.
Also, there's the book counterfactuals and causal inference that you may wish to read and ordered learn causal inference techniques.
If you want to learn more about critical perspectives on data science, it's a variety of resources I can point you to.
So the book data feminism that I listed in the Class Resources is a good primer on critical thinking on data.
There's also if you want to get an example of some of the kinds of things that critical data scholars think about.
There's a short little book called Data Now Bigger and Better.
That is a selection of essays on data from a critical and a particularly from an anthropological perspective.
Also, if you want to learn more,
if you want to learn more about the underlying philosophies and mechanisms by which science in general, not just data science works,
Sergius is Mondo's introduction to science and technology studies is very good and a keyword that you can go look for to find much,
much more reading as critical data studies. So to wrap up, this class has laid a foundation for you to integrate further knowledge.
Never stop learning new things. There is so much more to learn as a student and as a practitioner to be able to do good and effective data science
and bring data to bear on questions that you have and decisions that you or your organization needs to make.