We're now at the end of the semester. I hope that you've learned a lot.
I have hope that you found the time that we've spent together to be educational, to be enjoyable.
We just have the final exam and turning in your last assignment left to go.
I have greatly enjoyed the time that you have spent together.
I have enjoyed learning from you as well for the comments and the questions that you asked through I read in your work.
Effective teaching is not a one to bet as want, not a one directional thing.
But I hope that always in the classroom that we learn from each other.
As I've said a few times, I'm hoping to use a lot of this material in the future.
So if you have feedback for how to make that more effective, for how to make good use of it,
for improvements that I should consider making to the material, to the core structure, I would love to hear it.
I've created a field for that in the course evaluation form. You could also email me or you can post it on Piazza.
I also hope that I'll see many of you in classes in the future. As I said before, I am teaching the recommender systems class in the spring.
I would love to have you in that class. I also hope to meet some of you in person, those who I haven't met before.
Once the university is able to return to instruction, to in-person instruction, hopefully sometime next year.
Please keep in touch. You know how to get in contact with me if you need input on data science.
If you need input on how to structure, navigate your academic career.
I'm happy to talk with you. I hope that you have a good close to the semester as you take your final exams and
that you get some rest over break and have a good rest of your academic year.