This video I'm going to talk with you about how to describe distribution,
so I said one of the learning outcomes with this week is that we can describe the distribution of a variable both numerically and graphically.
And we saw some of that in the descriptive statistics in the previous video.
We're going to go deeper into that in this video. So we want to be able to learning outcomes for for this particular video or to be able to provide
numerical descriptions of the distribution and visualize the distribution of a variable.
So the question when we ask, how is a variable distributed? There's a few questions that we want to.
A few things we want to break that down into four specific questions.
First, what is the average value mean or medium, whichever is appropriate?
How spread out is the data? This these two things really give us a lot.
Where is the data? How spread out is it? Tell us a lot about it.
But then we want to look at is it skewed? Does it do values tend high?
Or do they tend low with respect to that that average value?
And then what does the data actually look like visually?
So the numeric descriptions, the previous videos, descriptive statistics give us quite a few.
The described method gives us a quick way to generate several of them.
So I generated a ten thousand random numbers. And they've got a mean and a median, both of about five.
They're spread out. Excuse me, a standard deviation about one.
So these numbers visualized or we can visualize them in what we call a histogram and a histogram shows how common different values are.
The x axis are the values themselves. And the Y axis is how frequent that value is.
It can be either account, the number of values, the number of observations that are about that value, or it can be relative.
The percent or fraction of observations. This is account one. We can see it goes up to twelve.
The Y axis goes up to twelve hundred. When we had a continuous variable, the number of Binz control the division points.
So I said Binz equals twenty five. That divides the variable into twenty five.
The range of the of the variable as we've observed it in the twenty five bins of equal width.
And so for each bean it's showing how many values fall into that bean.
So the largest bit is just over twelve hundred centered right at five.
This data is also symmetrical. There's no skew to it.
There's a little bit of variation in the size stapes, the two sides, just the way things fall into the bins.
But there's no significant skew. It's evenly distributed around the mean, the mean and the median are equal reflecting that.
This this function, the highest function comes from the library matplotlib.
So the import for that is import matplotlib, that pie plot. The typical name for that is PLDT.
And that gives us functions to do. Plotting matplotlib is one of the fundamental plotting libraries for Python.
A lot of other plotting libraries such as Seabourne, Plot Nine, et cetera, are built on top of matplotlib.
So if we want to look at some real data, we can look at the average rating for movies.
So remember, we have this movie data set. We've computed each movies average rating.
Well, how are those average? How are those average ratings distributed? So, I mean, is three point seven the median is three point one five.
The there's a little bit of a what we call a left skew and the left skew this the direction and the skew is how far out.
The longer tail goes. So left skew means we have a longer tail on the left and the data is more bunched up on the right.
We have a longer tail on the left of the histogram. We can see that. That gives us a slight left skew.
The mean is slightly less than the median. That's also an indicator of left skew.
But it's not very skewed. The mean and the median are pretty close in this case.
We can also look at the movie rating count. So this is the distribution. So we have a variable.
So for each movie, we've got these two variables, its average rating and and the number of people who rated it.
And so we can look at the distribution of the movie rating count. This distribution is very, very heavily skewed.
A very strong right skew. The mean is much greater than the median for twenty three versus six.
Morreau, most this means most movies are going to have far fewer ratings in the mean and it's hard to
like the histogram shows us that it's skewed and shows us this huge spike at the small values.
But it's hard to really see what's happening with the distribution here.
So an alternate way that we can plot the distribution is.
So here's the word histogram. It just means the tabulation of how frequent each value is.
So we can compute the frequency of each value.
And the panda's method value counts. Does that. And so what we can what it computes.
It's a serious. Where the index is the values of the original series. And the value is the number of times that value appeared.
And so if we do that, we can then make a scatterplot and a scatterplot is where we plot some value on the X versus some value on the Y.
And the index, the index is an array. So our x axis and the scatterplot is the index, which is the actual values themselves.
And the Y index is the value of the earth in the array, which is how many times that value appeared in the original array.
And we're then we're going to do something. We're going to rescale it using what we call a log scale.
So you'll notice the Y, the X and the Y axes tend to the zero, tend to the one, tend to the to tend to the three.
Rather than being evenly spaced, they're evenly spaced.
The logarithms are evenly spaced and effectively since we're using ten base ten logarithms here.
What this does is it shows us, rather than the values themselves, that shows us the order of magnitude of each of the values.
And so. We can see one tend to the zero is the mode.
It's the most frequent one, that's the top point. And also we can see that the first part of the the first part of it is a lot, almost a line.
And when we have a line, we have a plot like this where the x axis is the number of ratings,
the y axis excuse me, the X axis is our value in the Y axis is how frequent that value is.
In this case, how many movies have that many ratings? And it's on a logarithmic.
It's on a log log scale. We when we see a line on a log log scale in this chart that indicates that what we're looking at is
a what's called a power law distribution or something that's close to a power law distribution.
And this is a common distribution that arises when we're talking about the popularity of various results of human activity.
It shows up in how frequently different words are used. It shows up in a lot of different human activity contexts.
If you look at, say, a social network. And you look at the popularity of different accounts.
You have accounts like Lady Gaga and beyond, say, have very, very popular Twitter accounts.
I have a moderately popular but much less popular Twitter account.
And a lot of people are down around 100 or 200 followers.
It's very common for the debt, for distributions of that kind of activity to fall to look like this.
And this kind of a chart where we have the scatterplot of X and Y axes is a good way
to see it and a good way to get a handle on what the state is actually looking like.
And we have this strong power law skew. So one of the artifacts of this I'm replanting our mean ratings here, except with more beans,
50 beans, instead of the default 10, we can we see the same basic shape.
We also see that a few values are much, much more common. Those values are one, two, three, four, five, two point five, three point five.
And the reason this is so these are exact rating values. Three point five is an exact.
You can rate it will be three point five. You can't rate a movie. Three point seven eight.
And so what the reason is. Look at how many movies have one rating.
Or two ratings. And if a movie only has one rating, it's mean rating is going to be the rating.
And so we're going to get a lot of movies since the most since this one rating is by far the most common popularity level of a movie.
We're gonna have a lot of movies. Where they're mean is exactly one of the possible rating values like three.
And so we see these spikes here in the distribution when we look at it in a more fine grained way,
just because there are so many movies that don't have very many ratings.
So we've seen numerical distributions, whether they're continuous, whether they're integer or other kinds of account data.
We've seen continuous distributions for a categorical distribution or go to as what's called a bar chart.
And so I'm again using value counts here to count the number of penguins.
So from the earlier video, the penguin dataset count the number of penguins of each species.
And then I'm plotting a bar chart that's showing us the the number of penguins that have each each species.
And we can see that the Adelie penguin is the most common here.
But the bar chart is going to be a really simple way to to view the distribution of a categorical variable.
Seabourne, which is an additional library we're going to see later, provides really convenient ways to do this.
But here I'm showing you the map, the raw matplotlib code, so that you can see how does the chart actually get generated?
It gets generated by counting, doing the value count, counting how many times each species appears.
And then we plot a bar chart whose x axis is the species and y axis is the number of times that species appears in the data set.