In this video, I'm going to introduce this week's topic of probability and inference.
So we're learning outcomes. This we could understand probability notation to be able to express formulas using probability.
Understand the difference to an estimation and testing and to be able to compute
confidence intervals and other estimates of precision and significance of an effect.
So to review just a little bit, we've talked about the concept of a statistic, a measurement that we take from a collection of data,
for example, and the Penguins dataset, which we're going to be using a lot this week.
The Gentoo penguins have an average weight of five thousand seventy grams of mean weight.
So but we have the question of we're trying to see how averaged how heavy on average are adult Gentoo penguins?
One of the things we want to know is how precise is this estimate of five thousand seventy six?
Is this likely to be close to the the actual average way far off?
How can we measure how precise this estimate is? We can also start to look at comparisons.
The Gentoo penguins in our data have longer flippers than the chinstrap penguins.
But does this mean Gentoo penguins have longer flippers than chinstrap penguins usually?
Or do we randomly get some long flipper Gentoo penguins and some short flipper.
Chinstrap penguins? And our data doesn't actually tell us anything about the relative flipper length of chinstrap and Gentoo penguins.
So what we're going to be developed, one of the things we're going to be developing this week is some tools to be able
to start to answer some of these kinds of questions and go from this statistic,
we call it. We have some data.
We compute a statistic over it to being able to say things about the underlying constructs from which the data are collected in this case.
The body size characteristics of different species of penguin.
So inference is learning about data to be able to go from the data that we have and learn things about
its structure to learn the values of different parameters that describe its underlying existence.
And so there's a couple of thing.
There's a variety of things you can do it this, too, things are going to be doing is estimating the value of a parameter.
So if there's an underlying parameter, which is the average length of a Gentoo penguin slipper,
can we estimate the value of that parameter by observing penguins in the wild?
And then the testing, the data support for a hypothesis, maybe the hypothesis that.
Gentoo penguins have longer flippers than chinstrap penguins. To define a term, though, an estimate is an estimated value of some underlying quantity.
Often we talk about a point estimate. So if we take our penguins and we compute the mean of our penguins flipper lengths.
That gives us a point estimate for the mean flipper length.
But often we'll have a confidence interval or something similar that describes how precise and how confident we are in this estimate.
And estimates [INAUDIBLE] is a procedure which is the metric and the mechanism that we're gonna use for applying that metric,
for computing an estimate and an s demand is a thing we're trying to estimate.
So an estimate. So we have an estimate. And that's the estimate of an S demand.
And if we're using a statistic from a sample to estimate a parameter.
So we're where we have our penguins and we compute the mean mass of our Gentoo penguins.
And we say, well, we're gonna use that to estimate. The typical mass of a Gentoo penguin.
Then with the typical mass as a parameter and the parameter or the statistic in this case is the estimate and the parameter is the estimate.
The value of this statistic is the estimate, the process of computing.
The statistic itself as an object like meet the mean of five point of five thousand seventy six is the estimate.
The mean as a concept is the estimate here. And the parameter in this case is the estimate and.
So, in effect, size is the size of the difference between two groups or treatments.
A lot of the things that a lot of the basic principles of statistical tests and statistical analysis come from the idea of controlled experiments.
So if in a controlled experiment, if if we had a bunch of penguins, I'm not going to try to draw penguins.
But I'll say penguins. Still a bunch of penguins.
And we want to see if penguins who eat one kind of fish have better growth.
Maybe we have baby penguins, baby penguins who have won access to one kind of food.
Have better growth than access to another. So we'll take our penguins randomly split them into two groups.
We'll have food. One. We'll have food to.
And then we will measure growth. And then we want to compare.
The growth of these two of penguins that are given the two different kinds of food.
There's much more sophisticated experimental designs. But the effect size is how much more or less the food one penguins grew.
And the food to penguins because we want to see it.
We can see, OK. Did they grow more? But the effect size as well. How big is that growth?
And. Even when we're not actually performing a controlled experiment like this,
a randomized controlled trial, we're using the statistical tools and other contexts.
This is the this is the underlying theoretical construct in which they're easiest to understand.
And we're going to understand a lot of them in other contexts in terms of.
This kind of a treatment setup, maybe we just have two groups like this.
This penguin is a June Gentoo and this penguin is a chinstrap.
We can't assign those conditions. We can't take a bunch of penguins and say, OK, this half, we're going to make them Gentoo.
In this half, we're going to make them chinstrap. We're gonna use the same math to compare, say, the flipper size of the chinstrap and the Gentoo.
But this is the kind of experimental construct in which it's which a lot of these kinds of all of these statistical techniques arise.
So a little bit about my perspective. So, I mean, we all come to these topics with our prospect, with our own perspectives.
I'm going to provide access. I'm going to provide links to know a couple of articles about my that have informed my perspective.
These are not required reading. And you're not going to be tested on those articles. But one is that there are few bright line rules.
So it's not as simple as we computer test p less than two point zero five.
Great. We know he found an effect instead. Multiple pieces of evidence.
The statistical significance from a test in one experiment. The confidence interval, the precision of the estimate in another context.
Together increase our confidence in the.
In what we're understanding from the data. No one experiment or analysis is the end of the story.
I'm going to be teaching you how to do all of the classical statistical well, not all.
I'm going to be teaching you how to do some of the classical statistical techniques,
like how to do a test and compute its p value, how to compute P values in other ways.
But there is not.
These individual pieces on their own are evidence that we used to paint a bigger picture and gain car, increasing confidence in our results.
Second is that probability is meaningful, even without a specific random process to discuss.
So some take the approach that we can only.
That the problem, the mathematics of probability, only apply when we're talking about actual random processes and the outcomes of random processes.
I do not take that approach. I take an approach in which probability can also quantify degrees of belief.
And so we can talk about the probability. We can talk about probabilities of actual parameters, not just the values that arise from them.
But I'll probably make some more sense later. Also effect size.
It estimates in the seat the. Precision of our estimates are often more important and more useful than hypothesis tests.
We're gonna do hypothesis tests, but in many cases.
The questions we ask are better answered by estimates, by estimates.
These are not universally held perspectives and I'm going to be teaching you tools.
Regardless of my perspective, but I just wanted to be upfront with some of the perspective that I bring to the
table and how I think about this material and it's informed how I present it.
And the choice of the which material I've chosen to present to you.
So to wrap up,
we're going to go move beyond just computing and comparing statistics to actually be able to start reasoning about the magnitude of the differences.
We see the significance of those differences if they are for lack of a better term,
real or if just they're just artifacts of the data and the data collection process.
The foundations of this are going to be probability theory, which I'm going to get into in the next video.