Also in this video, I went to talk with you about the basic principles of probability to lay a foundation for some
of the reasoning we're going to need to do this week and throughout the rest of the semester.
So we're learning outcomes for this video are for you to know the fundamentals, set operations.
We're going to use sets to discuss logical events that become the basis of probability
and to know the fundamental public concepts of probability theory for single events.
So to introduce a set, a set is an unordered collection of distinct elements.
There's no duplicates in it. So if A were to somehow be twice in a collection, it's not a set.
And also the elements have no intrinsic order. We can impose an order for Elst from elsewhere.
But if we have a set, there's no intrinsic order to the elements in it by default.
We then in a few relationships around sets, if we can say that an element A is a member of a set.
We can say that one set is a subset of or another. We can also compute the size or the cardinality of a set.
Now, sets can be infinite. That is, they can contain infinitely many elements.
There are also multiple types or sizes of infinity.
The smallest infinity is what we call countable infinity.
And the countable infinity is the cardinality of the set of natural numbers.
So zero one or one, two, three, four or five on forever.
There are accountably, many such numbers. That's the smallest infinity.
There are larger infinities. The details of that aren't going to be superimportant. They're going to come up once or twice.
But this is not an advanced. We're not going to dove deep. But I.
I might need the word accountably occasionally. We then have several operations onsets.
So A Union B is the number is the set of items.
That's an either A or B or both. It can be a both. Can be an either of them.
The intersection is the items that are in both of the sets. And then we have the set difference.
The items that are in A but not in B Union, an intersection are both symmetrical.
You can swap the the sets around. Difference is not symmetrical.
And then we have the complement.
If A is a subset of some larger set, some universe than the set of all items, not in a universe minus A is a complement.
Now, with these sets, we can then start to talk about what we call events.
So probability is the probability theory.
We talk about the probability of events. And so we have a set of elementary events and these are the distinct individual outcomes.
For example, if we flip a coin, are elementary events are heads and tails.
If we roll a six sided die or elementary events are one, two, three, four, five, six.
But then an event is a set that is a subset of our set of elementary events and the elementary events themselves.
We don't treat those as events. We make Singleton sets. So we just have the set that just contains H.
And that's going to be the coin is heads. But this way we can talk about events that are combinations of others,
such as E itself, the set of all the elementary events that mean something happened.
It doesn't matter what happened, just something happened.
And the also we can talk about, for example, two four six is the event if we're have our dice, two four six,
the SEC containing those three dicer die rolls is the event road even number because the hole at the elementary events.
So the individual rolls. One, two, three, four, five, six. There are three of them that are even two, four and six.
And so we can say the set of those three is the event rolled even number.
So we think about events. We're going to talk about events in terms of these sets.
And you set notation to talk about the combinations of events.
This is going to build up the basis of our probability theory. So then set operations described logical events.
So A, Intersect B means both A and B happened at the same time.
We have a A as a set of elementary events where some property is true,
say even B is a set where some other property is true, say divisible by three, A Intersect.
B is the set or both properties are true. This set may be empty.
But in this case, even in divisible by three is gonna be a six.
A Union B is either a C, so intersection is equivalent to logical and a union B is either A or B happened or both.
If it's possible for them to both have it at the same time, it might be that both happen, but at least one of them happened.
This is logical. Or we can also we also have A happened, but not B, so if A is even and B is divisible by three A but not B would be three.
Excuse me, A, but not B would be two and four because two and four of the even numbers that are not divisible by three.
As I said, these are equivalent to the logical operators, so A and B, A or B and then A and not B.
So we have these these individual outcomes, the elementary events.
We have the events themselves that are subsets of it. We then decide this D.
Define a set F. That is going to be the set of all possible events.
These are subsets of E! So this is a set of stats. And this set has to has an important property.
It's closed under. So first E is in it. So E is is an F.
And it is closed under complement and countable unions. So if.
If set A is in this field F. Then its complement is as well.
So E minus A is in it. The way we think of that, if a as say, even if even as an event, while odd, is an event to.
Also, if we have. Solemn events, then their union is also an event.
So if and also if if it is infinite, then this is count what accountable union?
Any count? Any any collection of counterplay many events. Their union is an event.
The details of that ring will save for a probability theory course.
But to be complete, there it is. We call this this field f a sigma field or a sigma algebra.
But. But F, is this the setup?
This collection of events? So we the in The Incredibles, you have the guy, the father, he comes home and the kids waiting there and.
What are you waiting for? I know something amazing, I guess. Well, something amazing.
It is an event that set off all elementary events that are amazing for whatever amazing means.
But then that also means that something not amazing, maybe something boring is also an event.
So you get this compliment thing. Like if. If, if. The set of all monetary events with some property say amazing is an event.
Well, the set of all of them that don't have that property also is.
So if we have our six sided die, we have the elementary events of the three or the six different values.
All of the singletons are events. They're all in our field and also all subsets of e wind up being events.
This we call this the powers. The power set is the set of all subsets. So there's any subset of E is an event.
And if you have it, so long as our set of elementary events is discrete and finite, all of the subsets are going to be events.
So let's I want to show you quick a theorem that we can prove already with the values that we have so far.
So if we have two events, a one and a two. The axioms told us it's usually the definition of a sigma field.
Told us that their union is an event,
but also their intersection is an event because the intersection can be turned into a compliment of a union of compliments by the Morgens laws.
If you've taken the logic class, you might remember those.
The compliments are in the hour in the field by club because the field has all the compliments in it.
The union of Compliments, therefore, is also in the field since it's in the field, its complement.
The intersection is in the field. So from the axioms we have, we can prove that the intersection is is an event.
So with these fields, we can now define probability and a probability is a measure of we call it actually a measure.
So it's a probability measure. But it's a measure of how likely the different events are.
So a probability distribution. It's a function over this field F and it obeys a few rules.
The probability of E the set of all elementary events is one. Basically, if we got something happening.
Well, the probability of something happening again, observe something happening is one.
Also, probabilities are not negative. All probabilities are at least zero.
And then if we have a disjoint sets or disjoint events.
So two events are disjoint. If they're mutually exclusive, they can't both happen at the same time.
Their intersection is empty. If we have to decide if we have disjoint events, then the probability of their union.
So if A and B are disjoint, the probability of A or B happening is the probability of A plus.
The probability of B. So for disjoint events, events, that cannot happen.
At the same time, we sum up their individual property probabilities to get the probability of any of them happening.
So if we're going to apply this to our DI, the problem, if we have all our singletons sets set containing just the value one,
two, three, four, five, six, the probability of each of these is one sixth.
The Dyas is fair. All values are equally likely. So the probability of even we're going to stay.
Even the set of even dice is one half because three of the six equally likely values one, two, three, four, five, six are even.
So we have when all the values are equally likely, we can count up to par.
The number of possibilities where our action, where our property happens, divided by the total number of possibilities.
And that gives us the probability. If they're not all equally likely, then things quickly get more subtle.
One consequence of this, another theorem that we can prove is that probabilities are not greater than one.
So. And I'm going to let you study the proof here in the slides, Off-line.
But we can prove from those axioms that probabilities are not greater than one.
And so this gives us a few different facts about probability. Probabilities are in the range zero to one.
If we have the union of two probability of two events there,
the probability of the union is the sum of the individual probabilities, minus the probability of A and B.
I'm going to let you think about why this is true. And we can talk about it in the discussion.
This also gives us that the probability of. A or B?
Is less than or equal to the probability of a plus the probability of B.
You can see that because the probabilities are at least zero, then P of A plus P, a,
B plus P of A or B or minus P of A and B is going to be no more than P of A plus people P plus P of beef.
The probability of a compliment is one minus the probability of the original thing.
We can compute the probability of of a difference. And we can also have an inequality relationship for subsets of fey as a subset of B.
It's probability is no greater than the probability of B. So what does probability mean so far, I've given you these rules.
It's just a function from sets of values. It turns out this is a surprisingly deep philosophical question,
but the depth of the philosophical question doesn't have to stop us from using it basically in two broad views,
which for our purposes are not going to conflict that much are that it's the expected or long run outcome of a random process.
And so. Probability of a Diab being one six means if we go, we roll six, the dice six hundred times.
We expect about a hundred of those to be one. It also can describe a degree of belief or expectation.
So that then that is a more subjective view on it that connects to the probability is is
describing what I know about what's going to happen when I roll the dice to wrap up,
though, we can use we can use sets to describe events or outcomes in their logical combinations.
We can then use probability to quantify the likelihood of different events and probabilities, follow a number of rules with rich emergent properties.
We're going to see more notions of probability and things we can do with it in the subsequent videos.