So, again, in this video, I want to introduce joint conditional and marginal probability.
The previous video we talked about probability in general, particularly the probability of one event at a time.
We're going to start talking about probabilities of that.
Would that involve more than one event?
So are learning outcomes understand the definitions and of the relationship between joint conditional marginal probability?
We're going to introduce Bayes Theorem. I want you to be able to apply it to invert the probability.
And also then we're going to introduce the concept of what it means for two events to be independent.
So to start out, joint probability is the probability of both A and B occurring simultaneously.
And we write it with A and B in columns. And so and it's the same as the and.
So remember, from the previous video, the set Intersect Operator means.
And so we just write P of A Khabab B, that's the joint probability of A and B occurring at the same time.
Sometimes this is written with a semicolon instead of a comma.
That's mean. The same thing. And sometimes you use both because your your events, they fall naturally into different groups.
And so you use commas to separate individual events and use a semicolon to separate the groups.
Not going to see it super often, but if you see a semicolon, that means the same thing as a comma.
It's a joint probability, but it.
It's just used to provide some clarity and grouping.
So, for example, if I roll, if I roll to die, two dice and the problem, the probability that the first one is four and the second one is five.
That's a joint probability. I could roll.
I could just compute the probability of the first one, and that's doesn't it. Second, I have no impact on it, but this joint probability is due.
One is for. And if two is five. Probability of that is one thirty sixth.
This is not the same as rolling a four and a five. Because there is an order here.
If I if the first dice diez five in the second Dice's four dayas for this event didn't happen because we are talking about this order.
If we want a four and a five, I'm going to let you think about what the probability of that would be.
So we can start to think about two dimensional spaces. Probability spaces.
In the last video we saw one dimensional probability where we can think about the role of a single die.
So I rolled a four. We can also think about drawing a single card from a shuffled deck.
Where I can draw an ace. Now, a key difference here, if I want to start thinking about two, I can roll two dice.
I get a one and a five. And they have nothing to do with each other.
Or I can roll one die and I get a five, I can roll it again and I get another five.
But if I draw another card from my deck. I can't draw another ace.
So for the dice, the each. Each one had the same probability, the probability of rolling a one and one on day one.
And the five. On day two is one out of 36. But if I have the probability of drawing.
A jack of hearts on my next draw is different because I've already drawn an ace of spades.
It's going to be one over 50 two. Excuse me, one over fifty one instead of one over fifty three.
drawCard knitted native diamonds. Further, the probability of drawing a diamond now is different from the probability of drawing a club.
Because I've drawn one diamond and I haven't drawn any clubs. So if I want to say the probability of clubs, there's still 13 left in the deck.
But there's only 12 diamonds left. So. The the the cards they change.
Well, since I'm not putting the cards back between draws, the cards change as much as I progressed through.
And there's a relationship between one sample and another. So the conditional probability P of be given a.
That's how we read. That is the probability that B happened. Given that we know A happen.
So when our dice five roll one die for.
That tells you absolutely nothing about what the second die is going to be. It can be a two.
It can be whatever. But if I shuffle my cards. And I draw a card, and that's eight of hearts.
That changes what the next probability is the probability of of a heart, the first time was 13, over 52.
But the probability of a heart the second time is twelve over fifty one because a heart is gone and a card is gone.
The probability of a spade the next time is thirteen over fifty one because I have a heart.
I haven't taken any spades but I have taken a card so close in 13. Over 52 to 13.
Over fifty one. Next card it turns out, is actually a heart.
But we have knowing the first card tells us something about what the next card is going to be.
And we call this a conditional probability. We can decompose joint probabilities into conditional probabilities.
So the probability of A and B is the probability of A given B.
Times the probability of B. And likewise, we can it also works the other way around.
It's been given eight times the probability of a. We can use this to breakdown a joint probability into a conditional.
We sometimes call this a factor, joint probability, but it starts to establish relationships.
The probability of drawing an eight of hearts, followed by a three of hearts is the same as that is the probability of drawing an eight of hearts,
followed by the times, the probability of drawing a three of hearts.
Given that, I have already drawn an eight of hearts.
We can also talk about the marginal probabilities of the marginal probability is the probability of a single event.
And if we know the joint distribution, we can compute the probability by doing what's called marginalizing the joint distribution.
So if we we can think of a card probabilities also as a joint probability.
So the three of hearts is the joint probability of a three and of a heart.
And so we can say, well, the probability of a three.
We can compute that with the sum over our suits of the probability of us three.
And that of or six. And that suit. And this computes this will be called this marginal probability.
The reason it's called a marginal probability is because if we draw out a table of the joint distribution.
So in the rose, we have the first the first value or event set of the set of possible events in the first case,
the set of possible events in the second case.
And this this hat, this requires us to have events where we have a set, I say a set of mutually exclusive events that span each.
So we need to be able to have events that cover everything. And they need to be mutually exclusive.
In order for this sum to work. But the second to die will be one of these six value.
Will be one of these six values. So. We can we have the values of each individual pair.
So the value of one being a six and two being a five is one over thirty six.
And then the margin. So if we sum this row.
We get one over six, which is the probability of the first die being a two.
And that's why it's called the marginal probabilities. It's what happens if we if we compute the margin of this table of the joint probabilities.
And I want to get to independents. I've talked about how the DICER Independent ruling one tells us nothing about the second.
So formally, two events are independent. If no one tells you nothing about another, the other.
So the probability of A given B, so the probability of rolling a set of five on my second day,
given that I wrote a two in the first, is the same thing as just rolling a five.
And so B tells us knowing B happened tells us nothing about A equivalently goes the other way probability knowing A happened tells us nothing about B.
And if two events are independent, then that are joint probability is the product of their marginal probabilities.
I can take A if A and B are independent, then the probability of A and B is the probability of A times the probability of B.
I'm going to let you as an exercise to get more familiarity with these with these distributions.
Prove that they are or with these definitions is to prove that these two definitions are equivalent.
So now then finally, I want to introduce something called Bayes Theorem.
So conditional probabilities have a direction. The probability of being given A and A given B are not the same thing.
But. We can they are related.
So. The probability of a penguin having a flipper length of 217 millimeters,
given that it's a Gentoo penguin, is not the same thing as the probability of that.
It is a Gentoo penguin. Given that it has a flipper length of 270 millimeters.
But if we know the probability of flipper length,
given that it's a Gentoo and we know the probability that it's the marginal probability that it's a Gentoo and that it has that flipper length,
then we can compute the probability that it's a Gentoo. Given the flipper length.
So if a. Gentoo. B.
Flip. Of, I'll say approximately to 17 millimeters.
We can read if we know one, we can add the marginals, we can reverse it and get the other.
This becomes very useful for a lot of kinds of probabilistic inference.
So to wrap up. Joint probability is the simultaneous is the probability of multiple events happening simultaneously.
These can be multiple overlapping descriptions of the same thing.
For example, the probability that my card is a three and the probability that it's a heart.
They can also be probabilities that relates to individual dimensions of a multidimensional space,
like the probability for different die or the probability of of different cards in a sequence.
Conditional probability describes the probability of an event condition and that other information we may have and these things,
these probabilistic building blocks. There's a building blocks for more reasoning.
We're going to use them quite a bit as we start to reason and as we start to describe other things throughout the cement's.