In this video, I'm going to introduce continuous probability.
So far, we've been talking about probability over discrete variables, dice rolls, et cetera,
but we're going to now talk about continuous probability and introduce the concept of a random variable.
Learning outcomes are for you to be able to compute an expected value and to understand why continuous events have
probability densities and the relationship between these densities and distribution functions and actual probabilities.
So if X is the value of a six sided Deyrolle, so we roll it, I has six sides,
X is the value one through six of that result, we call X a random variable.
It's a variable that has a random numeric value. Technically of random variable is actually a function from elementary events to real values,
but for our purposes that nuance is not generally going to be very important.
The expected value of the variable is the sum.
Of the different values it can take of the value.
Times the probability of that value. So it's one times the probability of a one and you add two times the probability of a two.
This is equivalent to the mean over many roles. If we roll the dice a thousand times, what would it mean?
Approximately B and also we can think of it in a gambling kind of a gambling or betting setting of the expected return from a roll,
the expectation in the meet. So the expectation is the mean over many points, but it's also in the mean of the random variable.
The random variable has a mean, even if we don't have any observations for it.
And the expected value is that mean. One way to see this,
if we've got a sequence of data points in our process is pick one of them uniformly at random probability one over N and we have it's value,
then we can compute. The expected value is the probability value times.
There is the sum value times, the probability of that. But this probability is one over N.
So when we pull that outside we get one over ten times the sum, which is exactly the sample mean.
That's the formula for the mean. So we can see the expectation and the mean are equivalent concepts here.
But that's a discrete variable, one through six. Rove is excited.
I don't happen to have a continuously value to die, but what's the probability that so we randomly pick agenda Penguin,
what's the probability that it's flipper length is two hundred seventeen. Mm.
It's a continuous variable, so two hundred and seventeen millimeters, there's very values on both sides of it.
What if it's 217 17? But we find a penguin and it's flipper length is to seventeen point one millimeters.
It's 217 plus 10 to the negative 10 mm, I don't have a ruler that precise, but the value these values are continuous values.
There's a value between 217 and 217, plus ten, the minus 10.
So the probability of any individual value of a continue of a truly continuously
valued random variable is zero because it's it's it's effectively never.
Going to be exactly this value might be pretty close, but it's but the probability of it being exactly that value is effectively zero.
So we need a different way to approach probability for continuous variables.
And the way we do this is that we assign probabilities not to individual values of the variable, but to intervals or ranges.
And so are elementary. Events are still real numbers. The penguin that we randomly picked has a flipper length.
Those are the elementary events. But we don't have the singletons. The singletons are not in our set of actual events we care about.
The events we care about are intervals, the sets of the set of intervals and their complements and their countable unions.
There's a lot of different sets in here. Any real value is in.
Actually, infinitely many of any real value we can pick is actually an infinitely many different events
because the intervals are all events and it contains infinitesimally small intervals.
And no matter how small an interval you pick, there's one smaller in there,
but it does not contain the individual singleton values and we assign probability to these intervals.
We do that through a thing called a distribution function.
And so the distribution function F is the probability that the random variable takes on a value
less than or so F of X is the probability that the random variable takes on a value less than X.
And so at X equals zero, so this and this is sometimes called accumulative distribution function or a CDF C D,
I'm going to write that down for you, CDF.
Cumulative distribution function, so what X equals zero, it takes on the value, the probability that the random variable,
it has a value less than X, which for the first three curves, these are the CDs for different parameters of what's called the normal distribution.
It's the probability that it's less than that. We go up to one. X equals one, and the probability that it's less that is higher,
the cumulative distribution function is monotonic, non decreasing, and it has a maximum value.
The limit as X goes to infinity is one.
So the probability is excuse to infinity. The probability that's less than X is one.
And as X goes to negative infinity, the probability is zero.
But this this is the basis for establishing the probability of continuous values is we say,
well, what's the probability that it's less than some value?
And then if we have an interval, so we want to say X, the probability that X one is less than X,
which is less than X to what we can do is we can subtract these two probabilities.
So what we say is so. The what we have here is the events X is less than X two, and we have the event not.
Or X is less than X one compliment, X is not less than one, so it's greater than X one.
And we take the union of those two events excuse me, the intersection of those two events.
What's the probability that they both happen and we get that we need F of X to minus F of X one.
So we call the probability on an overall probability mass how much probability the mass is on this interval.
Also, when we have a discrete event, it's probability is also called a probability mass.
So if you have discrete variable, then the function of what the probability is of different values is called a probability mass function.
How much probability is on this discrete value? But we we can't have mass on discussing on individual discrete values of a continuous variable.
We can have probability mass on an interval and we can have a probability density on an individual value.
So a distribution is often defined.
So I've got us to the distributions of the probability of a of a variable having a particular value through the distribution function.
But the distribution function is often actually defined as the integral of a density
function in the density function is therefore the derivative of the distribution function.
We have a density functions that the distribution function is the integral from negative infinity to X of the density,
and that gives us the probability that it's less than or equal to X.
And the this is the graph of the density function and these are the densities for the same distribution functions you just saw.
So they go back down. They're not monotonic and they're showing how much density is at different values.
So X the purple one has the most density at X, the mean of the the mean of these three.
Is all the same, the expected values, the same, the distribution function at zero point five is the same, but the densities are different,
which means the purple one is more strongly concentrated around zero than the red one or the orange one.
Densities can exceed unlike probability, unlike probabilities,
a density can actually exceed one, they're not going to be negative, but they can exceed one.
You can have density. I've seen densities of 10 and some of my analyzes because the density is not a probability.
Instead, the density is the limit. As we see if we pick a point, the density at that point is the limit.
Of the so we we have a point here, so we've got our curve.
We've got a point, we have a window around it. Of wealth to Epsilon.
And it is the limit as that window gets smaller and smaller of the probability mass in that window divided by the width of the window,
the density because the density is the mass, divided by how much length the mass is spread over.
If you're going to compute the density of the weight of an object, you'd be the the weight over the amount of area.
We're dealing with one dimension here. So the limit as this window gets smaller and smaller of.
The mass divided by the width and because we're dividing by that width, the densities can exceed one.
You might remember this definition of that as the definition of the derivative from calculus that and that that's the relationship here.
The density is the derivative of the distribution function. The distribution function is the integral of the density.
We can also compute continuous expectation and continuous expectation is an integral.
So as the as the the expectation of a discrete variable was the sum of the values, timeliness,
the probabilities, the continuous expectation is just the integral of the values times their probabilities.
When we go from the script, from continuous, we have to go from segments to integrals. But the concept is the same.
It's still the mean. So to wrap up the probability of any individual value of a continuous variable is effectively zero.
It is zero. But so instead we use probability density, distribution functions and we assign probability mass,
not individual points of a continuous variable, but to intervals of it.
And the expectation also then that the expected value is the mean of a random variable.
Couple of things I haven't shown you.
We can also talk about conditional expectation, which is the expectation of the random variable, given some other information.
We're going to be building on this as we go forward. I'm also going to be posting some notebooks that work through computationally.
How do we actually start to compute and how do we count frequencies of events to start to estimate probability from data that we have?