Hello, in this video, I want to talk about the concept of distribute, particularly named distributions, we introduced the fundamentals of probability.
We've gotten the continuous variables and random variables.
I want to talk about what it means when we talk about something, say, having the normal distribution.
And so our learning outcomes for this video were to understand the idea of a distribution,
to be able to identify parameters and statistics of a distribution.
The notebook and the linked reading have the linked material, has more information, more information on these distributions, many more distributions.
So I encourage you to spend some time exploring that particular distribution.
Families are one place where Wikipedia is a rather fantastic resource.
I've included a link to Wikipedia's list of probability distributions, which is organized by by distribution type.
And it each of the pages provides rather mathematically dense but useful detail on how the distribution is defined.
Some of its key properties and relationships to other distributions.
So but to get started, this idea of working me, focusing on distributions of numeric variables.
These can be both discrete and continuous. So discrete. We might have a distribution of accounts.
It can also be categorical so long as we encode them as a numbers.
So we may encode a a success or failure outcome as zero for failure and one for success.
Speaking of which, the banali distribution does exactly like it does exactly that.
If we have binary outcomes. Success and failure, which we code as one and zero respectively by convention.
And we have a parameter, the success probability. Then we have we can then also compute some statistics of this distribution.
Its mean, which is since the outcomes are just zero and one, it would be the fraction in the long run, run it infinitely many times.
What fraction would you expect to be successes? And then it'll also have a mode, which is the value that's going to occur more often.
For example, when Theta is point three, the mode is failure.
There are a few things we want to do to characterize the distribution. So we have its parameters.
So in the Bernoulli distribution, the parameter was the success probability. There are other parameters as well,
and some of the parameters come in particular types such as location and location
is a parameter that controls where on the x axis the distribution is located.
Sometimes it is the mean, but not always. The key thing is that the location parameter controls where on the x axis.
So it slides it back and forth in the x axis, some distribution. It's also going to change the shape somewhat as it slides.
But the location parameter controls where on the x axis it is the scale parameter controls,
how far, how wide it is, how far out it spreads out its density.
Some distributions called location scale distributions are controlled by location and scale parameters.
And the shape of the distribution doesn't change it at all, doesn't changes all at all as you move it around,
the location just shifts the same curve back and forth on the x axis.
And the the scale just spreads it out or contracts it on the x axis.
And so if you if you do a simple way of plotting it, the curve is gonna be exactly the same.
The X axis is just going to be shifted and smushed or spread out underneath the curve.
And then a shape parameter controls the shape of the distribution.
So this distribution, which is a normal distribution, doesn't have a shape parameter,
but there's a skewed normal which adds a shape parameter to let you get shapes like this.
And in it, that shape parameter allows you to shift between the normal, the traditional normal and this skewed normal.
And so there's other types of parameters as well. But three common kinds of these location, scale and shape parameters,
locations where scale is how wide and then shape is what it's actually shaped like there.
We then to characterize the distribution,
we have a density or a mass function that use probability density or probability mass function that uses these parameters to assign probability,
mass or density to different values. We then have what's called the support, which is the range of values the distribution is defined over.
Not all distributions are defined over the same range.
And there's often we want to it's useful to think about the underlying random process.
Most distributions are described as the result of a particular random process.
It does not mean those processes are the only things they're useful for describing,
but it's mathematically the distribution arises from analyzing that particular process.
We then can compute some statistics of a distribution.
It's mean the expected value of a very of a random variable with that distribution is one of them.
It's also called the first moment of the distribution. Then we can compute the standard deviation or variance.
For some distributions, for example, normal, though,
it has location and scale parameters that are the mean and standard deviation, the variance is called the second central moment.
We can also compute other things, such as the median or the fiftieth percentile of the distribution in other and quintiles.
So the binomial distribution is we take that Bernoulli and we stretch.
We do it multiple times. The binomial distribution is it has the parameters and which is the number of trials.
The number of Bernoulli trials we're going to run. And Theta is the success probability of each individual trial.
The trials are assumed to be independent and the burn the binomial distribution describes the distribution of how many successes.
We'll see if we run that many trials with that success probability.
It's mass function is. The probability of success times the number of successes.
The probability of failure times the number of failures and then multiplied by end, choose why and choose why.
Is the number of possible ways to arrange why failures out of any successes so.
So that's a probability mass function I show here. Also, the DI a graph of it's you can see where how the mass is distributed for N equals 10.
And Theta equals zero point three.
So you can see three. That's the mode, and that's also the mean and the median.
Three. If we flip awaited coin, that comes up heads 30 percent of the time.
Ten times three will be the most common number of heads.
But there's quite a bit of spread. We're going to see a lot of twos and a lot of fours as well.
And we'll see some runs with zero heads. We're not going to it's.
There is going to be very, very few runs that wind up having 10 heads with a coin with that bias.
The normal or the Gaussian distribution that I just showed you has mean and look, has its scale parameter or excuse me,
its location parameter is the means at scale parameter is the standard deviation.
When the mean is zero and the standard deviation is one, we call this a standard normal.
And the stand I'm showing here, the standard normal with both the probability density function and the the distribution function, the CTF.
So you can see how those relate to each other of align them vertically.
The code to generate all of these plots is in their notebooks. You can see how I did them.
You will see we see here that the cumulative probability goes from zero to one.
Cumulative probability always does that. The density, the bell curve goes out to zero on both sides.
The density is concentrated in a particular window. And the.
And it's a density. So it goes up to whatever that the maximum density is.
If we if we contracted that, if if we decreased the scale, the density would increase, the maximum density would increase.
So to wrap up, random variables are often described where probability distributions, which are in turn governed by parameters.
There's quite a few different standard probability distributions.
I encourage you to spend some time with the notebook and the linked resources to learn more about different distributions.
And we're going to be introducing more as they come up for various things throughout the rest of the class.