This video I want to talk with you about sampling and the data generation process,
we've talked about probability and that's going to give us the foundations to be able
to start reasoning about the process of sampling and how we get the data that we have.
So our learning outcomes are to understand the relationship between a sample and a population we've mentioned.
I've mentioned that before, but we're going to get into it a little bit more on this video,
identify when we can make an inference about a population and when it's just something that we can say
about the data and determine whether the data is likely to be independent and identically distributed.
I'm going to introduce that concept today. So the inferential logic of statistics is based on sampling and samples.
A lot of many of our statistical techniques are designed based on analysis of
what happens if you apply them repeatedly with certain randomization structure.
That randomization structure comes in our sampling to select which data we're going to be analyzing.
We can sample from a couple of different things. We can sample from a distribution.
So we've introduced distributions. I can sample from a normal distribution and I'll get a bunch of values that will be normally distributed.
That's really useful for doing simulation studies and for probing how our statistical techniques work.
We can also sample from a population and if we want to understand something about a population,
we can sample from it with with a sampling strategy that's going to ensure that we have representative sample.
So if we think about the penguin data set we've been working with a little bit and we're going to see more this week.
If we have the population of penguins and they have some flipper length mew fouls, we've got our penguins, they have a flipper length.
And it's important. This is this is this is the population of penguins that exist.
And really, it's the population of hypothetical penguins that could exist.
But we have this population of penguins. We then take a sample of the penguins.
So we have it, but there's a bunch of Gentoo penguins out there or chinstrap penguins.
We take a sample of penguins and then we compute a statistic from the sample.
And there's one key thing we need to know about the sample is whether it is representative.
And by that, we mean that. Studying the sample is going to teach us about the population.
There's not parts of the population that are systematically excluded from the sample.
There's not parts that are disproportionately more likely to appear in a way that we can't control for, etc.
What we want is that the populace, looking at the sample,
gives us things that look gives us results that look like the population scaled down to our sample size.
Particularly for like, if we're going to infer the mean flipper length,
then we want the sample to have the same distribution of flipper lengths as the population.
If there was something that caused longer flipper penguins to be easier for us to pass in our sample, then it would not be representative.
With respect to studying flipper length, depending on our philosophy of statistics and of science,
we may consider that the penguins themselves are instantiations of a distribution governed by some ideal penguin.
In which case we're trying to understand the properties of Penguin Enis.
Platonic ideal penguin.
Not just the population of penguins that happen to exist on Earth, but for the purposes of the vast majority of what we're doing.
Whether or not the ideal penguin is a thing that's that exists and or is reasonable to talk about won't much matter.
But it sometimes might come up as a conceptual entity. So representative sampling mean a couple of things for a sample.
We need to be representative of the population, particularly with respect to the parameters of interest.
It doesn't necessarily have to be representative in every possible way, so long as it's representative for the things we're inferring.
But if it's not representative in some way, identifiable way, that usually should give us pause about the quality of our sample.
It also used to be large enough to allow us to properly and for the do rigorous inference of the parameters that we're interested in.
One crucial thing to note is that the size of the sample does not depend on the sample size or excuse me, on the population size.
Once we start seeing the tools for quantifying the precision of an estimate based on sampling theory.
The size of the population is not going to be a variable in the precision of our estimate.
This is a common. This is a common misunderstanding of sampling.
You'll see it comes up poor sometimes, particularly around political polling.
Raising the question of, well, how is a poor 15 hundred people represented to get accurate representation of of.
US with the opinion of the U.S. populace. But the accuracy, so long as they're sampling strategy, is good.
The accuracy and the precision of the estimate does not depend on the sample size so long as your sample is big.
So does not depend on the population size, so long as your sample is big enough.
So also, better data is often better than more data.
Historically, a lot of that has because it takes time to get data.
It takes time to run experiments. It's expensive. There's a lot of statistical inference.
It's concerned with how do we make efficient use of modestly sized samples.
This is one of the areas where. Data science diverges a little bit from classical statistics.
I don't want to say that they're different, though. What we. The tools of statistics are the building blocks for it.
And it's statistician's that really are leading the way in figuring out what we actually need to do here.
But we have such vast quantities of data. What how we have to handle it changes because we're no longer dealing with relatively small samples.
Uniform sampling is an easy if you can actually do a uniform sample.
It's a good way to do a representative sample for a lot of purposes. All population members are equally likely actually achieving.
This is not as easy as it sounds, but uniform sampling has a lot of nice properties.
The resulting statistical analysis is relatively straightforward as the analysis go.
But one one downside of uniform sampling, if you have a large population, is that your uniform?
There might be subgroups and there might be subgroups of interest that just never show up in your sample.
And so you need if you want to make sure that those subgroups are reflected,
especially if you're looking at at the subgroups, the preference within subgroups.
So if you read the details, say a say a Pew Research survey or poll.
You'll have they'll have their high order results and they'll break them down by a bunch of subgroups.
You have to make sure that your samples. The samples from each of the subgroups are representative in addition to the whole.
So additional strategies are stratified sampling, which can make sure that different groups are represented.
So you have you might sample a fixed number.
You might make sure that you sample and people from each state to make sure you can.
You have data and relatively comparable data on each state. You may over samples.
You may have your first order sample and then go get more samples from a smaller community to
make sure you have enough data to do robust inferences about their particular preferences.
And either these strategy areas you have to re sample or reweight.
You have to somehow correct. To be able to do inference from the whole sample.
But that certainly doable over sampling does not mean that.
The results, the conclusions from the overall sample are biased towards the over the over sampled groups opinion,
because you're going to correct for that when you do the top level, the top level analysis.
This is another thing I see.
I come up with with Ill-founded complaints on political polling is using the fact that a poll oversampled to discredit its top
level conclusions without investigating whether they corrected for the oversampling when they were computing those conclusions.
But if we go back to our penguins, we have three species of penguins. And then we have a set of penguins from each species.
And a key question we want to think about here is what is the population?
And then there's other questions we want to be able to think about.
Can we answer the questions to answer the questions about the distribution of penguin species?
And can we answer any questions about typical measurements within a species?
So if we think about our penguins, there's two different ways the data can come to us.
The sampling strategies we could have the universe of all possible penguins.
And then we sample some penguins and we see, OK, what species? One, what species to take their measurements.
And then we put it in our analysis.
The other one is we have penguins and the penguins have different species and we sample from each species of penguin.
And then we go and we take their measurements, information and smuggled into our analysis and the.
The second one is probably what was happening with this data, because they have a particular place,
they're going and collecting the penguins, they're collecting them by a particular species.
I mean, this this this island or this beach on the island has a particular penguin that's going gonna be more common.
They're getting a global uniform sample of penguins is difficult.
And so if we think about it in terms of having we have samples from each species,
we have a sample of chinstrap, a sample of Idalia and a sample of Gentoo penguins.
Then we can infer about the.
Within the species distribution site, how is the flipper length of a chinstrap distributed this upper length of a deli?
How do those compare? But assuming that our samples are representative of the species of penguin,
but what we probably can't do with this data is say chinstrap or more adult common than Adelie or vice versa,
depending on which one is more common in the data set. The.
By understanding the sampling strategy. And here to make rigorous conclusions, we need to go spend time with the paper documenting the data.
But by thinking about an understanding the sampling strategy, we can start to get out,
what can we actually use to try to infer about the data and what's just a statistic or excuse me?
What can we use to try to infer about the population and what's just a statistic of the data?
We have like we have data on this many of penguins of each species.
But that doesn't mean that's how many penguins there are of each species.
So we need to think about that, what we call the data generating process or the DGP.
And this has this is around how everything that goes into how the data came to us.
And oftentimes what we're trying to do is infer parameters of the data generating process.
And so if we think about the movie data, people and movies exist, we could think about the process by which they come into existence.
We have to scope our investigation so we can say we assume people in the movies exist.
People find movies and watch them somehow. Netflix recommends more movies.
People maybe watch them. This feeds back into two with the but understanding the data generating process and identifying.
Oh, Netflix is recommender. Is in the loop on Netflix's data.
Lets us understand. Well, actually, when someone recommend read when someone decides to watch a movie.
That choice is not entirely what we call exoticness from outside the system.
It's affected by the system because it's in response to recommendations,
because we start to think about what is the debt data generating process that gives us a bunch of data about what movies people watch.
Reasoning about the data's generating process allows us to understand our sample strengths and weaknesses and capabilities and to.
And to find opportunities to do our inference and check where it may have gone wrong.
So I now want to introduce briefly this concept of independent and identically distributed.
A lot of. A lot of. A lot of statistical techniques required data to be either the data itself or the data after
some processing or the errors in the data to be independently and identically distributed.
And what this means is that the values do not affect one another in any way, and they're all drawn from the same distribution.
Particularly, we don't have changes in the mean or the variance as the distribution, as we say, move through time.
If we sample uniformly at random from a large population,
it's we can generally treat it as I.D. Each at each sample is independent of each other as well,
unless there is some some mechanism that causes them particularly to be linked.
If we have a small population and we're sampling a large fraction of it, then they're not necessarily independent because if you sample one,
you're not going to sample that again unless you're sampling with replacement as opposed to if you have a very large population,
you sample your you're not reducing the pool very much at all.
One last thing I want to mention, I'm not going to get into the details of it as an illustration for the power of thinking about
sampling and what it can let us do in our inference is a problem known as the German tank problem.
And this problem arose in the Second World War when the allied military forces were trying to estimate axis production capacity.
And so you capture a tank. And you find a serial number on it, and it's serial number would say two zero eight nine.
You want to know how many tanks have been produced? You want to know how many tanks have been produced?
And so. It turns out if the serial numbers are being assigned sequentially, which they were.
And you have observations of a bunch of, say, tanks,
you can applying sampling theory and the statistics that come about reasoning about how we get samples.
You can infer how many tanks probably exist.
Effectively, what you're doing is you're inferring the max. Oftentimes we infer for the mean, you can infer from many different statistics.
They figured out how to infer from the max based on a number of observations.
And the max of those observations to figure out how many tanks were likely produced after the war,
comparing the statistical analysis to the actual production records recovered from Nazi factories.
The statistical estimates were far closer to the actual production records than traditional intelligence
estimates that were using spies and surveillance to try to figure out how many tanks were being produced.
But the reasoning about the sampling process and pushing through the math of sampling allows us to
then be able to make probabilistic statements that can infer some relatively remarkable things,
such as the number of tanks produced based on the serial numbers that we've seen so far.
There are then countermeasures for that, such as randomizing your serial number so they don't show up in order and you have a much larger pool
of serial numbers and then you can't just use serial numbers to infer how many have been built.
So to wrap up, our data comes to us by some process. And classically, we think about this in terms of sampling.
How did we pick these items to analyze and then what would happen if we did that sample multiple times?
A lot of the properties of our statistical techniques are defined in terms of
what would happen if we ran the sample and computed the statistic many times.
And the data generating process is the mechanism by which our data comes into existence.
And we may model it in some way in order to be able to try to do inference about the human or physical processes that our data reflect.