This video, we're going to start to getting to actually being able to augment our statistic with come
up with a measure of the confidence we have with regards to how it relates to the mean.
These are going to be extremely subtle to interpret correctly,
but they do get us towards being able to say things more robustly about the relationship of our estimate,
the statistic and the parameter that we're trying to estimate.
So our goals with for this lecture are for you to be able computer confidence interval for the mean,
using the standard error and correctly interpret a confidence interval. So let's return to our sample of the populations.
We've got our penguins and and we've got we're sampling our penguins and we're computing a statistic.
One question we can ask is, how does the statistic relate to the underlying parameter?
So this is important to be able to do inferences that can compute the mean flipper length of chinstrap penguins.
But how does that relate to the main flipper length of chinstrap penguins?
Well, the chinstrap penguins in the world world,
so classical frequenters statistics does this by thinking about what would happen if we repeated the experiment multiple times.
So let's say you want to measure penguins and I'm a penguin measuring robot.
And you tell me to go man, to go collect a measure that the flipper thinks and 50 penguins.
And you tell me to do that a hundred a hundred times each time taking a different random sample of penguins.
This allows us to the.
The mean flipper lengths I come back to you with are going to have a distribution.
So we have the flipper lengths, have a distribution. We go and we've you go have your your penguin measuring robot.
Go sample 50 penguins could measure the flipper lengths and give you the mean hundred times.
That also was going to have a distribution and we call this the sampling distribution of the statistic,
because it's what happens when we compute the sample, the statistic of our sample.
And we do it repeatedly.
And so this chart shows us the blue line, which you kind of can't see very well, because it's right up with the orange line is getting at the.
There you can see they're slightly different. The blue line is the true population.
So here are my samples are being drawn from a random number generator that I've configured.
So I know the population distribution. Precisely. We have the sample.
The sample is the orange histograms and there's an orange density estimate on top of them, so.
That's the sample itself. That's the distribution of values in my sample. And this is this is with 50 a sample size of 50, this green distribution.
That is the sampling distribution of the sample mean.
And so if I were to take one hundred of these orange samples or a thousand of these orange samples.
The green curve is the distribution, the means of those samples.
What have. So, yeah, as I said, we take a sample, we compute the experiment,
and we think about what the distribution is of the statistic from compute, from repeatedly doing this experiment.
So the sampling distribution of the sample mean. So we take a sample of size N and we compute the sample mean X bar.
This the sampling distribution is normal and it has a mean of the population mean.
And a standard deviation. Of the population, standard deviation divided by the square root of the sample size.
So. And also, for this to be true, X does not need to be normal.
And this is starting to get at what I mentioned in the previous video about the
precision and the accuracy of our estimate does not depend on the population size.
So. If the population has a standard deviation of one and we take sample sizes of size one hundred.
Then there's the means from those samples is going are going to be normally distributed with standard deviation.
One tenth, regardless of how big the population is.
The only variable to compute how far our our sample mean is likely to be the only things we need to compute.
How far our sample mean is likely to be from the true mean.
Are this this standard deviation of the population and the size of the sample?
We don't actually need the size of the population.
So but we don't have the population mean and the population standard deviation to be able to use that distribution directly.
But what we do compute is a confidence interval. And so while the sampling distribution lets us say things about the distribution
of the sampling mean and what happens if I compute a thousand of those means?
The confidence interval is also something that we understand in terms of what were to happen
wouldn't if we did it in infinitely many or sufficiently close to infinitely many times.
And so you compute a confidence dance interval with this statistic.
And this piece here asks over the square root of N is the standard error.
So. And our distribution here,
we have the standard deviation over the square root of N and that is that's really the error that what that's doing is it's bounding the error.
We're going to have and trying to estimate the mean or it's not bounding.
It's characterizing the error. We're going to how we expect to have when we're using the sample, mean to estimate the true mean.
So we call an estimate of that statistic using the sample standard deviation, we call this the standard error.
And the standard error is approximately the sample standard deviation of the sampling distribution,
one point nine six comes from the definition of it comes from the normal distribution in a standard normal.
Ninety five percent of the probability Nasse is between plus and minus one point nine six.
But if we computer confidence interval in this way. So we. So if we say X bar, the mean plus or minus one point nine, six times the standard error.
That gives us an interval upper and lower bounds. So for our chinstrap penguins, we have a mean of one in nine five point eight.
Two, we have a standard deviation sample size. And we can computer standard error so that we can say that that was a standard error.
And the confidence interval,
so we can say our chinstrap penguin confidence interval is one point nine five point eight two plus or minus one point six nine.
And what the confidence interval means is it's the result of a procedure that we can perform.
And remember our little penguin measuring robot?
Well, if we had the penguin measuring robot returned the confidence interval instead of the the mean itself.
And we have it go measure confident, we have it go measure penguins, sample penguins and measure them a thousand times.
Nine hundred and fifty of the confidence intervals that it gives us approximately.
This is all probabilistic, so it might be a little more, a little less,
but approximately ninety five percent of the confidence intervals that it gives us contain the true mean flipper length for a chinstrap penguin.
That's what the confidence interval means. And so the width of this interval is an estimate of our precision.
It's really important to understand a couple of things. It's really important to understand a couple of things.
One, the it is not we are not 95 percent confident the mean Lise's in the interval.
Then it is not that the mean lies within the interval with probability point nine five.
That would be another thing related thing called a baozi incredible interval.
It also isn't precisely a statement about X Bar itself. What the confidence interval means is.
It's an interval generated from a using a procedure that ninety five percent of the time will include the mean with the true mean within the interval.
So a brief aside, I mentioned the population standard deviation,
which we usually don't know because we don't have the population and the sample standard deviation,
and there's actually a slight difference in how we compute them in the samples that we're computing, the standard deviation from a sample.
We divide by N minus one instead of N.
And this is the key reason for this is that the samples to the standard sample standard deviation has what we call N minus one degrees of freedom.
Because we've already computed X bar. This is an intermediate statistic.
That we've already computed.
Given X bar and X one through N minus one, you can solve for X and only and minus one of the of the sample values are allowed to vary.
And still have the same X bar. And so because we have this is called degrees of freedom, because we have N minus one degrees of freedom.
We. We can.
We have to divide back and minus one. No, they think of it since X Bar is computed from the X's.
The Xs are not independent of X Bar in the population.
The the the the instances are independent of each other, given the mean.
But in this in the sample they aren't because we could given we can compute the last one.
If we had the mean and we have the first ten minus one. So we can start to compare values based on confidence intervals.
So I computed here the confidence intervals for the flipper lengths for our three types of penguins.
And there's no overlap in the confidence intervals. This is evidence that the flipper that the penguins have different flipper lengths.
If they had the same if they tended to have the same flipper length, then of the confidence interval would probably overlap.
We're gonna see later methods for directly comparing two means.
But we can start by using the confidence interval to see. OK.
Do they overlap? And the confidence interval also allows us to estimate if it's different.
If it if it's far away from a value. If we've.
If. The confidence interval, the low or high end of it, is pretty far from zero.
Then a reasonably far from zero, then zeroes. Probably not.
I mean. So but as I said, we have to be really, really careful about how we interpret confidence intervals.
We take us. The procedure is take a sample of size n compute the statistic infinitely many times.
Ninety five percent. In this case, the statistic is the upper and lower bounds of the confidence interval.
Ninety five percent of the time, the Trumaine will be in this interval.
Ninety five percent of the time this procedure will return an interval that contains the true mean.
We could also have other confidence interval, such as a ninety nine percent one.
But as I said, the confidence interval is not where we're 95 percent sure that parameter is.
We also have a couple of outstanding issues with the confidence interval.
So to wrap up, taking a sample and computing a statistic is a random process that results in a sampling distribution.
And this is the sampling distribution is the probability distribution from the process.
Take a sample and computer statistic. We can use this to try to start estimating the precision of our of our estimates.
So we have the X bar, which is Selke. This is my estimate for the main.
Mina, the penguins I saw were gonna use that as the estimate for the mean of penguins.
But we can use knowledge of the sampling process to develop techniques that let us not only estimate but estimate how far off our estimate is.