This video, we're going to talk about the bootstrap,
a technique for understanding properties of sampling distributions and we can't take a bunch of samples.
Our goals for this video are to be able to approximate the sampling distribution,
using the bootstrap and compute a bootstrapped confidence interval for a statistic.
So let's go back to our penguins. We've got a population of penguins. We sample of penguins.
The sampling that we compute a statistic over the sample. We repeat this a bunch of times.
And doing so gives us the sampling distribution of the statistic.
So the sampling distribution for the means really well understood, normal with particular parameters.
Estimating this depends on the accuracy of of the standard of the sample standard deviation, usually pretty good.
It's a parametric mach estimate. So it's estimating in terms of distribution with parameters.
Other statistics have other distributions. And we may not know cleanly what all of them are or they might be quite complex.
So or we may violate the assumptions of a statistical method.
So using the the the standard 95 percent confidence interval for the mean is not to going to get you too far off.
But what if you want to compute a confidence interval for a median or you want
to compute the confidence interval of a new statistic that you developed?
So you can do a lot of difficult probability, theoretic calculus.
But what you're trying to get at is what's gonna happen if we take many samples and compute the sampling distribution.
But if we do that, it's very expensive. Going and measuring 50 penguins and computing their mean flipper length a thousand times costs a lot of money.
So. We can cheat, kind of.
We can sample from our sample. And re sampling from the sample allows us to approximate the sampling distribution.
So if we have a sample, we can construct a new sample by sampling from the original with the key thing here is with replacement.
So just because we picked X to our new sample, X one is X two from the old sample, doesn't mean we can't reuse X two.
The idea is that if the sample is drawn evenly and representatively from the distribution, the population distribution,
then the relative frequencies of different items in the sample reflects the relative frequencies of of approximately those values in the population.
And so if we sample from this, if we. Sample each data point from the sample.
The whole sample, then that's comparable to sampling it from the whole distribution.
So we do that multiple times to get an entire new sample, we want to have the same length as the old sample.
We compute from the statistics, from our new sample. Then we do this a bunch of times, a thousand times, 10000 times.
And the distribution of this statistic from doing the boot.
This and this technique is called the bootstrap. The distribution of the statistic from the bootstrap approximates the sampling distribution.
It's not perfect because there's stuff in the population that might not have made it into the sample,
but it's going to approximate the sampling distribution well enough to use it to start to estimate confidence and other properties of sampling.
The statistic. So to bootstrap a confidence interval, one way we can do it.
This is called the percentile method. Is to compute the mean of a bunch of samples.
So the mean we're computing a mean and this I'm doing all this with no high.
So if X is our sample. This can be a panda series.
The choice, the choice random number generator method is going to draw a sample of size N.
And the num pi choice function by default samples with replacements.
We're going to draw a sample of size N where N is the same length as as the Xs so and equals one of X.
S. We're going to do this ten thousand times, this is Arby.
And then we can compute. The two point five percentile and the ninety seven point five percentile to get
a window of where is 95 percent of the probability mass in this distribution.
And so we do this with our penguins and we get with one of our species of penguins and we get a confidence interval.
When you ask seabourne cap plot to plot the mean of the values grouped by category.
The error bars it gives you or the confidence bars it gives you are done using a 95 percent bootstrapped confidence interval like this.
It's the bootstrap itself is very simple. Its power is that we can replace mean with basically any statistic.
And we use Rie's sampling from the sample in order to estimate the sampling distribution.
Also, this syntax I'm using here. This square brackets is how we make a list.
Remember this syntax where we have an expression.
And then we have for I in range or I n anything that's iterable is what's called a list comprehension.
It's a very convenient way to build up a list from a loop. This is a place where we do use a loop.
It might be possible to vectorized the bootstrap. Doing so is difficult.
And also, so long as we vectorized each individual bootstrap vectorized in the bootstrap process
itself isn't as important because the bulk of the computation is within the iterations.
So we're gonna go ahead, do a for loop over our bootstrap intervals and then the bootstrapped the actual.
Bootstrapping itself. What we do within each bootstrap iteration.
That's thoroughly vectorized. So this gives. But doing this process, this boot means this is a distribution of the boot means.
And it shows that we've got the sample mean and it shows it matches up with those Quantico's that we just saw in the previous slide.
So we can estimate the sampling distribution for any statistic and we can estimate arbitrary properties of the sampling distribution,
which notes Quantrill's wants to know its variance. Lots of different things we can do with the sampling distribution by doing the bootstrap.
It's not a perfect method,
but it's a remarkably powerful method that allows us to do quite a few different things to understand the sampling behavior of our statistics.
To wrap up the sampling distribution requires taking multiple sample to the sampling.
Distribution is about what happens. We take a lot of samples from the population.
We can simulate this by re sampling the sample itself using a technique called the bootstrap.