This video and one to interest. Introduce us to ways of comparing distributions visually so our outcomes are to be able to draw.
Q Q Plot to compare two distributions and assess fit with one of these plots.
So we get some data points, we can draw them with a histogram. We know how to do this and we can look at them.
And we want to if we want to ask, say, are these points normally distributed? That's hard to tell from the histogram.
These look like they're probably normal. If I could envision drawing a curve that looks approximately normal through those.
OK. But that's not a very good. That's not a very good test.
And it also. Particularly because with the beaning and also with random.
Little clusters here and there. It's difficult to accurately tell from a histogram of what we're looking at as normal,
but histograms are not the only ways we can show distributions if we want to compare to distributions.
We can use something called a Q cue plot and a Q Q plot gives us an easy way to compare whether the data are likely drawn from the same distribution.
So each point is each point corresponds to a data point.
But. On the on the x axis, we are showing that the quantity of corresponding to that point.
In the theoretical distribution, so the reference distribution, so the theoretical Quantrill's in this case might want to test for normality.
This is a standard normal distribution. So the first point in the data set, where would the first point be?
Probably be if I drew this at this many points from a normal distribution.
And the y axis is the the value in the actual data.
In this case, normalized or standardized have a mean of zero and a standard deviation of one.
But otherwise unchanged. And if the data come from the reference and reference distribution of the same distribution.
So we're using normal as our reference and the data are normal. Then we're going to see.
Fist straight line. That we see through the data points.
Because when we align up the data points and where we would expect them to be, what we would expect them to be if they were normal.
Those match the data, match what we would expect if this data were drawn from a normal distribution.
If we see some points over here doing this. And something like that.
Then that would indicate that we don't have a normal distribution and we see a few points here that are kind of off the line a little bit.
That's OK. Especially out of the tails. It's it's common to see a couple of points at each side that that aren't quite on the line.
But the fact that in the middle of the plot. That line is lining up.
That gives us confidence that what we're looking at is a normal distribution and.
This this plot design allows us to directly compare to distributions in a way that's much, much more precise than trying to eyeball a histogram.
The X coordinates can be values from the theoretical distribution, such as a normal. You can use this for any kind of distribution.
You can use it for an exponential a T, a wible pick your distribution.
And but they can also be from a second datasets. We have if we have two data sets and we want to see if they were drawn from the same distribution.
We can do that with a Q Q plot as well. So the plot one of these the stats that's models package provides the coocoo plot function and.
There's a couple of options. There's one, the line equals forty five options going to show a match line.
It's going to draw that red line that we saw. And there's another option that aligns the data to standardizes the data.
That drawing the 45 degree line, that straight line from corner to corner is going to be the line where a match that data match falls.
I'm writing a notebook, the one sample notebook in this week's material. It demonstrates how to draw.
Q Cube plot. And it also shows how to build your own Kyuki plot. So we use stats, models, Kyuki plot in there.
But then I also work through the pieces just using standard num pi a matplotlib features in order to get us to a cute, cute plot.
Hopefully that I hope make a little more sense, but most of the time I just draw the queue.
I use just use stats, models, Kyuki plot to get my Kyuki plots.
So to conclude Q Q plots, let us compare data between two to see compare data from two different distributions.
It might be observed data and a theoretical distribution, or it might be two different, two different samples of data points.
And on the Q Q plot, when the distributions match the data are in a straight line.