This video, I want to talk with you now about testing hypotheses.
So we've talked about estimating values and computing the precision of an estimate by looking at the width of a confidence interval.
We've seen how to do that, both param metrically using the standard error for the mean and also doing it with the bootstrap.
In this video, we're going to talk about no and alternative hypotheses to test for hypotheses and bootstrapping P values.
So if we had the question, do pet Gentoo penguins have longer flippers than chinstrap penguins?
We can what we can do to try to assess this question is measured the difference in average flipper length.
And then we can ask.
Suppose they didn't have different length that Jeonju penguins and chinstrap penguins are the same in terms of their flipper length.
How likely would I be to find this big of a difference in flipper length?
Under those conditions, this probability, we call that the null hypothesis.
For most statistical tests, the null hypothesis is everything's the same.
There's no actual difference. And this probability that we see this big of a difference, given that there's no difference, is called a P value.
So. We're doing the test. We define two hypotheses.
The null hypothesis in this case that the mean flipper account or the mean flipper length for a Gentoo is the same as for a chinstrap.
And the alternative hypothesis, they aren't. And then we use we can use in this case,
we can use what's called a two sample t test that computes the probability that our that we see this big of a difference in our sample means,
given that there is no difference. H0 The true means are the same.
If P is low, a common threshold is point zero five. Then we read say that the data reject that.
We reject the null hypothesis. If it's if P is large, then we say the data could not reject the null hypothesis.
This bias is our discovery procedure into towards not claiming things.
But we. We. We say here, if it's small, that we reject the null.
So there's many different tests, each with their own H zero H.
Not that the null hypothesis.
The one sample T test is the null hypothesis is that the mean is zero, or we can set it to mean as any other particular constant.
The two sample T test asks. So we've got sample two different samples and we have their sample means.
The null hypothesis is that the means are the same. The paired t test, we have, again, two measurements, but in the two sample T tests,
we have measurements from one sample of measurements from another sample in the paired T test.
We have one sample and we take two measurements for each for each element in the sample.
And this can be one way this comes up is in what we call between subjects or within subjects experiment.
So when it between subjects experiment you. Take say, if you're trying to test a the effectiveness of a computer interface or your.
You're trying to test whether the new widget you stuck on your Web site is improving sales.
You have a sample of your users, half of them. You have used the new widget.
Half of them, you have used the old widget. You compute the sales and then used you test.
It's between subjects, but you have different subjects in each condition or within subjects.
Experiment. The subjects are in both conditions.
So if you have two different, maybe you have two different widgets for two different boxes for how you want to finish checking out.
A shopping cart. And you're doing a study in a lab and you have you want everybody to try both.
And you have them. So you have everybody. Put the shopping experience with one interface.
Complete it with another. You measure maybe the speed, maybe the error rate.
When you do this, you do what's called counterbalancing.
You have half of them, have them in one order and half of them in the other in case there's an order or learning effect.
But the idea here is that for each user, you have their speed with one interface in their speed with another interface.
So they're paired in that case. You do the paired t test.
And what you're tactically want to test is your testing. It's it's a one sample t test.
The test, if the me if the mean of the difference between two measurements for the same person, the same idea when the sample is zero.
If it's zero then they came from the same. Then there's no actual difference.
So that's our that's our null hypothesis. ANOVA extends it beyond one level.
So to one sample, two sample pairs. What if we have.
Five samples. Then we use Enova. What if we have?
Five measurements. Then we use what's called repeated measures, Enova. But the H.
The null hypothesis for Enova is that all means are equal.
So each of these tests, though, they make assumptions and they're often quite strong, the T test makes them assumptions about the data.
It's relatively robust to violations of its normality assumptions.
Independence is a killer in any of these tests.
And this is why you have to use the paired t test when you have paired data because the samples are not independent.
If I do, I if I am particularly slow at using of doing a kind of task,
then even if the new interface makes me faster at it than the old interface, I will.
My speeds will be lower than they would someone else.
And so by pairing it controls for that, because it's just looking at the difference between the speed.
How much did it speed me up? How much did it speed up?
Enova also depends on quite a few assumptions getting into the details of a nova are beyond the scope of what we have time to get to,
particularly this week. But we can also bootstrap a P value in.
The idea here is that we have some statistic. I'm going to call it T. But I might be the mean.
It might be some kind of a normalized statistic. It might be whatever statistic we're trying to compute and what we do.
So the goal of the bootstrap lots is resample. But the goal here is to simulate the distribution of the statistic under the null hypothesis.
So we transform the data to follow the null hypothesis in some way.
We bootstrap the transform data and we compute a statistic from each bootstrap sample.
And then we look at what's the probability that this bootstrapped statistic exceeds.
Or is at least as large as our sample statistic. The tricky part of doing this is properly sampling from the null hypothesis.
And this you're gonna have to figure out for each bootstrap that you want to do. But if we're going to test if we're gonna do the two sample test.
So the T-test, the the H not is that this means are the same.
We can also think about a somewhat richer no hypothesis that chinstrap it Gentoo instant's strap Flipper's have the same distribution.
But here we're only going to measure the mean. So the no bootstrap, though not since the null hypothesis is they have the same distribution.
What I can do is I can pool all the measurements.
So it is going to take all of the Gentoo chinstrap, penguin flipper length, stick them all together in one big list.
And then I'm going to. Because if if there's no difference in flipper length between a Gentoo, an entrenched chinstrap,
then if I'm sampling of flipper length, it shouldn't matter which penguin I'm sampling it from.
So. We compute our bootstrap samples, one that's the length of our chinstraps sample ones that that's the length of our Gentoo sample.
And we compute the P value. That's the fraction of the bootstrap runs where the magnitude, the difference exceeds our observed difference.
And so if our observed value is if the observed value we have and the difference is common, then the penguins are probably not that different.
But if it's very difficult to boots, if it's very rare for this bootstrap procedure to give us the value we saw,
then that's evidence that there's a difference in the flipper lengths of the penguins.
The notebook I'm going to give you to go with this video shows the code for how to actually do the bootstrap of the P value in addition to the T test.
Another issue we run into is when we have multiple usually we don't just run one test in a paper or another report.
We have many if we call the. So the threshold we use, we compare this p value, the probability of seeing this, of seeing a result that's extreme.
If the null hypothesis is true.
We compare that to what we called the significance level alpha, which is our threshold for saying, and probably it's more likely to be true.
So if we have Alpha is O point five, then if we run 20 tests.
That. And the null hypothesis is true and all of them.
We will probably find one that sticks statistically significant. If we run 100, we'll probably find five.
And so you get what's called a false discovery. There are ways to correct for this the bond ferrone correction is a conservative but
sound correction that scales down our significance level by the number of tests we run.
Not not just the ones that are reported in the paper.
And there's other corrections that work in various situations to be able to correct for these multiple comparisons is the Benjamina family,
the Benjamina Horsburgh, which works if all of our tests are independent.
There's another variant that works that can deal with non independence between dependency relationships, between our different tests.
So, for example, if we if we compare all pairs of penguin species, chinstrap to Gentoo,
chinstrap to a deli Chinh strapped to their skewes, you just accidentally chinstrap to a deli.
Adelita Gentoo. Those aren't all independent. But one thing we need to think about is what the results are for.
If this is our threshold and we're saying, OK, P less than point zero five,
we found something and that's our evidence, then we need to be scaling and most of the time.
But as I said back in the first video this week, my perspective on this topic is multi evidentiary.
A P value is not a conclusive judgment that we found something.
A P-value is one piece of evidence that this is worth continuing to look at and in support of of the results that we're finding.
It's if the P value is high. So the results we're seeing are completely consistent with the null hypothesis.
Then that means we probably haven't found something. But if it's low, there's a bunch of other reasons why why we might have seen what we've seen.
We should have some skepticism. It's one piece of evidence among many of the uncorrected p value is still evidence we have.
So depending on how we treat it in the process of drawing our conclusions.
So a few pitfalls, the P values of the multiple comparison ones.
There's also the issue of what we're doing, experiments on the same data set over and over.
Should we be correcting for all of the P values ever run on that data set?
They're also designed for prospective experiments. So the mathematics around P values, also the mathematics around confidence intervals, et cetera.
They came out of this sampling theory where we're thinking about things prospectively.
So I'm going to go and I'm going to take a sample and computer statistic and I want to know what the distribution of that is.
But in data science, we're often in retrospect, if we have an existing data set,
even if we're gonna sample from it, we're often looking at the whole data set before we do our sampling.
That doesn't mean they're not useful. The statistic, they're really, really P-value.
We can still compute it. It's still a piece of evidence. It's just not.
The judge's final sentence also full validity for what he values telling us requires us to plan the whole analysis before we look at the data.
The P-value computes the probability of our statistic being this large, given the null hypothesis, is true.
But when we look at our data, first we do an exploratory analysis. We plot some charts.
I say, oh, this looks like a relationship. This looks like looks like these means are different.
And then we go to our hub. Then we go do a T test.
What we're actually computing is the probability of the statistic,
given that the null hypothesis is true and that the null hypothesis looks false because our choice of what to test is influenced by this information.
And so the p value is not measuring what the process that we actually use to drive it.
Also, the null hypothesis is usually not precisely true. Paying mean penguins might be slightly different, just not different enough to matter.
Again, I said this is not this does not mean we should not compute the P values.
This does not mean they're useless. This means they need to be. Taken as one piece of evidence in the context that the totality of the evidence
that we bring to understanding what it is that we're trying to understand,
statistics and actual application is a lot of reasoned judgment calls.
There's bad call there. There's there's many, many ways to do statistics poorly.
I have a book on my shelf called Statistics Done Wrong The Woefully Complete Guide.
The reason judgment's doesn't mean anything goes,
but it does mean that we need to there's not gonna be the bright line rule to say, yes, we found something.
We have our pieces of evidence who have our confidence intervals. We have our P values. We have the other things we compute from the bootstrap.