This video, I'm going to talk with you a little bit more about t tests. Give us some more ideas of what they do, how they work.
And also, when you need to use the different kinds and their python functions,
learning outcomes are for you to be able to select the appropriate form of t test for some data that you have.
And understand what the T test does. So if we have.
So we have some idea normal's so they're independent and identically distributed in their normal observations of a variable.
And we want to test the null hypothesis that the true mean is equal to some fixed value.
Often this is going to be we're going to see if it's equal to zero. But we can see if it's equal to any other particular value.
And so the null hypothesis is the day, the mean, the true mean of the population is equal to to our value, say zero.
And we want to see, does the data support or reject the null hypothesis.
So what we do is we calculate a test statistic called a T statistic,
which is the difference between the sample mean and the the target mean divided by the standard error.
And what this gives us is it gives us a normalized version of the difference in the difference and means that's
normalized by the natural variance from the sampling distribution that we would expect in the for computing the mean.
And the idea here is that if the MI so that the sampling, the standard error gives us the standard deviation of our sampling distribution.
Remember, the sampling distribution of the sample mean is normal with variance of the standard error.
And so we. If the meet the difference in means is small with respect to that width, that that error, then it's going to be.
Then the difference in means is probably due to sampling error. But if the difference is big,
then it's substantially less likely that that's due to the sampling and more likely that the mean the population doesn't actually equal our target,
such as zero. So what we do with this T statistic is we compute the probability that doing this a bunch of times.
So repetitions. We compute the probability that doing this a bunch of times is going to give T.
T statistics that are at least as large in their magnitude as the observed one that we have.
If the null hypothesis is true. This is a probability given age zero.
So we're trying to see what's the probability that we have a T with this size of absolute value.
This is called a two sided T test that the common ones we're just seeing, the magnitude of T is going to be this large.
If the means are actually equal, the code for this is to use the T test one sample function from Saipov.
What happens if we get this T statistic and it follows a distribution called a T distribution with N minus one degrees of freedom?
And so if the distribution and so we can look and we can see where does the T statistic, where does the observed T value fall in this distribution?
And it might be that, oh, there's a lot. So it's it's here. And if we consider it where, it would be on the left as well.
OK. There's a lot of probability mass outside those values.
So a value, this extreme value of this about point five under this particular distribution.
That's got to be common. Just do the sampling variation. That value is completely expected.
But if we go all the way out here to a T statistic of point of three point five.
There is not much probability mass outside the three point fives.
And that means that if the no hypothesis were true, seeing a T statistic of three point five would be very unlikely.
Which means that the data it's the data probably didn't come from the null hypothesis.
They probably came from something else. And so we would reject the null hypothesis.
But that's what happened with the tease, with the T test. You compute this T statistic from your data, which is this standardized difference in means.
And you compare that to the distribution, the t distribution gives us the distribution of T statistics under the null hypothesis,
which is that there is no difference in means. And as the degrees of freedom go to infinity, the T statistic approaches normal.
It's an adjusted normal, basically. So I want to talk just a moment about these degrees of freedom.
So the degrees of freedom are the number of ABB's observations in a series.
We have a series of observations we have and observations. How many of them can freely vary for the purposes of computing a statistic?
If we if we're just trying to if we're trying to compute the mean all of our values can change.
Change any value in our dataset. It's going to change the mean.
But if we have the mean, the sample mean and we're trying to compute the standard deviation.
Then we can't. Not all of them can vary.
Only out of end data points only and minus one can vary.
Because if we have X one directs event X squared minus one and we have the mean, we can compute the last value.
So for the purpose of the standard deviation, effectively, one way we can see it is that computing the intermediate statistic,
the mean we're gonna compute the standard deviation if we can, to compute this T statistic.
It uses up one degree of freedom. Can you fix it?
Only N minus one of our samples can vary, and so that lead.
So we have N minus one degrees of freedom or computing standard error, which then goes into the T statistic.
So for the the one sample t test, the degrees of freedom and minus one,
we use that to compute the T distribution, we see where the C which T distribution we're going to use.
We see where our value lies on it. The two sample T test it take so that one simple T test test is my saying is the mean of my source population.
My sample came from equal to some fixed value. The two sample team test asks, I have two samples.
Did they come from a population with the same mean? So let's say we have the we have the Adelie penguins and the Gentoo penguins.
We have the mean flipper length of these two samples of penguins. And we want to see, do they come from the same man or they come from?
Does the population of Adelie penguins and Gentoo penguins probably have the same mean?
Or does it probably have different means that this depends on the samples being independent?
No relationship between data points in each sample data point is in one of the two categories.
If you have relationships, then we're going to see the paired T test.
But this makes sense of how a penguin is either in a deli or a Gentoo.
So we're gonna use the the independent, the independent T test.
The null hypothesis is mbewe one equals mbewe to the means of the two populations that are represented by these two samples are the same.
And our T statistic is we subtract the means and then we divide by a combination of their standard deviations and sample sizes.
This is the degrees of freedom for this are significantly more complicated if we
allow the two populations to have the two samples to have different variances.
Are we allowed? Excuse me? We assume the two part. We allow the two populations of different variances.
If we assume they have the same variance, we get a much simpler version of the two sample T test.
But in general, they might have different variances. If this is the T statistic, the degrees of freedom are relatively complicated.
I don't recommend actually calculating this yourself. We have tea test functions that are going to help us calculate the T test.
This just gives you an idea of what those are doing so that you can better understand when you run a T test what's actually happening.
So we do our Adelie penguins, we get a T statistic of minus five point seven eight.
We can plot that on our on our T distribution. We get a P value of six point oh five times 10 to the negative eight.
This data would be very, very shocking to find if.
A deli and Gentoo penguins had the same flipper like. So we reject the null a paired t test is when we have two measurements from the same samples.
So each data point appear, rather we have two measurements,
but rather than having a measurement from one sample on a measurement from another sample like the penguins, what we have is they're paired.
So each measurement in one group hat is paired with a measurement and the other, for example, we've got two tests in this class.
Your score on test one in your score on test two would be paired sample of paired observations.
And what we do then is we compute the difference between these observations, say your test to score minus your test one score.
And that gives us one sample and we compare them that mean to zero.
So apparently test is a one sample T test that the mean difference is not with the null hypothesis that the mean difference is equal to zero.
And this is really useful for testing if there is a difference. When you take the same student and you give them two tests, you take the same.
The same patient and you give them two treatments, one week one and one week two.
This is a way of testing if there's a difference between the two observations of the two treatments on the same patient or the same research subject.
You're going to use this in assignment to to compare ratings from two different sources.
For the same movies. So to run these tests, the one if you have one sample and you want to test it, mean use the one sample T test.
If you have paired measurements. So you've got the movies and you have the all critics score and you have the top critics star.
Those are two measurements for the same movie. And you want to see if they're different than you use a paired T test.
Saipov gives you a paired T test function. But you can also compute the differences and use the one sample T test.
You can test two independent sample. So.
The four, if you see the four, two independent samples, you use the two sample T test the independent tests.
So sci fi calls this T test end by default. Both sigh pie and Stach models to independent two sample T test functions assume equal variance.
You can turn this off and say pi by setting equal var equal to false.
When you're calling the T test ion d function and it'll use the more sophisticated T statistic and the more sophisticated degrees of freedom.
So there are a lot of other tests. This is the usual practice for test.
A significant test. You compute a statistic and then you compare that statistic to a known distribution
that describes how it would be distributed under the null hypothesis.
In these cases, we compute a T statistic and the T distribution describes how that statistic is distributed when the null hypothesis is true.
We can also use these statistics then to bootstrap,
although sometimes we might we might not use the standardized Verd like the T statistic and we can directly bootstrap with the means.
To wrap up significance tests, compute the probability of a statistic under the null hypothesis.
Fundamentally under the hood. That's what they do.
The tricky parts are you need to have the statistic and you need to know its distribution under the null hypothesis.
The T test does this with the T statistic and with the standard I. Or with the T statistic, which is a standardized version of the vet of the.
The difference of the mean observed from the mean that you're trying to compare.