Hello again, this video. I want to talk to you about ways of knowing what's called epistemology in our learning outcomes for this video,
for us to understand different sources of knowledge and identify saw sources of knowledge that are appropriate to a question,
because the way that we're going about work in this class, we said at the very beginning,
data science is the practice of using data to gain quantitative insight in the questions of social, scientific or business interest.
It is not the only way to obtain knowledge is not the only source of knowledge.
And so I want us in this video to think a little bit about some of these other sources of knowledge and how they relate to each other.
So some types of knowledge we can can encounter are quantitative knowledge that we've been working on in this class.
I'm going to work on for the rest of the class. And that's around numbers and quantities, qualitative knowledge,
which looks at the actual content and we aren't doing quantitative count like we aren't counting things.
We are computing statistics. We're looking at say what taxed or what videos or what images actually say analytical or knowledge or proofs.
These are these are mathematical derivations.
There's no there's no data in them that's driving them.
For example, the fact that the T statistic is distributed under the T distribution, under the null hypothesis.
That's mathematically proven. We didn't do a bunch of simulations or experiments to figure that out.
There's theory building to put together knowledge from a variety of sources and from a variety
of experiments or studies or investigations into a coherent theory of how a subject works.
And then there's critical knowledge that pokes at and investigates the structure, particularly the power structures.
But the structure of how something how a process for producing knowledge or how a thing we're studying is put
together and what how it got to where it is and what impact that may have on the results that we get from it.
One thing that's important to note is both quantitative and qualitative forms of knowledge are empirical.
They're getting from the data to the conclusions or to the insights that we have on
the question of quantitative methods do not have a monopoly on being data driven.
No one form of knowledge is the best.
And we often need multiple forms of knowledge together to gain a full understanding of something that we're trying to study.
So a quantitative measure methods are the things that we've been doing this semester, numeric methods and estimates.
We could ask how many of us there are, if something, what fraction and have some property.
We can try to predict numeric outcomes, lots of different things we can do with numbers.
And there's various sub methods. For example, observational studies.
They look at what we can see. We have data that we've collected.
Either we've gone and collected it in the field.
We have it from a dataset and we can see we've observed some process and we can look for correlations,
we can look for connections, and we can try to gain insight based on what we can observe in the world.
Experimental studies look at what happens when we intervene, when we act, when we change something.
How does what we're studying respond to it? So the observational studies can be so we look at our penguins and we can see their flipper lengths.
We can see their body masses. Experimental studies can let us get at.
Well, what happens when we give some penguins one diet and then other penguins another diet to understand it,
to isolate the impact of diet on, say, penguin growth?
And a simulation study looks at what happens in synthetic environments,
and these allow us to run a lot more analysis and studies than we can in an experiment because we don't have to collect data.
We don't have to use experimental resources in order to to create and observe changes.
We can just turn read a bunch of random numbers.
According to some structured process, and these are really good for understanding, particularly what have our made her methods.
So. If we have a method for studying what would happen in an experiment, we can simulate a bunch of different experiments,
maybe with different outcomes to see what our method would do when we got to control the experimental results because we made them up.
This is a really powerful tool for studying the statistical properties themselves.
And one of the things, especially those of you who are in the data science P.
D program, but also as you get deeper in your data science knowledge,
that's something that's going to be be very important for you to be able to go to to level up
from using the methods that we were developing and that we're learning to study phenomenon.
We're going to use we're gonna use our linear models to study something about penguins, maybe to being able to study the methods themselves.
Can what can we say about how a linear model works or about how a T test works or or the bootstrap simulation studies are really useful for that.
But these quantitative methods, they can ask some really useful.
They can address some really useful questions. We can see how often something happens.
We can see when it happens. How likely is it when X happens?
How likely is it for Y to happen? We can get these kinds of how often, how many, how likely kinds of questions.
What's hard to answer is why does X happen or when X happens?
What do those situations actually look like?
So an example, I'm going to talk a little bit more about it as we go through the slide, but we're trying to understand.
So we've got we've got a large company with a number of locations, B, where a supermarket chain.
And we want to understand employee retention. We can look at, say, how often employees leave or say, leave within their first year.
We can ask. When some particular change happened to the store, change happens in personnel policies.
How likely are employees to leave or if one employee leaves?
Are there more that are likely to follow? But, well, we don't really what the numbers can't give us is for any given employee leaving.
What was the situation? Why did they leave? It also doesn't give us insight into what new phenomenon should we look for.
The numbers can't tell us on their own and the quantitative methods can't tell us on their own.
What questions to even ask of the data. So this gets us to qualitative methods.
And qualitative methods are about interpretation and analysis.
And it lets us look at questions like why did someone do X quantitative?
Lets us ask how often it happened. Qualitative. Let's start to get at.
Why did they do it? Why did it happen? Or what do people want?
And the key thing about qualitative methods is that they engage directly with some kind of source material,
written text images, interviews and interview transcripts.
But you've got some source material, often textual.
But sometimes it's visual, sometimes it's video, and you're engaging directly with it and interpreting it.
Humans ever. You can't import pandas that qualitative, that's not a thing.
There's a very human process of engaging with the material in order to derive knowledge.
One quick note is that surveys where they get data from humans are not on their own qualitative.
If you ask someone a Likert Stiles survey strongly disagree to strongly agree and a bunch of questions.
You're getting quantitative data. If you have open free form text and you start to go analyze what they said.
That's qualitative data.
So in our example problem, if we want to understand employee concerns and opportunities to improve how our organization is treating employees,
we could go do some structured interviews and a semi structured interview.
Is it interview where you have a plan going into it, but it's not a rigorous answer.
These questions in a row and we're done kind of plan. You have goals for the interview.
You have key questions thought of in advance.
But the conversation, an interview can also go in the directions that seem natural as the interviewer is leading through it.
And the resulting data is you've got all of these interviews with employees. You.
You're probably going to transcribe them because we're doing the analysis as often a
lot easier to work with the transcribed text rather than the actual than the audio.
But you don't. It's expensive. And if you're going to sit down and have a half hour interview with each employee, that takes a long time.
You don't have time to interview them all.
One key thing, when we're doing quantitative methods or goals, statistical representations that the statistics we computer,
accurate estimates of the underlying parameters, the goal and qualitative analysis is not statistical representation.
The goal is to make sure that the different.
Subgroups and sex and characteristics and dynamics that you might try to be look, be able to find in the data are all represented at least once.
We're not going to be getting statistical counts out of this.
And so the statistical representation is just not the right way to frame thinking about qualitative responses.
So one particular method, there's many methods for qualitative analysis.
You can spend. I have spent my research career of 10 plus years now getting very good at a lot of quantitative methods.
You can spend that much time and then the entire rest of your career getting very good at qualitative methods.
There is skill just as much as the quantitative methods. There are no easier really to do them well.
But one particular qualitative method is called grounded theory,
and the idea of grounded theory is to start from the text itself and build up to ideas and figure out what themes are in the text
and how they connect to each other in a way that is as close to the text as possible and is derived from the text as possible.
And to get the ideas and the concepts from the text rather than from your preconceived ideas going into it of what should be in the text.
So what you do when you're doing grounded theory, if you're going to do grounded theory on these interviews,
is that you would break them into distinct statements or observations and then you would group these observations together into themes.
So you would take an observation. And if it's like an existing theme that you have, you would add it.
And if it's not like any any of the existing themes, you would start a new theme taking observations.
See, is this like any of the five kinds of things I've seen so far? Yes.
Put it in the pile. Like actually physically moving things around the piles is useful for this.
And if not, we're going to start a new one. So you have this this matching thing going on.
And then as you're going through the process, or once you get to the end of the process, you may merge.
Themes may say, oh, these things were really they were seeming separate.
I am coding, but they really do seem like they're together or maybe they're subthemes of another theme.
Now, in statistics, we have this notion of, OK, we have a statistically significant sample or a statistically significant results.
We know if we found it, we can talk about our sample size and things with this kind of a method.
What you use as your stopping condition is what's called saturation. And here, like stopping early to get statistical significance, not valid.
Saturation is. And the idea of saturation is that more data does not reveal more concepts.
So you've grouped your things together. You found 12 themes and doing this grounded theory process with another trend.
Another few interviews does not generate any new themes.
And this, if you're doing the process, if you got confidence in the process, then what this means is that you've hit conceptual saturation.
You have identified the themes that are coming from your data. More data isn't adding new themes.
So we have the themes. Our goal here is to extract themes. Now we have them.
The outcome of this process is our themes with illustrative quotations.
So we've put these observations in cities into the additional into the different themes and these observations themselves,
the things that our our interviewees, our employees said.
Those are quotations that illustrate the dynamic going on in that theme.
As I said before, qualitative methods are empirical. The conclusions are grounded in and supported by data.
The data is just analyzed differently. To get to those conclusions. Qualitative is very useful for demonstrating the existence of a phenomenon.
People do this because people say they they give or there's this reason why people leave.
Yes, we have at least one who said that was the reason they leaved in our in our data set.
And they can also help us elucidate the mechanisms for phenomenon because they allow us to dove much more deeply into each
specific example to understand what were the factors that caused this employee to leave or that causes them to continue to stay.
And the data is is what's called sometimes thick but low in quantity.
We don't have very many of these interviews. Relatively speaking, we might have 10 or 20.
We might even have 50. But we're not going to have the hundreds of data points we might have from a survey or from some other quantitative method.
But each of those individual data points,
an interview with a with an employee is much richer and gives us much more detail on it, on individual samples.
You can also mix methods, what's called mixed methods, research.
There's a variety of ways that you can combine quantitative and qualitative methods together.
I'm going to talk briefly about two.
One is where you do a qualitative study first so you can do a qualitative study with a small group to identify what concerns people have.
You may do some interviews with employees to understand some of their concerns around workplace safety or workplace environment.
And then you can follow that up with a quantitative study to see how widely held these different
concerns that came up in your qualitative study or qualitative demonstrates existence.
Quantitative measures, prevalence. Another one you can do as quantitative first.
You could do a quantitative analysis to identify the stores with low employee retention.
That's something quantitative analysis can do well. And then a qualitative analysis can help you understand why.
So go to some of those stores, interview some of the employees,
interview some of the managers and understand what's happening at the stores that have low employee retention.
These are just two ways that we can use qualitative methods and quantitative methods together, either to have the qualitative methods,
generate the hypotheses that we're going to go test quantitatively and measure the prevalence of quantitatively
or to better understand the dynamics and the nuances of what's happening in an effect that we see quantitatively.
So 30. What is 30 mean?
Numbers on their own don't mean anything. We have to have context to interpret this meaning.
Thirty is the typical size of this class. This fall, we only have twenty three.
But the typical size, this class is 30. OK, that give me a little more meaning.
At least know what we're talking about now in our department.
That's large for an art, for a graduate class, but it's about average for the department's classes overall.
OK. That helps. Gives me context to understand that we're looking at a large graduate class.
Why do we care about graduate classes as well? Class size affects teacher student engagement.
So this gives us. There's many other reasons why we might care about class size.
But it's easier to individually engage with students when the class size is relatively small.
That gives us more context for understanding why we even care about this value.
So we need context to interpret quantities and identify quantities of interest.
Qualitative methods can give us a lot of that context and a really, really rich way.
Now I want to talk briefly about analytical methods. Analytical methods are dealing with mathematical proofs and derivations.
As I said, they're usually quantitative, but they're not empirical. We're not looking at what data is telling us.
We're looking at the intrinsic fundamental properties of computation of method, etc. They're always true, given their assumptions that they.
If we have a proof that given some assumptions X follows, that's not something that depends on the condition.
When the assumptions hold, assuming that the proof is correct, it holds it may be probabilistic.
The proof we have may be something about how often something happens, like confidence intervals.
Confidence intervals don't always contain the mean. But we have a probability.
We have a proof about how often they do contain the mean.
Then another method is I want to bring up to you a little bit is critical methods, including what's called critical theory.
And the key idea of these methods is to analyze and explicate the power structures that
are at play and the thing that we're studying or in our process of studying in itself.
Who has power in a given situation? What are the effects of that power and that distribution of power?
Can also ask, how does perspective and the power or lack thereof that comes with it affect the questions and the can we equip.
The questions we ask and the conclusions that we come to from those?
For example, if we're trying to understand employee retention, the fact that it's employer or the employer's agent talking to the employee,
that creates a power dynamic that can affect the employees response to the survey if they think
things they say might be might affect their employment or the terms of their employment,
that might affect what they say. But that power dynamic can, in a very direct way, affect the data.
The results that we get out of it. So one way that one application for thinking about power is to look at who is making the decisions.
This looks at the overall process itself.
What we're doing this study to understand employee retention and what is causing low employee retention or what's caused it,
what's what's making our employees want to stay with the organization. But.
Credit one thing. Critical methods are going to get at is. Who is making the study about the decisions about the study?
Who's deciding what questions to ask in our survey or or our interviews?
Who is deciding who to talk to in this? And who's going to be deciding what to do with the results?
Because. If it is a collection of employees that are deciding what to do with the results,
that's very different than efforts, organization management that's deciding what to do with the results.
One thing also that's important to note is asking employees and questions about retention,
even very, very good, even if it's done very, very good faith.
We want to make the organization a good place to work. For going to ask our employees what.
What they see going on. How they think about their their work.
Asking the poor ye employees on its own is not sharing power in the way that critical methods.
Think about who has power and how it's distributed.
So then I want to talk then a little bit about theory, not in the critical theory sense, but in the theory building sense,
some dictionary defines theory as a plausible or scientifically acceptable general principle or body of principles offered to explain phenomena.
It's a it's a kahir is a framework. That links together our findings from a lot of different studies, from a lot of different experiments,
from different sources of knowledge into a coherent explanation or way of thinking about a phenomenon or a set of problems and theory drives analysis.
Because if we're doing good data science, if we're doing good quantitative analysis, our questions aren't just made up.
They come from a reason we have from theory why that's a relevant question to ask.
And theory in turn, comes from all of these sources because data.
And analytical and query and critical inquiry, they refine their confirm and confirm and sometimes they reject theories.
The process by which that happens is long and complicated and is the the subject of study
of both the philosophy of science and the discipline called science and technology studies.
But. Feary and our defriended are different modes of inquiry, have this.
This interactive relationship. That we have a theory that tells us things to go look for, we go look for them.
Those in turn come back and help us refine our general understanding of how the thing we're studying works.
Lastly, I want to say a little bit about our science and technology studies concept.
So often said that knowledge is socially constructed and it becomes relevant, particularly when we start thinking about as relevant in general,
being to try to understand how our tools work and their limitations and their possibilities.
It also becomes very important to start to think about the social ramifications
of data science and the ramifications of social structures on data science.
But what this means is that knowledge comes through processes and those processes are social.
Social construction does not mean that knowledge is fake or made up or unreliable or like, oh, it's socially constructed so we can dismiss it.
No, that's not what it means. All it means is that what we know about the world we know is through social processes.
Because you're in this class learning how to do data analysis.
I am teaching you a particular way of approaching data, a particular way of applying statistical tests and interpreting the results.
That is a social process. We're having these dialogs and conversations about it.
I learned these through a social process. I subject when we go and we publish papers.
We subject them to a peer review process. This is a social process, our peers look at it and assess it.
And as a as a community. We come to our notion, sometimes agreed upon, sometimes contested, about what kinds of questions we should ask,
how we should go about answering them, how do we know if what we've found is true?
Well, with our tools for doing that may be very reliable in the sense that they produce knowledge that's useful for for predicting future behavior,
for understanding what's going on around us.
There's still there's social processes and they were developed socially and
they therefore have the various biases and limitations of a social process.
And understanding that I find helps me.
Respect science and statistics and the quantitative methods we're studying.
More. Because rather than putting them on a pedestal that they can never achieve of, they are the ultimate, for example.
They are the ultimate source of knowledge. Some who basically go there were like,
if we can't show it with a randomized controlled trial and a statistic and a statistical test, not going to believe it.
And it puts them in what they can actually do. They can generate a lot of quantitative insight that can help us understand the world better.
We have processes that we think are probably pretty good.
Understanding the social nature of these processes is a useful tool for us to be able to think about how to make them better.
And so it's it's it's important to recognize this the social nature of our methods, but not to let that paralyze us.
And they said not to let that dismiss them. It doesn't mean we're not finding useful knowledge.
It just means there's social processes that got us to where we are today.
So to wrap up quantitative measurements and analysis are not the only or the best way to produce knowledge.
There is no best way to produce knowledge. Multiple sources of knowledge together give multiple sources of knowledge together.