Hello, and this video, I want to talk with you just a little bit about how to read and interpret Python error messages,
learning outcomes are to be able to read a Python error message and understand
common kinds of python errors and the things that tend to cause them so.
You get a Python exception, so Python reports errors typically through exceptions.
And so we write in a lot of code and it gives us an error. So how do we read this?
There's a few things we want to look at. First. It's going to tell us near the top.
The type of error. This is an attribute error. Then at the bottom, it tells us, again, the error type.
And it gives us a message that often tells it gives us more information about what precisely went wrong in this case.
It tells us the data frame object has no attribute DFA. So I ran this in a notebook or ratings as a data frame.
There is no attribute DFA and that to the attribute errors telling us that.
So starting at the bottom here. This is one of the most important things to look at.
This is going to tell you what went wrong. And understanding what went wrong is the first piece to being able to understand why your code broke.
But then the last piece we have is the traceback. And it's so it's code says traceback and it says most recent call last.
So this tells you where that error happened. And the most recent call it, as it says, is last.
So if we go from the bottom up, we're going to find this happened in the.
Pandas core generic code and get atter that's deep in pandas.
And then it happened in our code. Ratings that DFA a good place to start and understanding a stack trace is to look
for the last entry since that's the innermost one that's in code you wrote,
because that's where your that's where in your code the error happened.
But the stack trace lets us work back up to understand why we got the error that we did and will often give us insight into.
So data frame has no attribute DFA, but where did we try to access that actually?
Oh, we access that in our code for saying ratings that DFA and there's no such attributes.
That's giving us the error. Being able to read the error message gives us a lot of useful information about what went wrong and being able to read the
error message and think about what that means in terms of your code is a crucial skill to being able to debug your python.
So a few components here, as we've seen, there's the error type. There's the location of the code where it happened.
And then there's additional information to go with the error.
Not all error types and not all code that throws errors or a particular type is going to put very useful information in the type error in the message.
It really varies from error to error and from library to library. But a lot of them do put useful information into that error message.
Once you know how to interpret it, so common type you there's a number of types of errors that you're going to see rather commonly.
The first one is a name error and a name error means you're trying to use a variable that doesn't exist.
So it's several different kinds of errors for referencing things that don't exist.
A name errors. You just try use a variable X at X does not exist and attribute error means you're trying to use a class member,
a method or a field on a classman object that does not exist.
Python calls those attributes. So when we say DOT, we have already a data frame.
We say dot act. When we say dot mean, what we're doing is we're getting the attribute mean,
which happens to be a function because that's how Python implements methods. But attribute error means we're trying to access one of these methods.
It can be a method. It can be a data field. But it doesn't actually exist.
A key error happens when we try to look up a key either in a dictionary or in a panda's index.
So using dot lock key area will come up. And the key doesn't exist.
So sometimes this arises. One way this arises is when pandas when you're passing something to dot lock.
Or just to the square brackets on a data frame and PANDAS isn't correctly interpreting the type of object that you're giving it.
That that's one way that can be caused, that this can be caused.
But the key here means it can't find the thing it's looking for in something that's looked up by key.
Pendas indexes.
If you're if you're passing in or a list or an array of index values, all of them have to be in the index or you're going to get a clear it index.
Error happens when you're accessing item by position, zero through and minus one,
either in a list or with Pande as I lock or something else that that uses this kind of zero based indexing.
And the index is out of bounds. It could be an umpire rate as well.
Index. So these are all different kinds of doesn't exist. Name error means the variable doesn't exist.
Attribute error means the class member doesn't exist. Key error means the key in the dictionary or index doesn't exist.
An index error means you've given it a numeric position that's out of bounds.
A few other errors you're going to see are file not found error. That means you're trying to access a file that doesn't exist.
If this happens, when you're reading a file, that usually means the file doesn't exist.
File is not found. If you get this when writing a file, what that usually means is you're trying to write it to a directory that does not yet exist.
The file doesn't have to exist for you to write it, but the directory you're writing it into does.
OS error often happens when we're reading and writing a file,
and that happens when there are other errors in the process, either of opening the file or of actually reading its data.
One way you might see this is if you're trying to write to a file on windows that you already have open somewhere else.
So to read an error, you want to understand three things, you want to understand what kind of thing went wrong.
So look at the air type RBD. Have a namer. You have a key air-to-air file not found.
Are these are all different. These all have different causes. Then you want to see what specifically went wrong.
The error message might tell you for a file not found error, it will usually tell you what file was not found.
And then you want to ask where it went wrong from the stack trace.
The key thing here is to understand what went wrong in your code so you can fix it.
Understanding this can really help you learn as you understand not how do I fix the error, but why did the error occur?
Oftentimes that gives more insight into how the code in the libraries that we're using in Python itself actually work.
Copying errors into Google can help you find useful resources.
But it's often not a good strategy for solving the problem because.
Someone else may have encountered that error. And good resources will give you the kinds of things that are going to help you fix that kind of error.
But there's a good chance no one else has counted that exact error.
And the solution that worked for them might not be applicable in your context.
And so it's important when we get an error message to understand why it went wrong so we can understand how to fix it in our particular context.
So to conclude, Python errors are reported by exceptions.
When we get an exception, we get a stack trace that includes a lot of useful information about what exception happened, where in the code it occurred.
And learning to read these is going to help us better understand the system that we're using and be able to fix and debug our code.