In this video, I'm going to briefly talk to you about the relationships between some of the different Python libraries that
we've been using since learning outcome as to know the relationships between these key data science libraries.
So NUM Pi is the foundation of most of what we're doing. And it provides the array features it built.
It has the Endi array n dimensional array data structure that we use to represent vectors matrices.
You can also use it for Tensas, which are three dimensional. They have rows and rows, columns in depth.
You can there's many of manipulation functions to do.
Vector operations. Vector vector vector matrix vector scalar matrix matrix to reshape, manipulate data frames.
All of the data frames make arrays and matrices. It also has what's called a ray broadcasting support.
So you can multiply a matrix by a vector in that doesn't do a matrix vector multiply.
But it if the matrix is as tall as the excuse me at the vector is, as long as the matrix is tall, it'll apply at it.
It'll apply it down the columns and apply this the same vector to every row and num pi really is the backbone of vector ization.
And spending some time, the textbook talks a lot more about how to use num pis various factorization capabilities.
But it's the it gives us the victimization operations and it's the backbone then of the rest of the libraries.
So we put them together. Cyb High builds on top of num pi and adds additional scientific capabilities, some primitive statistical capabilities.
Pandas builds on top of num pi to give us the data structures that allow us to assign labels to columns and rows.
So we have our column names, we have a row names. A num pi matrix has to be homogenous.
Every element has to be the same type. Abandons data frame from each column can have a different type.
The columns have names. We can have a row indexes.
It also gives us some additional data types, such as it has a categorical data type that NUM Pi does not natively support.
It provides additional date time capabilities, stats, models,
builds on top of Pan doesn't PSI Pi to give much more sophisticated statistical modeling capabilities?
There's overlap. There's some functions that appear both num pi and PSI, Pi, num pi and pandas, CI pilots, stats, models.
But that's, that's models builds on all of these to give us relatively sophisticated statistical modeling capabilities.
If you're coming from our stats models is where you're gonna find a lot of the linear models,
a lot of the hypothesis tests and things that you might be looking at looking for from R, then I'm plotting.
Matplotlib is the low level plotting library that most other, particularly static plotting infrastructure.
A python is built. It works directly with num pi seabourne builds on top of matplotlib.
It also uses side pi and pandas and stats models to draw some of its more sophisticated plots, but it pulls all of it together.
I'll let you do some of your data visualization. So if you need basic array functions, you're gonna get those from num pi.
You need to do more advanced things with a raise and some basic statistical functions.
Then you're gonna reach for PSI, Pi, PSI, Pious signal processing.
It's got a whole bunch of different things and it also has sparse matrices, which you're going to see later.
And it has a whole bunch of statistical distributions if you need to work with label data and basically
any of our any of our observation data that we're gonna be pulling in for our work in this class,