Hi, no slides this time. Want to talk to you for just a few minutes about where to learn more, so we've introduced a number of Python things.
We're going to see more python things. We've introduced some basic inferential techniques.
We're going to see more inferential techniques. We're going to see more techniques of other kinds.
But this class, I'm not certainly not able to cover everything you're going to ever need to know.
You're not going to cover everything you're ever going to need to know and a master's degree or an APHC.
So where do you go to learn more? One immediate thing is to take more classes for many of you.
This is your first class in a data science oriented master's or HD program.
You're going to take, say, the machine learning class in the spring.
You're going to take maybe natural language processing, maybe recommender systems.
Maybe you're going to take one of the information retrieval classes or social network analysis.
The variety of classes you can go take classes in mathematics and statistics and econometrics and the econ department.
You can go look for econometrics. There's a variety of classes that you can take that can help fill in some knowledge.
But beyond that, there's a lot you can do to study and learn more.
There's lots of books I'm referencing some in this class.
I'm going to be adding links to more as we go through the class further and get get to more techniques that are worth pointing you to a book for.
But also, some of the things that I do is, for one, I read a lot, particularly when I'm reading a lot of papers.
I read a lot of things on the Internet. And I pay attention to the statistical methods.
So I'm very active on Twitter, for example, and I follow a number of people who tweet about statistical methodology.
Some of them are very advanced and sophisticated statisticians, and I pay attention to what they have to say.
What are they saying about statistical methods? Oftentimes I need a lot more background to fully understand the argument that they're weighing in on.
But I'll see if it seems relevant to anything I'm working on and maybe go and get some of that background.
And so that's one sources is seeking out.
Blogs, social media feeds, etc, from people who are regularly posting information about statistical techniques or data science techniques.
You have to be careful. There's a lot of bad information out there. But there's a lot of quite good.
There's a lot of quite good and well-informed statisticians and data scientists who are posting things that you might want to pay attention to.
And some of them are also very, very funny. I also, as I'm reading research papers, I pay attention to their method.
Sometimes it's just to better understand the methods.
Sometimes a paper was going to have an interesting method that might be useful for me to add and adapt to my own research.
I also reflect on my processes as I'm working on a project.
They ask what's working, what's not? Where are the holes?
Whereas this project at the edge of my knowledge and I really need to understand something else to push it forward.
I pay attention when I'm at conferences to what methods do people seem to be applying?
What methods do I maybe need to add to my tool box?
Because people are getting a lot of value out of them and doing the kinds of research that I try to do.
I also spend time trying to understand my tools, reading the documentation for things like pandas and num pi, trying things out.
Oftentimes I'll spin up a notebook just to try something out, to see how it works and how it works in my data.
Looking at examples, I'm pretty opinionated in my programing, so there's a lot of examples I don't like,
but but looking at examples and trying to understand how other people did things and
why they did them that way and seeing what I can incorporate into my own process.
But a lot of it is practice. And also, I think as I'm working.
Is there a better way I can do this? Is there a way I can do this more efficiently?
Sometimes I don't care. Like, OK, that was fast enough. But paying attention to and reflecting on.
OK, how about how is this working? How am I actually doing?
This computation really goes a long ways towards identifying the places where I might need to go level up my skills.
So at the end of the day, what I do to keep learning more of this material is I pay attention to the work, both my work and the work of others.
Pay attention to the details. How are we getting these results?
What assumptions is this making? Are those assumptions valid? Can I apply this method in another technique, in another context?
It's question of all of that asking myself and then reflecting my own practice.
And as I'm working on a project. What am I happy about and how this project worked out?
What am I dissatisfied with?
What do I need to go learn in order to address the point of the project that this dissatisfied me and continually learn more things?
Spend time thinking, try the mountain new projects and building up my skills incrementally over time.