Hello. This week, we're going to talk more about regression. We introduced it when we started talking about two variables.
We'll be studying a lot more, how to use it and how to evaluate it. In this week's material,
so are learning outcomes are for you to be able to compute single and multivariable regressions to
test for violations of their assumptions and to assess the predictive accuracy of a regression model.
So if you'll remember, we have a dependent variable y called the outcome.
This case, if we're going to try to predict the Rotten Tomatoes audience rating with the critics rating,
the regression version of what you did in assignment to. We have our independent variables, X predictors.
In this case, the all critics rating, and our goal is to try to estimate compute an estimate which we call Y hat.
That'll be our standard notation for an estimate that tries to.
We try to estimate the audience rating using the critics rating.
And so we can learn a linear model, a line where we have an intercept. We have a slope.
And then we have some residuals. The goal is that we learn these parameters in order to minimize the least squares.
We're going to be talking more in subsequent videos about what precisely that means.
But this is the setup. We have this outcome and we want to try to predict it.
This is a very common setup and data science tasks. A lot of times what we're going to try to do is predict some outcome.
This is also a really common task in machine learning.
If you take the machine learning class in the spring, you'll be doing a lot of this.
So but talk about this. We're gonna be using the term model quite a bit.
What does that mean? Or model for our purposes? There's lots of different words in the model meetings, the word model.
It's a mathematical representation of the essential dynamics of a system of interest.
It's a simplification, but it captures the piece of the system that we're interested in measuring.
For example, if we. If critics are doing their job of assessing the quality of movie and in fact recommending effectively to audiences,
we would expect critic ratings to match audience or to map in some respect with audience ratings.
And so we can look at the relationship to model. It's a gross simplification.
We can look at the relationship to model. The pathways by which critic ratings and audience ratings might be related.
So there are several different purposes of modeling. One is to understand the relationships between our predictor and our outcome variables.
The model itself, these are correlational. They are not causal. You have to have great care when ascribing causality to what we learn.
But another purpose is to be able to predict future outcomes.
And this doesn't require the model to be causal or even to be what we call inferentially valid.
It just means there has to be a strong enough and reliable enough relationship that you can use it for the prediction.
You can also use it to estimate hypothetical other outcomes. You have to be careful with this.
But if you've got a model, you can use it to estimate, well, what would happen if the data were like this, but a little bit different.
And then you can also use them to estimate of the effect of something then you can correct for that effect in later analysis.
Regression is a type of modeling that predicts or estimates a continuous variable.
So you've got one or more. We have a continuous outcome variable and we have one or more.
We have one or more explanatory variables. Or features and that we're going to use them to predict that continuous outcome.
So a linear we're particularly focused here on linear models, so.
And because it's linear regression in a linear equation is a variable as an equation where you have a sum.
This whole thing is a sum of individual scalar multiplication. So X K times a constant.
X one times a constant. To be zero batur zero times one.
And so it's a linear model, is a linear equation, is the sum of these together multiples.
Linear models are incredibly capable. Useful for a wide range of things.
And also, we can transform many nonlinear problems into a linear problem.
Either transform our features and now the problem's linear, transform our outcomes and other problems, linear viotti of techniques for doing that.
So for a large range of problems, linear models are very good first thing to try.
And there's also a very good baseline comparison for more sophisticated models.
So we're gonna be learning this week about linear regression models were then later in later weeks, we're going to see linear classification models.
So to wrap up models, summarize data generating processes and let us predict future outcomes, given that we might not have observed yet.
And linear models are particularly simple but flexible class of models that we're going to be spending time with over the next weeks.