Blow, the previous video introduced the idea of modeling, and in this video, we're going to talk more about it.
So the on the learning outcome is to understand the relationship of models to reality.
And here we're not talking about walking down runways, wearing various articles of fabric, created things that make ordinary people say,
how much do they have to pay you for you to put that on and pretend it was clothes or building ships and airplanes and various other things?
We're going be talking primarily about statistical models.
So as I said in the previous video, a model is a mathematical representation of the essential dynamics of a system of interest.
But we have ours. We have our.
If we think about our data pipeline and our data generating process, we have some things that are out there happening in the world.
These give rise to either some observable phenomenon or an experiment that we can run that will elucidate.
These are observable phenomenon. We then collect data from these that are going to be our raw data.
What are our observations either from the experiment or observations collected from
the phenomena that then we process into a data set that's useful for our task?
We have inferences and then finally we hopefully get some answers. But we can think about this top piece here as this is our data generating process.
The D. G. P. How did our raw data come into existence?
Things happened that were observable phenomena. We collected the data. How did that happen?
So in statistical modeling, we simplify the data generating process to be able to predict an outcome.
There's two, broadly speaking, two kinds of models that we can think about.
Correlational models, look at relationships between observables and so in our movie data.
If we want to keep using the movie data as an example, you've got critic.
And you've got the audience.
And we can look at correlation between what the critic thinks and what the audience thinks or what the critic thinks and how much.
Our. Box office revenue or our.
How many people are rating the movie? But it doesn't make a causal claim.
We don't have this causal claim that the critic rating causes the audience.
It's just that the critic rating and the audience are related. There may be a little causation, but we're not making a causal claim here.
A causal model models the DGP more deeply to estimate causality.
You have to be really careful with these. There's an entire field called called causal inference that it's looking at.
How do you rigorously do this when you can't run an experiment? The best way is when you can run an experiment, if you can run an experiment.
You can often get causality through what's called a randomized controlled trial.
If you're able to set up an experiment where you've got a group that a group that receives the treatment, you call it a treatment,
the treatment you want to test and a group that doesn't and they aren't all other way, all other ways equal.
Randomization is a good way to achieve that. Then you can conclude that your intervention or your treatment caused the outcome.
But. Randomized controlled trials. Are expensive and often oftentimes they're not very.
They're not even possible to run feasibly due to the nature of the phenomenon or
due to the do the nature of the phenomenon or due to the non replicability of it,
which is a part of the nature. So you can't it's difficult to do randomized controlled trials, say, of national or even state level health policies.
You can do some state level thing by comparing one state to another. But but if you've got like there's only one United States of America.
So you can't you can't say, well, what happens in the US with one policy and without one policy because or replicates of the United States.
Cause you don't really you can't duplicated or even more so the world.
But there are ways and there are two contexts and times in which you can infer causality from observables and causal inference.
Is the study of that. So the model necessarily simplifies the problem, we isolate the pieces we care about,
we might need to have some other pieces involved in order to to what we call control for other effects.
But. The simplified model, hopefully capture like the goal is not to completely represent the underlying reality.
The goal is to capture enough that we can predict or infer usefully.
And then we have the unpredicted value, which is what we call the residual or the error.
And so if we think about our movies. Movie. Movie. Example. The movie data.
And again, maybe we think about the genres. So a movie exists and it has some genres.
And it's in some genres. And we have a difference.
And it also gets reviews and. The genres might cause some of the reviewing behavior,
but they're probably both caused by the movie itself and the movie is a Western and the movie gets them reviews.
And so we can look at the correlation withdrawn under to see if there's a difference.
But that's not the same thing as claiming the genre causes the review difference.
What we need to go more deeply is to understand what causes the movie to be in a particular genre.
Now, when we're modeling, we're also going to be talking about what we call parameters.
And we've introduced parameters before in the statistical sense,
in modeling a model parameter is a numeric variable as a part of the model, in a linear model, they're going to be our coefficients.
We estimate these parameters from the data. And for example, in the before, we might estimate the mean credit rating for each genre.
We then have a little challenge of how do we handle multiple Shomrim membership's?
But if the model if the model captures the data generating process and it's an
accurate reflection of a simplified version of the data generating process,
then the model parameters will hopefully also correspond to underlying population parameters.
We don't necessarily get that guarantee, but the goal of a good model for inferential purposes is to get these correspondences
to underlying population parameters to describe how the mechanism works on the inside.
So for an example that adapted from Wikipedia. Children grow as they age and older children.
Therefore we're gonna. If one child is older than another, we expect it to probably be taller.
There's a lot of variation. There's a lot of variation in the height of five year olds.
But if we randomly pick a five year old and a six year old, we probably expect the six year old to be a little taller.
And so we can model this as modeling height as a base offset plus a multiplier of the age.
And this isn't perfect. I get it. As I said, there's a lot of variation in the heights of five year olds, but it's a starting point for prediction.
And the residual is what the model can't account for.
And we model these as we model the residuals as random.
That doesn't mean they are random. But we can treat these unknowns as a random variable.
And so we we treat these these residuals as a random variable.
We're going to have random variable ways of dealing with them. But this is is what we get when we have a model.
Older children are taller. So we can try to predict it a child's height with their age.
And then we have this leftover that we can't predict with the age.
There may well be other things that we could throw in that would allow us to predict that. But we can't predict it with age.
So to conclude, models simplify a process so we can understand at least pieces of it and predict them.
They're simplifications, but they're related to the data generating process that we can try to learn about what is actually happening.
That's giving rise to the data that we see so we can use the data to learn about the world.