For this video, we're going to talk about prediction and inference,
learning outcomes for you to be able to distinguish between prediction and inference and understand different meanings of the word inference.
We've talked about prediction and inference a little bit before. I talked about inferential validity.
This video, I'm going to talk more about what we mean by these concepts.
So in prediction, we're trying to predict other values from the model with our penguins.
We might be able to we might be looking at, OK. That can I predict.
If I get a if I if you give me the flipper length of a penguin in the future, can I accurately predict its bodyweight for our movies?
If you give me some critic ratings, I predict its audience response.
Or can I predict its box office? Proceeds. Porten thing about prediction is that models don't need to be inferentially valid.
And the quality and strength we estimate the quality and strength of the prediction by actually trying to use it to predict data.
We haven't allowed it to seen to see. It's important to note the evaluation of the prediction.
Accuracy does need to be statistically valid. Inference uses the models, structure and parameters to learn about the world.
So we might want to learn about fundamental relationships, about penguin physiology.
Its validity depends on assumptions that we introduced last week or in the last video,
we talked about single very regressions and then we have various measures of its quality and strength.
R squared is how much variance that explains P value is statistical significance.
We're going to have checks for its various assumptions and we've got the coefficients which look at the strength of the relationship.
So what we're trying to do inference we can make a statement of credit rating increases
as the critic rating in crace of one point increases audience ready by point one.
There'll be an inferential statement. It's making a claim about the relationship of these things.
And we measure this with we've got our squared, as we saw in the last video of point three nine four.
We've got a very small P value and we assume that it's a linear relationship.
We assume that our observations are independent.
That we've got these normal residuals and also that the residuals have equal variance or what we call Hommel Skip Mastec.
I'm never not going to think that homo scare tactic and it's opposite hetero skin mastic are very strange words.
So that's an inferential kind of claim. We're claiming a relationship and not necessarily causal.
But we're claiming this correlational relationship prediction looks really similar.
We can predict audience ratings using the model to point to eight plus one point one eight.
Our top. And we measure this by saying, oh, what's mean absolute error?
So if we take the the errors, those Epsilon's residuals,
we take the absolute value and take the average is two point is point to eight six or the root mean squared errors
point three five nine root means squared error is a very common measurement to the accuracy of a predictive model.
And we're not making any assumptions.
We don't even have to assume linearity. We can for this to be a useful predictor, it'll hopefully be a better predictor if we if it's actually linear.
But if if all we care about is how accurate it is at predicting, then.
We don't have to worry about all of our influence, inferential validity assumptions,
but we also have to be very, very careful about the claims we make.
We can claim it's useful for predicting, but we can't, from an invalid model, make claims about the underlying phenomenon that we care about.
It does make the assumption that we have tested it on data that were not available for training.
So what does that mean? So in a machine, what we call it, a machine learning setting.
We often have what we call a trained test split. And so we take our input data.
And we split it into two pieces. This is our input.
We say 80 percent of the data. 80 percent of comment split goes into our training pool and 10 percent.
Goes into our testing pool. We then fit our linear regression or whatever other model we're doing.
We fit or train at. On the training data, it does not get to see the test data.
So we're letting your model does not include the test data in the fitting process.
And then we ask the model to predict the test outcomes using the test features.
And what this does is it tests. It's easy to predict data data.
I've seen. I just memorize all the data. I've seen it test, though.
Can I learn a relationship from training data that generalizes to data that was not in the training data?
And we called particularly we call the kind of learning that we're doing this week supervised learning because we have a thing,
this continuous outcome variable that we're trying to predict. It's also important, though, to split before the exploratory analysis of features.
I'm going to be talking more about train test splits in a later video dedicated to experimental setup.
But this is the basic idea of how we how we set up data to be able to test predictive accuracy because we don't want to be able.
We don't want to test the model's memory. We want to test its ability to predict things that's never seen before.
We need to split, as I said before, exploratory analysis,
because we don't want knowledge of the distribution of our data and our tests of our variables
in our test data to affect our choice of variables in the model development process.
And if we're going to be, say, trying different features,
trying different variants of a model before we settle on the final one, we actually need to split into three partitions.
We have our training data. We have tuning for optimizing the model, testing the predictive accuracy of different candidates,
and then we have a test data that's saved for our final validation.
Again, we're gonna be talking more in detail about why each of these splits is necessary in a later video.
But I also said that I want you to understand different uses that determine for it.
So here we're using the word inference to talk about the use of a data analysis of the
use of a statistical model to understand or infer things about the underlying world.
So we're trying to understand how movie preference works.
We're trying to understand penguin physiology or we're trying to understand the hydrodynamics of.
Of a river or of an a quarter of a marine processing plant.
And we're trying to use the data we collected and the statistical models and
analysis that we do of it to draw conclusions about the underlying real world.
There's some other uses of inference, though, particularly one that comes up in data science,
in machine learning is sometimes when we have a model we've trained.
It's we've take her. We fit our linear regression. And we're using it to make predictions for additional for new data points.
Like maybe you've you've trained up a statistical model that estimates the likelihood that a particular transaction is fraudulent.
Now you're using that model as transactions are coming in to your online shopping portal and to determine how likely they are to be fraudulent.
Sometimes that last stage is called in France,
especially in the deep learning literature on some other machine learning literature is that that's the first stage of the model training stage.
And the inference stage is if you actually go use the model to make inferences about new new data points that are coming in.
So to sum up, inference uses a model structure and parameters to try to understand things about the world and draw generalizable knowledge.
Prediction just uses a model to predict future observations,
particularly though inference has stronger requirements for its validity than the usefulness of prediction.
It is important to note, though, that just because you can yolo the statistics inside a predictor if all you care about is its predictive accuracy,
you have to pay attention to the validity of the statistics you use to test if the predictor is actually a better predictor than something else.
You can't cheat on those, but if your only goal is predictive accuracy,
the linear model you're using for it doesn't need to need to meet all the requirements that it needs to meet.
If you're trying to use it for inference.