This video, I want to talk about how to use categorical variables as predictors in our linear models,
learning outcomes are for you to be able to use a categorical predictor and understand what dummy coding is and why we use it.
Categorical variables, if you'll recall from earlier in the class or unordered discrete,
the variables that take on an unordered set of discrete values that are called levels.
And one of the things about these is we can't do arithmetic. You can't say like Gentoo Penguin Times three.
That's not a meaningful concept to talk about.
And even when we're using integers to encode our categorical variables, for example, a movie idee or just any kind of an I.D.,
we can't use those as model predictors because then they don't have numeric meaning.
It doesn't mean anything to multiply a movie idea by a coefficient.
And so we need another way to encode categorical variables if we're going to use them in our linear models.
And the solution is something called dummy coding. So what we do is we convert each level into a diff separate integer column.
So our penguin's dataset has three different penguin species, Adelie chinstrap and Gentoo.
And each of those becomes a column.
The pandas get dummy's function will get will convert Assiri a categorical series into a data frame of Dumi coded values.
And so this will give us the. So give us the dummy codings for the penguins.
And we have a we have one for each for each species.
This is also called one coding. Particularly when we're doing this, we have one for every level.
It's call we. It's one hot coding or dumi coding.
Another way that we can have a one where we have a one in the Adelie caller.
If that penguin is in a deli and we're gonna have a zero everywhere else because we only have one value of the categorical variable perone.
Often, though, we need to drop one of the categorical or one of the variables.
Typically the first one and we do this with the drop first option to get dummies.
And the Adelie column now, you'll see, is gone. We just have chinstrap and Gentoo.
And what how it's encoded is at a deli.
Penguin is all zeroes, but it chinstrap Penguin will have a one in the chinstrap column in a agentive will have a one in the Gentoo column.
This is going to be particularly useful for linear regression because if we have all of the levels,
we're going to have problems of fitting our linear regression models. If we just have we have all but one of them,
then effectively we're treating one of the levels as the default and the other levels are getting the code for what
happens when your when it's one of the other values instead of the first or the default value that you chose.
So the results of this are that the category of calls are encoded as numeric variables that we can then use in models.
We can multiply that, my coefficients, et cetera. We're going to see that in a model coming up.
Wrap up to use categorically in our linear models or other Neumar models, or we're going to need to do numeric computations on a categorical value.
We need to encode them numerically dummy coding.
Let's do this by converting each level into a zero one variable that indicates whether or not the observation has that value of the variable.
And often we drop one so that four end levels we have N minus one dummy variables and all zero is the.