Hello. And this video, I want to talk about how to test the assumptions that we make in a linear model.
So we're going to review the linear assumptions. And I want you to be able to identify violations of these assumptions,
particularly with regards the assumptions about how variables are distribute residuals are distributed.
So to review the assumptions that a linear model makes are first, that it is linear.
The outcome of the outcome and the predictor have a linear relationship.
The next assumption is that we are our observations are independent of each other.
And then that the of the residuals are normally distributed and have equal variance.
We call equal variance. Homos get asked to study same variance across the range of fitted values.
A violation of the equal variance condition is called hetero US city.
Or we say that the residuals are hetero scholastic.
The last three of these are supposed to result in independent and identically distributed normal residuals.
So let's start with linearity. This is the fundamental assumption of a linear model.
We wouldn't run a linear model if we didn't think that there was a linear relationship to study.
And so if we want to check this what we are or see whether a linear model is even going to be reasonable to try.
What we can do is we can do a scatterplot with quite possibly the regression line to see that seems to fit.
And that looks vaguely linear ish. Independence is difficult to check.
It's a property of data collection. We don't have tests or plots to say this is independent.
There are ways certain violations of it will manifest when we go and we plot the results of training a linear model.
But common ways that it's violated or if we've got time series.
If you're collecting data over time, it's often what we call auto correlated, which means one day is correlated with the day before.
They're not independent.
If you've got data that comes in groups or comes from common environments, for example, if you've got data on patients from five different hospitals,
patients within a hospital are going to be correlated because that hospital has its own practice, its own doctors, et cetera.
Also, if you've got multiple measurements for repeated individuals, that is another example of non independence.
For example, this is what came up when we were working with the paired t test or its related bootstrap tests,
where you have two observations and there say you've got the midterms and the mid be from the same student.
They're not independent of each other because a student who's doing well in the class is probably going to do well in both midterms.
And that violates the independence, the independence. That that violates the independence of those two variables.
We have the student linked, but if we've got.
But the students just going to show up as one row in our list of observations that are trained and linear model from.
But if we have students showing up as multiple rows, for example, the ratings that a user gives to books or movies,
the ratings by the same user are not fully independent of each other.
The solutions to this are out of scope for this week for sure.
But they involve correlated error models, sometimes hierarchical models or mixed effects models to be able to deal with the
kinds of grouping dynamics that can cause some of the independents violations. But then the nor the errors are supposed to be normally distributed.
And so the way we do this is we do a Q Q plot of the residuals.
When you fit a linear model, the resulting object gives you access to the residuals.
This plot was generated by the notebook that I've linked to in the in the weeks content information.
So you can go see the code that I used to generate this residual plot from from a linear model fit.
But you get a Q Q plot of residuals. And this looks pretty good. We've got and the the values are pretty much tracking with the pretty straight line
right along there of a violation of normality means we still have a line that fits,
but our P values and our confidence intervals are gonna be unreliable. We have to be careful using the line for using the model for inference.
And it's not these these assumptions are not all or nothing. The data often aren't perfectly normal, but they're pretty close.
Also then the next one. The last one is the equal variance of errors or homeless get as density.
And so the residuals are supposed to have constant variance.
And the way we check this is we make a scatterplot where the Y axis are the predicted or fitted values.
So this is the results of our linear regression, linear regression.
And the that's the x axis, the y axis is the residuals, so this is our EP.
So this is our Y hats. And this is our epsilons.
And this lets us see if there are what we're looking for is no patterns, no visible patterns, particularly in the Y axis.
We might have patterns in the X axis just because there are.
If there's a categorical variable involved, then the predicted values, the fitted values are going to fall into some chunks.
But we don't want is any patterns in the Y axis in response to those.
This looks pretty much like noise. A couple of these have higher ones.
Another one has lower. But, you know, you expect an outlier or two here and there.
The main body of these is pretty much the same width all the way across.
There aren't bands or other patterns that look or we aren't seeing a particular shift, which isn't necessarily a violation of the variance thing.
What we want. We don't want to see angular shifts in our residuals either violation of this.
So if we see distinct patterns, what in this plot?
What that means is that the model is failing to capture a systemic effect because there is a systematic error when you predict low the variance.
The residuals do something different than when you predict high,
which indicates there's a important feature that's not being taking a taking care of in the model or taking a cap
taken account for in the model that is affecting the relationship of your prediction to the actual resulting value.
Remember, Epsilon is Y. So the the the error epsilon.
Equals Y. The actual value outcome, variable minus Y hat.
Our estimated outcome variable from the linear regression. So where we can see some violations of this.
So this. This variable or so these residuals from another linear model, they have just a little bit more curve.
To the residuals than we would like to see, they're pretty close to normal.
But there's a little more curve indicating that the tails aren't quite fitting, the normal distribution.
But also, if we look at the residual versus fitted plot, we see kind of this funnel shape.
So for high fitted values, the variance of the residuals is much higher than for low fat values.
And that's that looks like a larger change and variance than can be explained just by the occasional outlier.
So we're going to say that these residuals are exhibiting hetero sked activity and therefore we're not going to trust the model that these came from.
So what do you do if you're doing just doing prediction.
If your own goal is to predict an outcome, then it might not matter because these assumptions, violations, they're a problem for.
They're a problem for in France. Not necessarily for prediction.
You still want to check your prediction and also check the distribution of your prediction errors.
It might be that it's mostly doing a pretty good job. But when you get to some edge cases, it pretty egregiously fails you.
You might just not be able to make a linear model work.
You might need to add or remove or transform some of your predictors or possibly transform the outcome, like take a log, take a square root.
Do some more feature engineering in order to get features that are going to produce a better a better model.
You might need to go to some non parametric techniques, such as boot straps.
There's a thing called a non parametric regression that we're not going to have time to get to.
But you can go. You can go study that if it might be useful for your problem.
Sometimes hierarchical or mixed effects models are going to take care of some of the additional effects that are causing your assumption violations,
particularly independents. But they can help in some other cases as well.
So to wrap up linear models, make four key assumptions that are necessary for inferences from them to be valid.
These assumptions aren't all or nothing. There's not a binary. It is or it isn't.
It's a judgment call that comes in part from experience and careful study of whether it's a violation is too strong and then plotting the plotting,
the residuals, both plotting a coocoo plot. We can test their normality and plotting the residuals versus the predicted values.
Allow us to detect violations of some of these assumptions and check the validity of our inferences.