This video, we're going to talk about how to compute prediction accuracy,
I gave you a couple examples back in the prediction inference video, but we're going to see here how to actually do it.
So we're going to compute the accuracy of our regressions predictions and understand the benefits of animacy over MAIG.
The code for this, you're going to find in the updated version of the correlation notebook from the tutorial section.
I've also linked to it in the in the resources links in this in this week's material.
So remember, Prediction tries to predict the future with the model.
And we don't actually care about how well the models, internal structures map to real world structures.
Acceptance, so far as we might hope that a model that's more directly connected to reality does a better job of prediction.
That hope doesn't always hold true. But the way we test the prediction accuracy is through a train test split.
So we so we take our data. We split it into two parts. We've got the train part.
We've got the test part. We're going to fit the model on the training data.
And there are one to ask it to predict the test data and see how well it does.
So to do the split we can do is if we've got a data frame,
I've got a data frame predictable that has the values and I've pruned out all of the ones where the predictor won't work.
So one of the predictors is that a or the outcome is N.A because we just can't predict those with with a linear model.
So I create a test sample. So I use the sample method on the data frame object.
So this is a D.F. Use the sample method on the data frame object, and I tell it, I want a fraction of a point too.
This is gonna pick 20 percent of the data. He uses test data. So now I've got this test data and it keeps the index from the predictable.
So even if it's just arranged next. Now, test has the values from that index that that correspond to the rows.
It doesn't change the indexes of your rows.
So what I can do then to get the training data, I'm the training data should be everything that's not in the test data.
So I'm going create as a mask. I don't use the mask as a name for a boolean value that's going to select Rose and I initialize it.
I said it was a serious and I initialize it to true to say, yeah, we want the value and I give it an index.
That's the same index as our original data frame. So it starts out saying we want to select every row.
And then what I do is I set the. So I use the test index to select items in here.
And I set the values where I set the values of the match.
I set the mask to false everywhere.
We picked a test row. You can also use dot lock here. I'm not it's a shortcut, but you can use dot lock there if you feel that's clearer.
And then with this mask, I get our training data by asking the training,
the predictable by passing the train mask is a logical series to index into predictable.
And that's going to give me my training data. So compute your test sample.
Create a mask. That's true. Set it false. Everywhere you pick the test row.
And then if you pick the remaining truths, you get all of the other data. And that's going to be our training data.
So then we fit the model on trains. We set up our oh well, if we're using it as well as we set up our lesson train, we we call fit.
It's going to give us a fit object. Then we call predict.
We call it predict method. So a fit object from a stat's model's model has a method called predict,
which we give in another set of data, and it's going to try to predict the outcomes for it.
So we ask it to predict our test data and then we compare the predictions to the test outcomes.
Now, something that I haven't quite specifically talked about yet is when we're when we're running code.
We have a model. And so we're gonna say model. Equals.
Oh, alas, we're going to our formula. And we also give it our data off.
And then we get fit equals model dot fit.
That's the stats model's pattern to the model itself, has the data, the the the the setup, the model that we're gonna be fitting.
And then when we actually fit the model, we get another object that has the parameters that are result of fitting the model.
No, if you've used Saikat learn before, we're going to be using Saikat learned later.
This is a different setup. Stats Models uses a little bit different pattern than Saikat learned does it has these separate model and fit objects.
But the fit object allows us to compute predictions for the test values that we can then compare to our test outcomes.
One way to compare them is by taking the mean absolute error. So we take the absolute values of our errors.
And then we take the mean of them,
we sum them up and we divide them by and I'm going to let you think a little bit about why we don't want to take the mean error.
I will note that the mean of our residuals, if we've properly Fedeli Squares module model, the mean of our residuals is zero.
So the root mean squared error squares, the individual errors rather than computing and absolute value, we compute the square.
We then take their mean and we take the square root of all of that. The square root puts it back in units of the original of the original values.
This. So why do we do the root mean square or.
So to see how to compute the root mean squared error, I have broken it down and I've ever written the code here.
So if we've got our outcome, if we have a variable called outcome in our test frame,
we subtract the predictions from the outcome and that computes Y minus Y hat.
And I've color coded the code to match the part of the formula.
We then take the square, we multiply the error by itself and that's going to compute the squares.
We then take the mean of all of that. And that's one that's the sometimes one minus enter the sum divided by the count.
And then finally, we take the square root. And you can see here, especially as you move past being able to use existing models,
you're going to need to be able to implement formulas in terms of num pi or PSI Pi or pandas.
And you've done that some already. But this, I hope, helps you see.
How do you take a formula like we can write out,
like our messy and you can break it down into the different num pi operations that you're going to need to perform in order to compute the formula.
So now why do we use are messy instead of energy? One is that it gives higher weight to larger errors.
So one is less than two point one is less than two point one squared is much less than two squared.
Also, though, and this is particularly important, is that it's continuous and differentiable the absolute value.
If we have X and we have Y, the absolute value is discontinuous at zero.
You can't take its derivative. You can take the derivative of the square and for a lot of optimization techniques in
order to learn models that are going to fit well and are going to have low error,
they rely on the differential ability of the errors. And so are messy.
Gives us an error metric that has a derivative.
So to interpret the prediction accuracy, both of these metrics are their units are in the original outcome variable.
But what is good enough depends on your application. How good do you actually need to be for the purposes you're deploying the model for?
Also there for a lot of problem, for a lot of cases.
There's a minimum possible error just due to the intrinsic variance of the data and the intrinsic noise of the data.
You can't predict. Well, you can maybe try to predict noise.
But if you've got part of the data that is just random noise of random variation that
puts a floor on how low your prediction accurate your prediction error can get.
But with equivalent test data, we can use MAIG in our messy to compare the prediction of effectiveness of multiple different models.
And that's where they really become useful as they allow us to say,
is this model better than our current model or better than some simple baseline model?
The linear models that we're seeing, like they're going to be really hot that we're using this week.
They're really powerful in their own right. They're also a really good baseline if you are using some more sophisticated model.
It's useful to include a linear model and the see. Can you beat a linear model? If not, maybe use the linear one.
So to wrap up, we measure of predictors, accuracy by comparing predictions to the actual outcome variables on test data.
And it's important that the test data was not seen during the fitting process.